<article xmlns:ns0="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ns1="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.1d3" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS Genet</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosgen</journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>PLOS Genetics</journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1553-7390</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1553-7404</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>San Francisco, CA USA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1008389</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PGENETICS-D-19-00916</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Research Article</subject>
</subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Biology and life sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Biochemistry</subject><subj-group><subject>Proteins</subject><subj-group><subject>Protein complexes</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Biology and life sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Genetics</subject><subj-group><subject>Gene expression</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Biology and life sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Genetics</subject><subj-group><subject>Heredity</subject><subj-group><subject>Genetic mapping</subject><subj-group><subject>Linkage analysis</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Biology and life sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Cell biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Chromosome biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Chromatin</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Biology and life sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Genetics</subject><subj-group><subject>Epigenetics</subject><subj-group><subject>Chromatin</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Biology and life sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Genetics</subject><subj-group><subject>Gene expression</subject><subj-group><subject>Chromatin</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Biology and life sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Genetics</subject><subj-group><subject>Genomics</subject><subj-group><subject>Animal genomics</subject><subj-group><subject>Mammalian genomics</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Biology and life sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Genetics</subject><subj-group><subject>Genetic loci</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Biology and life sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Cell biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Chromosome biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Chromosomes</subject><subj-group><subject>Autosomes</subject><subj-group><subject>Chromosome pairs</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Biology and life sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Cell biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Chromosome biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Chromosomes</subject><subj-group><subject>Chromosome pairs</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Biology and life sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Biochemistry</subject><subj-group><subject>Proteins</subject><subj-group><subject>DNA-binding proteins</subject><subj-group><subject>Histones</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Chromosome-wide co-fluctuation of stochastic gene expression in mammalian cells</article-title>
<alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Expression co-fluctuation of linked genes</alt-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" ns0:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Sun</surname>
<given-names>Mengyi</given-names>
</name>
<role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Data curation</role>
<role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Formal analysis</role>
<role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Investigation</role>
<role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Methodology</role>
<role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Writing &#8211; original draft</role>
<role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Writing &#8211; review &amp; editing</role>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001" />
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" ns0:type="simple">
<contrib-id authenticated="true" contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-6141-1290</contrib-id>
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>Jianzhi</given-names>
</name>
<role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Conceptualization</role>
<role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Funding acquisition</role>
<role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Project administration</role>
<role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Resources</role>
<role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Supervision</role>
<role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Writing &#8211; original draft</role>
<role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Writing &#8211; review &amp; editing</role>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor001">*</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001" />
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff001"><addr-line>Department of Ecology and Evolutionary Biology, University of Michigan, Ann Arbor, MI, United States of America</addr-line></aff>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="editor" ns0:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Bai</surname>
<given-names>Lu</given-names>
</name>
<role>Editor</role>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1" />
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="edit1"><addr-line>Penn State University, UNITED STATES</addr-line></aff>
<author-notes>
<fn fn-type="conflict" id="coi001">
<p>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p>
</fn>
<corresp id="cor001">* E-mail: <email ns0:type="simple">jianzhi@umich.edu</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub">
<day>16</day>
<month>9</month>
<year>2019</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="collection">
<month>9</month>
<year>2019</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>15</volume>
<issue>9</issue>
<elocation-id>e1008389</elocation-id>
<history>
<date date-type="received">
<day>6</day>
<month>6</month>
<year>2019</year>
</date>
<date date-type="accepted">
<day>28</day>
<month>8</month>
<year>2019</year>
</date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-year>2019</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>Sun, Zhang</copyright-holder>
<license ns0:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" ns0:type="simple">
<license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" ns0:type="simple">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<self-uri content-type="pdf" ns0:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1008389" />
<abstract>
<p>Gene expression is subject to stochastic noise, but to what extent and by which means such stochastic variations are coordinated among different genes are unclear. We hypothesize that neighboring genes on the same chromosome co-fluctuate in expression because of their common chromatin dynamics, and verify it at the genomic scale using allele-specific single-cell RNA-sequencing data of mouse cells. Unexpectedly, the co-fluctuation extends to genes that are over 60 million bases apart. We provide evidence that this long-range effect arises in part from chromatin co-accessibilities of linked loci attributable to three-dimensional proximity, which is much closer intra-chromosomally than inter-chromosomally. We further show that genes encoding components of the same protein complex tend to be chromosomally linked, likely resulting from natural selection for intracellular among-component dosage balance. These findings have implications for both the evolution of genome organization and optimal design of synthetic genomes in the face of gene expression noise.</p>
</abstract>
<abstract abstract-type="summary">
<title>Author summary</title>
<p>Gene expression is subject to substantial stochastic noise or fluctuation. We hypothesize that expressions of neighboring genes on the same chromosome co-fluctuate because of their common chromatin dynamics. To test this hypothesis, we make use of the fact that each diploid cell contains a maternal and a paternal copy of the same chromosome that are differentiable by their DNA sequences. Hence, allele-specific single-cell RNA-sequencing can quantify the expression level of each allele in individual diploid cells, allowing measuring the expression co-fluctuation of linked alleles as well as that of unlinked alleles of the same genes. Using such data from mouse cells, we discover chromosome-wide gene expression co-fluctuation and provide evidence that this long-range effect arises in part from chromatin co-accessibilities of linked loci attributable to three-dimensional proximity. We show that genes encoding protein complex subunits tend to be chromosomally linked, likely resulting from natural selection for intracellular among-component dosage balance. Thus, minimization of the deleterious effect of gene expression noise has probably produced a nonrandom distribution of genes in the genome. These findings have implications for the evolution of genome organization and optimal design of synthetic genomes.</p>
</abstract>
<funding-group>
<award-group id="award001">
<funding-source>
<institution>National Institutes of Health</institution>
</funding-source>
<award-id>GM120093</award-id>
<principal-award-recipient>
<contrib-id authenticated="true" contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-6141-1290</contrib-id>
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>Jianzhi</given-names>
</name>
</principal-award-recipient>
</award-group>
<funding-statement>This work was supported by U.S. National Institutes of Health research grant GM120093 to J.Z. The funder had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement>
</funding-group>
<counts>
<fig-count count="4" />
<table-count count="0" />
<page-count count="30" />
</counts>
<custom-meta-group>
<custom-meta>
<meta-name>PLOS Publication Stage</meta-name>
<meta-value>vor-update-to-uncorrected-proof</meta-value>
</custom-meta>
<custom-meta>
<meta-name>Publication Update</meta-name>
<meta-value>2019-09-26</meta-value>
</custom-meta>
<custom-meta id="data-availability">
<meta-name>Data Availability</meta-name>
<meta-value>Software used and the underlying numerical data for all figures can be downloaded from Github (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://github.com/mengysun/Linked_noise" ns0:type="simple">https://github.com/mengysun/Linked_noise</ext-link>).</meta-value>
</custom-meta>
</custom-meta-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="sec001" sec-type="intro">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>Gene expression is subject to considerable stochasticity that is known as expression noise, formally defined as the expression variation of a given gene among isogenic cells in the same environment [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1008389.ref001">1</xref>&#8211;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1008389.ref003">3</xref>]. Gene expression noise is a double-edged sword. On the one hand, it can be deleterious because it leads to imprecise controls of cellular behavior, including, for example, destroying the stoichiometric relationship among functionally related proteins and disrupting homeostasis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1008389.ref004">4</xref>&#8211;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1008389.ref008">8</xref>]. On the other hand, gene expression noise can be beneficial. For instance, unicellular organisms may exploit gene expression noise to employ bet-hedging strategies in fluctuating environments [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1008389.ref009">9</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1008389.ref010">10</xref>], whereas multicellular organisms can make use of expression noise to initiate developmental processes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1008389.ref011">11</xref>&#8211;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1008389.ref013">13</xref>].</p>
<p>By quantifying protein concentrations in individual isogenic cells cultured in a common environment, researchers have measured the expression noise for thousands of genes in the bacterium <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1008389.ref014">14</xref>] and unicellular eukaryote <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1008389.ref015">15</xref>]. Nevertheless, because genes are not in isolation, one wonders whether and to what extent expression levels co-vary among genes at a steady state, which unfortunately cannot be studied by the above data. By simultaneously tagging two genes with different florescent markers, Stewart-Ornstein et al. discovered strong co-fluctuation of the concentrations of some functionally related proteins in yeast such as those involved in the Msn2/4 stress response pathway, amino acid synthesis, and mitochondrial maintenance, respectively [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1008389.ref016">16</xref>], and the expression co-fluctuation of these genes is facilitated by their sharing of transcriptional regulators [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1008389.ref017">17</xref>].</p>
<p>Here we explore yet another mechanism for expression co-fluctuation. We hypothesize that, due to the sharing of chromatin dynamics [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1008389.ref018">18</xref>], a key contributor to gene expression noise [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1008389.ref018">18</xref>&#8211;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1008389.ref020">20</xref>], genes that are closely linked on the same chromosome should exhibit a stronger expression co-fluctuation when compared with genes that are not closely linked or unlinked (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen.1008389.g001">Fig 1</xref>). We refer to this potential influence of chromosomal linkage of two genes on their expression co-fluctuation as the linkage effect. The linkage-effect hypothesis is supported by two pioneering studies demonstrating that the correlation in expression level between two reporter genes across isogeneic cells in the same environment is much higher when they are placed next to each other on the same chromosome than when they are placed on separate chromosomes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1008389.ref021">21</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1008389.ref022">22</xref>]. However, neither the generality of the linkage effect nor the chromosomal proximity required for this effect are known. Furthermore, the biological significance of the linkage effect and its potential impact on genome organization and evolution have not been investigated. In this study, we address these questions by analyzing allele-specific single-cell RNA-sequencing (RNA-seq) data from mouse cells [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1008389.ref023">23</xref>]. We demonstrate that the linkage effect is not only general but also long-range, extending to genes that are tens of millions of bases apart. We provide evidence that three-dimensional (3D) chromatin proximities are responsible for the long-range expression co-fluctuation through mediating chromatin accessibility covariations. Finally, we show theoretically and empirically that the linkage effect has likely impacted the evolution of the chromosomal locations of genes encoding members of the same protein complex.</p>
<fig id="pgen.1008389.g001" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1008389.g001</object-id>
<label>Fig 1</label>
<caption>
<title>The hypothesized linkage effect on gene expression co-fluctuation.</title>
<p>The cellular mRNA concentrations of two genes should be better correlated among isogenic cells in a population under a constant environment (A) when the two genes are chromosomally linked than (B) when they are unlinked. In the dot plot, each dot represents a cell.</p>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" position="float" ns0:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1008389.g001" ns0:type="simple" />
</fig>
</sec>
<sec id="sec002" sec-type="results">
<title>Results</title>
<sec id="sec003">
<title>Linkage effect on gene expression co-fluctuation is general and long-range</title>
<p>Let us consider two genes <italic>A</italic> and <italic>B</italic> each with two alleles respectively named 1 and 2 in a diploid cell. When <italic>A</italic> and <italic>B</italic> are chromosomally linked, without loss of generality, we assume that <italic>A</italic><sub>1</sub> and <italic>B</italic><sub>1</sub> are on the same chromosome whereas <italic>A</italic><sub>2</sub> and <italic>B</italic><sub>2</sub> are on its homologous chromosome (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen.1008389.g002">Fig 2A</xref>). Expression co-fluctuation between one allele of <italic>A</italic> and one allele of <italic>B</italic> (e.g., <italic>A</italic><sub>1</sub> and <italic>B</italic><sub>2</sub>) is measured by Pearson's correlation (<italic>r</italic><sub>e</sub>, where the subscript "e" stands for expression) between the expression levels of the two alleles across isogenic cells under the same environment. Among the four possible pairs of an <italic>A</italic> and a <italic>B</italic> allele, <italic>A</italic><sub>1</sub>-<italic>B</italic><sub>1</sub>, <italic>A</italic><sub>2</sub>-<italic>B</italic><sub>2</sub>, <italic>A</italic><sub>1</sub>-<italic>B</italic><sub>2</sub>, and <italic>A</italic><sub>2</sub>-<italic>B</italic><sub>1</sub>, the former two pairs are physically linked whereas the latter two pairs are unlinked. The linkage-effect hypothesis asserts that, at a steady state, expression correlations between linked alleles (<italic>cis</italic>-correlations) are greater than those between unlinked alleles (<italic>trans</italic>-correlations). That is, <italic>&#948;</italic><sub>e</sub> = [<italic>r</italic><sub>e</sub>(<italic>A</italic><sub>1</sub>,<italic>B</italic><sub>1</sub>)+<italic>r</italic><sub>e</sub>(<italic>A</italic><sub>2</sub>,<italic>B</italic><sub>2</sub>)&#8722;<italic>r</italic><sub>e</sub>(<italic>A</italic><sub>1</sub>,<italic>B</italic><sub>2</sub>)&#8722;<italic>r</italic><sub>e</sub>(<italic>A</italic><sub>2</sub>,<italic>B</italic><sub>1</sub>)]/2&gt;0. Note that this formulation is valid regardless of whether the two alleles of the same gene have equal mean expression levels. While each of the four correlations could be positive or negative, in the large data analyzed below, they are mostly positive and show approximately normal distributions across gene pairs examined (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1008389.s001">S1 Fig</xref>).</p>
<fig id="pgen.1008389.g002" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1008389.g002</object-id>
<label>Fig 2</label>
<caption>
<title>Chromosome-wide linkage effects on gene expression co-fluctuation in mouse fibroblast cells.</title>
<p>(A) The logic of the method for testing the linkage effect. When gene <italic>A</italic> and gene <italic>B</italic> are linked, the correlations between the mRNA concentrations of the alleles of <italic>A</italic> and <italic>B</italic> that are physically linked (<italic>cis</italic>-correlations) should exceed the corresponding correlations of the alleles that are physically unlinked (<italic>trans</italic>-correlations). That is, <italic>&#948;</italic><sub>e</sub> = (sum of <italic>cis</italic>-correlations &#8722; sum of <italic>trans</italic>-correlations)/2 should be positive. This relationship should disappear if gene <italic>A</italic> and gene <italic>B</italic> are unlinked. For each gene, the paternal and maternal alleles are labeled by 1 and 2, respectively. (B) Fraction of gene pairs with positive <italic>&#948;</italic><sub>e</sub>. The red line represents the null expectation under no linkage effect. The 95% confidence intervals estimated from all gene pairs are presented. <italic>P</italic>-values from binomial tests on independent gene pairs are presented. (C) Fraction of gene pairs with positive <italic>&#948;</italic><sub>e</sub> in each chromosome. The 95% confidence intervals estimated from all gene pairs are presented. Binomial <italic>P</italic>-values estimated from independent gene pairs are indicated as follows. NS, not significant; *, 0.01 &lt; <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05; **, 0.001 &lt; <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01; ***, 0.0001 &lt; <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001; and ****, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.0001. The red line represents the null expectation under no linkage effect. The control (Ctl) shows the fraction of unlinked gene pairs with positive <italic>&#948;</italic><sub>e</sub>. (D) Median <italic>&#948;</italic><sub>e</sub> in a bin decreases with the median genomic distance of linked genes in the bin. All bins have the same genomic distance interval. TSS, transcription start site. The red line shows median <italic>&#948;</italic><sub>e</sub> = 0. The blue line shows the linear regression of the binned data, and the 95% confidence interval of the regression is presented. Spearman's &#961; from unbinned data and associated <italic>P</italic>-value determined by a shuffling test are presented. (E) Fraction of linked gene pairs showing positive <italic>&#948;</italic><sub>e</sub> increases with the minimal number of reads per allele required (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 10<sup>&#8722;300</sup>). (F) Median <italic>&#948;</italic><sub>e</sub> for all linked gene pairs (red) and median <italic>&#948;</italic><sub>e</sub> in the left-most bin of panel D (blue) increase with the minimal read number per allele required (both <italic>P</italic> &lt; 10<sup>&#8722;300</sup>).</p>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" position="float" ns0:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1008389.g002" ns0:type="simple" />
</fig>
<p>To verify the above prediction about <italic>&#948;</italic><sub>e</sub>, we analyzed a single-cell RNA-seq dataset of fibroblast cells derived from a hybrid between two mouse strains (CAST/EiJ &#215; C57BL/6J) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1008389.ref023">23</xref>]. Single-cell RNA-seq profiles the transcriptomes of individual cells, allowing quantifying stochastic gene expression variations among isogenic cells in the same environment [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1008389.ref024">24</xref>&#8211;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1008389.ref026">26</xref>]. DNA polymorphisms in the hybrid allow estimation of the expression level of each allele for thousands of genes per cell. The dataset includes data from seven fibroblast clones and some non-clonal fibroblast cells of the same genotype. We focused our analysis on clone 7 (derived from the hybrid of CAST/EiJ male &#215; C57BL/6J female) in the dataset, because the number of cells sequenced in this clone is the largest (<italic>n</italic> = 60) among all clones. We excluded from our analysis all genes on Chromosomes 3 and 4 due to aneuploidy in this clone and X-linked genes due to X inactivation. To increase the sensitivity of our analysis and remove imprinted genes, we focused on the 3405 genes that have at least 10 RNA-seq reads averaged across cells mapped to each of the two alleles. Note that this gene set constitute &gt;30% of all expressed genes in the cells concerned. While most of the 3405 genes tend to be highly expressed, 16% of them have lower expressions than the median expression of all expressed genes. The 3405 genes form 3404&#215;3405/2 = 5,795,310 gene pairs, among which 377,584 pairs are chromosomally linked.</p>
<p>For each pair of chromosomally linked genes, we computed their <italic>&#948;</italic><sub>e</sub> by treating the allele from CAST/EiJ as allele 1 and that from C57BL/6J as allele 2 at each locus. The fraction of gene pairs with <italic>&#948;</italic><sub>e</sub> &gt; 0 is 0.61 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen.1008389.g002">Fig 2B</xref>). This fraction has a rather narrow 95% confidence interval (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen.1008389.g002">Fig 2B</xref>), demonstrating that the fraction is significantly higher than the null expectation of 0.5. Because a gene can appear in multiple gene pairs, which are not mutually independent, we applied a binomial test in a subset of gene pairs where each gene appears only once. Specifically, we randomly shuffled the relative positions of all genes on each chromosome and considered from one end of the chromosome to the other end non-overlapping consecutive windows of two genes. The observed fraction of gene pairs with positive <italic>&#948;</italic><sub>e</sub> still significantly exceeds the null expectation of 0.5 (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 2.4&#215;10<sup>&#8722;16</sup>, binomial test). That most gene pairs exhibit <italic>&#948;</italic><sub>e</sub> &gt; 0 holds in each of the 17 chromosomes examined, with the trend being statistically significant in six chromosomes even by the above conservative test (nominal <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen.1008389.g002">Fig 2C</xref>). As a negative control, we analyzed gene pairs located on different chromosomes, treating alleles the same way as described above. As expected, this time the fraction of gene pairs with <italic>&#948;</italic><sub>e</sub> &gt; 0 is not significantly different from 0.5 (<italic>P</italic> = 0.25; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen.1008389.g002">Fig 2B</xref>). The fraction of gene pairs with <italic>&#948;</italic><sub>e</sub> &gt; 0 appears to vary among chromosomes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen.1008389.g002">Fig 2C</xref>). To assess the significance of this variation, we compared the fraction of independent gene pairs with <italic>&#948;</italic><sub>e</sub> &gt; 0 between every two chromosomes by Fisher's exact test. After correcting for multiple testing, we found no significant difference between any two chromosomes.</p>
<p>To examine the generality of the findings from clone 7, we also analyzed clone 6 (derived from the hybrid of CAST/EiJ male &#215; C57BL/6J female), which has 38 cells with RNA-seq data. Because 10 of these cells are aneuploidy for different chromosomes (see the supplementary materials in [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1008389.ref023">23</xref>]), we analyzed the remaining 28 cells. Similar results were obtained (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1008389.s002">S2A and S2B Fig</xref>). Because clone 6 was from a male whereas clone 7 was from a female, our results apparently apply to both sexes. We also analyzed 47 non-clonal fibroblast cells with the same genetic background (cell IDs from 124 to 170, derived from the hybrid of CAST/EiJ male &#215; C57BL/6J female), and obtained similar results (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1008389.s002">S2C and S2D Fig</xref>). These findings establish that the linkage effect on expression co-fluctuation is neither limited to a few genes in a specific clone nor an epigenetic artifact of clonal cells, but is general. The linkage effect on co-fluctuation (and the decrease of the effect with genomic distance shown below) is robust to the definition of <italic>&#948;</italic><sub>e</sub>, because similar results are obtained when correlation coefficients are replaced with squares of correlation coefficients in the definition of <italic>&#948;</italic><sub>e</sub>.</p>
<p>We next investigated how close two genes need to be on the same chromosome for them to co-fluctuate in expression. We divided all pairs of chromosomally linked genes into 100 equal-interval bins based on the genomic distance between genes, defined by the number of nucleotides between their transcription start sites (TSSs). The median <italic>&#948;</italic><sub>e</sub> in a bin is found to decrease with the genomic distance represented by the bin (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen.1008389.g002">Fig 2D</xref>). Furthermore, even for the unbinned data, <italic>&#948;</italic><sub>e</sub> for a pair of linked genes correlates negatively with their genomic distance (Spearman's <italic>&#961;</italic> = -0.029). To assess the statistical significance of this negative correlation, we randomly shuffled the genomic coordinates of genes within chromosomes and recomputed the correlation. This was repeated 1000 times and none of the 1000 <italic>&#961;</italic> values were equal to or more negative than the observed <italic>&#961;</italic>. Hence, the linkage effect on expression co-fluctuation of two linked genes weakens significantly with their genomic distance (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001).</p>
<p>Surprisingly, however, median <italic>&#948;</italic><sub>e</sub> exceeds 0 for every bin except when the genomic distance exceeds 150 Mb (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen.1008389.g002">Fig 2D</xref>). Hence, the linkage effect is long-range. To statistically verify the potentially chromosome-wide linkage effect, we focused on linked gene pairs that are at least 63 Mb apart, which is one half the median size of mouse chromosomes. The median <italic>&#948;</italic><sub>e</sub> for these gene pairs is 0.017, or 68% of the median <italic>&#948;</italic><sub>e</sub> for the left-most bin in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen.1008389.g002">Fig 2D</xref>. We randomly shuffled the genomic positions of all genes and repeated the above analysis 1000 times. In none of the 1000 shuffled genomes did we observe the median <italic>&#948;</italic><sub>e</sub> greater than 0.017 for linked genes of distances &gt;63 Mb, validating the long-range expression co-fluctuation in the actual genome. The same can be said even for linked genes of distances &gt;90 Mb (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001, shuffling test). The above observations are not clone-specific, because the same trend is observed for cells of clone 6 (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1008389.s002">S2B Fig</xref>).</p>
<p>Notably, a previous experiment in mammalian cells [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1008389.ref021">21</xref>] detected a linkage effect for chromosomally adjacent reporter genes (<italic>&#948;</italic><sub>e</sub> = 0.834) orders of magnitude stronger than what is observed here. This is primarily because expression levels estimated using single-cell RNA fluorescence in situ hybridization in the early study [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1008389.ref021">21</xref>] are much more precise than those estimated using allele-specific single-cell RNA-seq [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1008389.ref027">27</xref>] here. We thus predict that the linkage effect detected will be more pronounced as the expression level estimates become more precise. As a proof of principle, we gradually raised the required minimal number of reads per allele in our analysis, which should increase the precision of expression level estimation but decrease the number of genes that can be analyzed. Indeed, as the minimal read number rises, the fraction of chromosomally linked gene pairs with a positive <italic>&#948;</italic><sub>e</sub> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen.1008389.g002">Fig 2E</xref>), median <italic>&#948;</italic><sub>e</sub> for all chromosomally linked gene pairs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen.1008389.g002">Fig 2F</xref>), and median <italic>&#948;</italic><sub>e</sub> for the left-most bin (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen.1008389.g002">Fig 2F</xref>) all increase significantly. Furthermore, the low capturing efficiency of single-cell RNA-seq substantially reduces the observed size of the linkage effect, and our lower-bound estimate of the median true <italic>&#948;</italic><sub>e</sub> is 0.15 (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="sec007">Materials and Methods</xref>).</p>
<p>Because what matters to a cell is the total number of transcripts produced from the two alleles of a gene instead of the number produced from each allele, we also calculated the pairwise correlation in expression level between genes using either the total number of reads mapped to both alleles of a gene or normalized expression level of the gene. We similarly found a long-range linkage effect (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1008389.s003">S3 Fig</xref>), with trends and effect sizes close to the observations based on allele-specific expressions.</p>
<p>Previous studies reported that the relative transcriptional orientations of neighboring genes influence their expression co-fluctuation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1008389.ref028">28</xref>]. This impact, however, is unobserved in our study (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1008389.s004">S4 Fig</xref>), which may be due to the limited precision of the expression estimates and the fact that only 422 pairs of neighboring genes satisfy the minimal read number requirement.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec004">
<title>Shared chemical environment for transcription results in the long-range linkage effect</title>
<p>What has caused the chromosome-wide expression co-fluctuation of linked genes? One simple explanation is the asynchronous DNA replication in dividing cells, where closely linked genes tend to be replicated at the same time so show positively correlated gene copy numbers and hence expression levels. But a simple calculation demonstrates that this explanation is not tenable. There are 10<sup>4</sup> to 10<sup>5</sup> replication origins per mammalian cell [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1008389.ref029">29</xref>]. Given the size of the mammalian genome (~3&#215;10<sup>9</sup> bases), DNA segments within 0.03&#8211;0.3 Mb share a replication origin. The asynchronous DNA replication could result in the expression co-fluctuation of genes in the range of 0.03 to 0.3 Mb, which cannot explain our observation of expression co-fluctuation at the scale of &gt;60 Mb.</p>
<p>Individual chromosomes in mammalian cells are organized into territories with a diameter of 1~2 &#956;m [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1008389.ref030">30</xref>], whereas the diameter of the nucleus is ~8 &#956;m [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1008389.ref030">30</xref>]. Thus, the physical distance between chromosomally linked genes is below 1~2 &#956;m, whereas that between unlinked genes is usually &gt; 1~2 &#956;m and can be as large as ~8 &#956;m. Because it takes time for macromolecules to diffuse in the nucleus, linked genes tend to have similar chemical environments and hence similar transcriptional dynamics (i.e., promoter co-accessibility and/or co-transcription) when compared with unlinked genes. We thus hypothesize that the linkage effect is fundamentally explained by the 3D proximity of linked genes compared with unlinked genes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen.1008389.g003">Fig 3A</xref>). Below we provide evidence for this model. Note, while our computational analyses cannot prove causation, they examine correlations among various quantities that are predicted by our hypothesis and hence can provide strong evidence for or against the hypothesis when performed rigorously and interpreted appropriately.</p>
<fig id="pgen.1008389.g003" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1008389.g003</object-id>
<label>Fig 3</label>
<caption>
<title>Mechanistic basis of the linkage effect on expression co-fluctuation.</title>
<p>(A) A model on how chromosomal linkage causes expression co-fluctuation. (B) Fractions of linked or unlinked genomic region pairs with positive, 0, and negative <italic>&#948;</italic><sub>i</sub> values, respectively. <italic>&#948;</italic><sub>i</sub> = (sum of <italic>cis</italic>-interactions &#8722; sum of <italic>trans</italic>-interactions)/2, where chromatin interactions are based on Hi-C data. All fractions are shown, but the blue and red bars for linked regions are too low to be visible. (C) <italic>&#948;</italic><sub>i</sub> decreases with the genomic distance between the linked regions considered. Each dot represents one pair of linked genomic regions. Shown here is log<sub>10</sub>(<italic>&#948;</italic><sub>i</sub> + 5) because <italic>&#948;</italic><sub>i</sub> is occasionally negative and it decreases with genomic distance very quickly. The horizontal red line indicates <italic>&#948;</italic><sub>i</sub> = 0. The blue line is a cubic spline regression of log<sub>10</sub>(<italic>&#948;</italic><sub>i</sub> + 5) on the genomic distance. Spearman's &#961; from unbinned data and associated <italic>P</italic>-value determined by a shuffling test are presented. (D) Fraction of linked or unlinked pairs of ATAC peaks with positive <italic>&#948;</italic><sub>a</sub>. <italic>&#948;</italic><sub>a</sub> = (sum of <italic>cis</italic>-correlations in accessibility &#8722; sum of <italic>trans</italic>-correlations in accessibility)/2. The 95% confidence interval is presented. <italic>P</italic>-values from binomial tests on independent peak pairs are presented. The red line shows the fraction of 0.5. (E) <italic>&#948;</italic><sub>a</sub> decreases with the distance between linked ATAC peaks. Each dot represents a bin. All bins have the same distance interval. The red line shows <italic>&#948;</italic><sub>a</sub> = 0. The blue line shows the linear regression of the binned data and the shade shows the 95% confidence interval of the regression. For better viewing, one bin (X = 156, Y = -0.02) is omitted in the figure; the extreme <italic>&#948;</italic><sub>a</sub> of the bin is probably due to the small sample size of the bin (<italic>n</italic> = 13). Spearman's &#961; computed from unbinned data and associated <italic>P</italic>-value determined from a shuffling test are presented. (F) Co-accessibility (<italic>trans</italic>-<italic>r</italic><sub>a</sub>) is greater for 3D contacted (<italic>trans</italic>-<italic>F</italic> &gt; 0) than uncontacted (<italic>trans</italic>-<italic>F</italic> = 0) non-allelic genomic regions located on homologous chromosomes. The lower and upper edges of a box represent the first (qu<sub>1</sub>) and third (qu<sub>3</sub>) quartiles, respectively, the horizontal line inside the box indicates the median (md), the whiskers extend to the most extreme values inside inner fences, md&#177;1.5(qu<sub>3</sub>-qu<sub>1</sub>), and the dots represent values outside the inner fences (outliers). <italic>P</italic>-value is determined by a Mantel test. (G) Expression co-fluctuation (<italic>trans</italic>-<italic>r</italic><sub>e</sub>) improves with the co-accessibility (<italic>trans</italic>-<italic>r</italic><sub>a</sub>) of non-allelic ATAC peaks located on homologous chromosomes. Each dot represents a bin. All bins have the same co-accessibility interval. The blue line shows the linear regression of the binned data. Spearman's &#961; computed from unbinned data and associated <italic>P</italic>-value determined by a Mantel test are presented. (H) <italic>&#948;</italic><sub>e</sub> is positively correlated with <italic>&#948;</italic><sub>i</sub>. All gene pairs are separated into 100 equal-size bins, and the blue line shows a LOESS regression with the 95% confidence interval of the regression shown. Spearman's &#961; computed from unbinned data and the associated <italic>P</italic>-value are presented. (I) Diffusion rates for molecules responsible for the chromosome-wide linkage effect should be neither too high nor too low. If the diffusion is too fast, the concentration of the molecule will be similar across the nucleus (top); if the diffusion is too slow, the concentration cannot even be similar for loci loosely linked on the same chromosome (bottom). Only when the diffusion rate is intermediate could the local chemical environment be homogeneous for genes on the same chromosome but heterogeneous for genes on different chromosomes (middle). The large oval represents the nucleus and each black "S" curve represents a chromosome. Blue zig-zags show molecular diffusions, while the blue area depicts a chemically homogenous environment.</p>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" position="float" ns0:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1008389.g003" ns0:type="simple" />
</fig>
<p>We started by comparing the 3D distances between linked alleles with those between unlinked alleles. The 3D distance between two genomic regions can be approximately measured by Hi-C, a high-throughput chromosome conformation capture method for quantifying the number of interactions between genomic loci that are nearby in 3D space [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1008389.ref031">31</xref>]. The smaller the 3D distance between two genomic regions, the higher the interaction frequency between them [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1008389.ref032">32</xref>]. It is predicted that the interaction frequency between the physically linked alleles of two genes (<italic>cis</italic>-interaction) is greater than that between the unlinked alleles of the same gene pair (<italic>trans</italic>-interaction). To verify this prediction, we analyzed the recently published allele-specific 500kb-resolution Hi-C interaction matrix [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1008389.ref033">33</xref>] of mouse neural progenitor cells (NPC). For any two linked loci <italic>A</italic> and <italic>B</italic> as depicted in the left diagram of <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen.1008389.g002">Fig 2A</xref>, we computed <italic>&#948;</italic><sub>i</sub> = [<italic>F</italic>(<italic>A</italic><sub>1</sub>,<italic>B</italic><sub>1</sub>)+<italic>F</italic>(<italic>A</italic><sub>2</sub>,<italic>B</italic><sub>2</sub>)&#8722;<italic>F</italic>(<italic>A</italic><sub>1</sub>,<italic>B</italic><sub>2</sub>)&#8722;<italic>F</italic>(<italic>A</italic><sub>2</sub>,<italic>B</italic><sub>1</sub>)]/2, where <italic>F</italic> is the interaction frequency between the two alleles in the parentheses and the subscript "i" refers to interaction. We found that 99% of pairs of linked loci have a positive <italic>&#948;</italic><sub>i</sub> (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 2.2&#215;10<sup>&#8722;16</sup>, binomial test on independent locus pairs; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen.1008389.g003">Fig 3B</xref>). By contrast, among unlinked gene pairs, the fraction with a positive <italic>&#948;</italic><sub>i</sub> is not significantly different from that with a negative <italic>&#948;</italic><sub>i</sub> (<italic>P</italic> = 0.90, binomial test on independent locus pairs; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen.1008389.g003">Fig 3B</xref>). In the analysis of unlinked loci, we treated all alleles from one parental strain of the hybrid as alleles 1 and all alleles from the other parental strain of the hybrid as alleles 2 in the above formula of <italic>&#948;</italic><sub>i</sub>. These results clearly demonstrate the 3D proximity of genes on the same chromosome when compared with those on two homologous chromosomes.</p>
<p>To examine if the above phenomenon is long-range, we plotted <italic>&#948;</italic><sub>i</sub> as a function of the distance (in Mb) between two linked loci considered. Indeed, even when the distance exceeds 63 Mb, one half the median size of mouse chromosomes, almost all locus pairs still show positive <italic>&#948;</italic><sub>i</sub> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen.1008389.g003">Fig 3C</xref>). Similar to the phenomenon of the linkage effect on gene expression co-fluctuation, we observed a negative correlation between the genomic distance between two linked loci and <italic>&#948;</italic><sub>i</sub> (&#961; = -0.81 for unbinned data). This correlation is statistically significant (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001), because it is stronger than the corresponding correlation in each of the 1000 negative controls where the genomic positions of all genes are randomly shuffled within chromosomes.</p>
<p>As mentioned, 3D proximity should synchronize the transcriptional dynamics of linked alleles. Based on the bursty model of gene expression [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1008389.ref034">34</xref>], transcription involves two primary steps. In the first step, the promoter region switches from the inactive state to the active state such that it becomes accessible to the transcriptional machinery. In the second step, RNA polymerase binds to the activated promoter to initiate transcription. In principle, the synchronization of either step can result in co-fluctuation of mRNA concentrations. Because the accessibility of promoters can be detected using transposase-accessible chromatin using sequencing (ATAC-seq) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1008389.ref035">35</xref>] in a high-throughput manner, we focused our empirical analysis on promoter co-accessibility. Note that although the bursty model does not consider certain details of transcription such as polymerase pausing and productive elongation, there is mounting evidence that the bursty model provides a good approximation of stochastic gene expression [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1008389.ref021">21</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1008389.ref036">36</xref>&#8211;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1008389.ref038">38</xref>], which is what matters to our study.</p>
<p>To verify the potential long-range linkage effect on chromatin co-accessibility, we should ideally use single-cell allele-specific measures of chromatin accessibility. However, such data are unavailable. We reason that, the accessibility covariation of genomic regions among cells may be quantified by the corresponding covariation among populations of cells of the same type cultured under the same environment. In fact, it can be shown mathematically that, under certain conditions, chromatin co-accessibility of two genomic regions among cells equals the corresponding chromatin co-accessibility across cell populations (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="sec007">Materials and Methods</xref>). Based on this result, we analyzed a dataset collected from allele-specific ATAC-seq in 16 NPC cell populations [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1008389.ref039">39</xref>]. We first removed sex chromosomes and then required the number of reads mapped to each allele of a peak to exceed 50 for the peak to be considered. This latter step removed imprinted loci and ensured that the considered peaks are relatively reliable. About 3500 peaks remained after the filtering. This sample size is comparable to the number of genes used in the analysis of expression co-fluctuation. For each pair of ATAC peaks, we computed <italic>&#948;</italic><sub>a</sub> = [<italic>r</italic><sub>a</sub>(<italic>A</italic><sub>1</sub>,<italic>B</italic><sub>1</sub>)+<italic>r</italic><sub>a</sub>(<italic>A</italic><sub>2</sub>,<italic>B</italic><sub>2</sub>)&#8722;<italic>r</italic><sub>a</sub>(<italic>A</italic><sub>1</sub>,<italic>B</italic><sub>2</sub>)&#8722;<italic>r</italic><sub>a</sub>(<italic>A</italic><sub>2</sub>,<italic>B</italic><sub>1</sub>)]/2, where <italic>r</italic><sub>a</sub> is the correlation in ATAC-seq read number between the alleles specified in the parentheses (following the left diagram in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen.1008389.g002">Fig 2A</xref>) across the 16 cell populations and the subscript "a" refers to chromatin accessibility. The fraction of peak pairs with a positive <italic>&#948;</italic><sub>a</sub> is significantly greater than 0.5 for linked peak pairs but not significantly different from 0.5 for unlinked peak pairs (binomial test on independent peak pairs; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen.1008389.g003">Fig 3D</xref>). Furthermore, after grouping ATAC peak pairs into 100 equal-interval bins according to the genomic distance between peaks, we observed a clear trend that <italic>&#948;</italic><sub>a</sub> decreases with the genomic distance between peaks (<italic>&#961;</italic> = -0.05 for unbinned data, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001, within-chromosome shuffling test; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen.1008389.g003">Fig 3E</xref>). In addition, even for linked peak pairs with a distance greater than 63 Mb, their median <italic>&#948;</italic><sub>a</sub> is significantly greater than that of unlinked peak pairs (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001, among-chromosome shuffling test). Together, these results demonstrate a long-range linkage effect on chromatin co-accessibility. Similar to <italic>&#948;</italic><sub>e</sub>, the observed <italic>&#948;</italic><sub>a</sub> is small. This is again at least in part a result of low capturing efficiencies in high-throughput sequencing. We estimated that the median true <italic>&#948;</italic><sub>a</sub> is at least 0.03 (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="sec007">Materials and Methods</xref>), an order of magnitude larger than the observed value.</p>
<p>Because we hypothesize that the linkage effect on expression co-fluctuation is via 3D chromatin proximity that leads to chromatin co-accessibility (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen.1008389.g003">Fig 3A</xref>), we should verify the relationship between 3D proximity and chromatin co-accessibility for unlinked genomic regions to avoid the confounding factor of linkage. To this end, we converted ATAC-seq read counts to a 500kb resolution by summing up read counts for all allele-specific chromatin accessibility peaks that fall within the corresponding Hi-C bin, because the resolution of the Hi-C data is 500kb. Because alleles from different parents are unlinked in the hybrid used for ATAC-seq, for each pair of bins, we computed the mean correlation in chromatin accessibility between the alleles derived from different parents among the 16 cell populations, or <italic>trans</italic>-<italic>r</italic><sub>a</sub> = <italic>r</italic><sub><italic>a</italic></sub>(<italic>A</italic><sub>1</sub>, <italic>B</italic><sub>2</sub>)/2 + <italic>r</italic><sub><italic>a</italic></sub>(<italic>A</italic><sub>2</sub>, <italic>B</italic><sub>1</sub>)/2. For the same reason, we computed the sum of Hi-C contact frequency between the alleles derived from different parents, <italic>trans</italic>-<italic>F</italic> = <italic>F</italic>(<italic>A</italic><sub>1</sub>, <italic>B</italic><sub>2</sub>)/2+<italic>F</italic>(<italic>A</italic><sub>2</sub>, <italic>B</italic><sub>1</sub>)/2. Because interaction frequencies in Hi-C data are generally low for unlinked regions, we separated all pairs of bins into two categories, contacted (i.e., <italic>trans</italic>-<italic>F</italic> &gt; 0) and uncontacted (i.e., <italic>trans</italic>-<italic>F</italic> = 0). We found that <italic>trans</italic>-<italic>r</italic><sub>a</sub> values for contacted bin pairs are significantly higher than those for uncontacted bin pairs (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.0001; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen.1008389.g003">Fig 3F</xref>), consistent with our hypothesis that 3D chromatin proximity induces chromatin co-accessibility. The above statistical significance was determined by performing a Mantel test using the original <italic>trans</italic>-<italic>r</italic><sub>a</sub> matrix of the aforementioned allele pairs and the corresponding <italic>trans</italic>-<italic>F</italic> matrix. Corroborating our finding, a recent study of single-cell (but not allele-specific) chromatin accessibility data also found that the co-accessibility of two loci rises with their 3D proximity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1008389.ref040">40</xref>].</p>
<p>To test the hypothesis that chromatin co-accessibility leads to expression co-fluctuation (even for unlinked alleles) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen.1008389.g003">Fig 3A</xref>), we analyzed the allele-specific ATAC-seq data and single-cell allele-specific RNA-seq data together. Although these data were generated from different cell types in mouse, we reason that, because the 3D chromosome conformation is highly similar among tissues [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1008389.ref041">41</xref>], chromatin co-accessibility, which is affected by 3D chromatin proximity (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen.1008389.g003">Fig 3F</xref>), may also be similar among tissues. Hence, it may be possible to detect a correlation between chromatin co-accessibility and expression co-fluctuation. To this end, we used unbinned ATAC-peak data to compute <italic>trans</italic>-<italic>r</italic><sub>a</sub> but limited the analysis to those peaks with at least 10 reads per allele. We used the allele-specific RNA-seq data to compute <italic>trans</italic>-<italic>r</italic><sub>e</sub> = <italic>r</italic><sub>e</sub>(<italic>A</italic><sub>1</sub>, <italic>B</italic><sub>2</sub>)/2+<italic>r</italic><sub>e</sub>(<italic>A</italic><sub>2</sub>, <italic>B</italic><sub>1</sub>)/2 for pairs of linked genes. We then assigned each gene to its nearest ATAC peak and averaged <italic>trans</italic>-<italic>r</italic><sub>e</sub> among gene pairs assigned to the same pair of ATAC peaks. We subsequently grouped ATAC peak pairs into 100 equal-interval bins according to their co-accessibilities, and observed a clear positive correlation between median <italic>trans</italic>-<italic>r</italic><sub>a</sub> and median <italic>trans</italic>-<italic>r</italic><sub>e</sub> across the 100 bins (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen.1008389.g003">Fig 3G</xref>). For unbinned data, <italic>trans</italic>-<italic>r</italic><sub>a</sub> and <italic>trans</italic>-<italic>r</italic><sub>e</sub> also show a significant, positive correlation (<italic>&#961;</italic> = 0.021, <italic>P</italic> = 0.027, Mantel test). Although the assignment of a gene to its nearest ATAC peak may not be biologically meaningful in some cases, such potential errors only add noise to our analysis, meaning that the true signal should be stronger than what is observed.</p>
<p>As predicted, there is also a positive correlation between <italic>&#948;</italic><sub>i</sub> and <italic>&#948;</italic><sub>e</sub> (<italic>&#961;</italic> = 0.014, <italic>P</italic> = 1.6&#215;10<sup>&#8722;17</sup>). In this analysis, for each linked pair of Hi-C bins, we computed <italic>&#948;</italic><sub>i</sub>. We assigned each gene in our dataset to its nearest Hi-C bin, estimated <italic>&#948;</italic><sub>e</sub> for each pair of genes that are respectively located in the two Hi-C bins considered, and computed the average <italic>&#948;</italic><sub>e</sub> between the two bins. The correlation between <italic>&#948;</italic><sub>i</sub> and <italic>&#948;</italic><sub>e</sub> can be visualized in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen.1008389.g003">Fig 3H</xref>, where Hi-C bin pairs are separated into 100 equal-size groups based on <italic>&#948;</italic><sub>i</sub>. Note that although the impact of 3D proximity (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen.1008389.g003">Fig 3H</xref>) appears weaker than the impact of genomic distance (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen.1008389.g002">Fig 2D</xref>) on <italic>&#948;</italic><sub>e</sub>, these two plots are not directly comparable because of the following reasons. First, the Hi-C contact frequency is not an accurate measure of 3D proximity, especially for region pairs that rarely contact, which apply to the vast majority of region pairs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen.1008389.g003">Fig 3C</xref>). By contrast, genomic distance is measured accurately. Second, the resolution of the Hi-C data used is much lower (500 kb) than that of the genomic distance (1 bp). Third, the Hi-C data and gene expression co-fluctuations data are not from the same cell type, which reduces the observed impact of 3D proximity.</p>
<p>Together, the above results support our hypothesis that, compared with unlinked genes, linked genes have a shared chemical environment due to their 3D proximity and hence chromatin co-accessibility, which leads to their expression co-fluctuation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen.1008389.g003">Fig 3A</xref>). However, 3D proximity can lead to promoter co-accessibility by several means, which have been broadly summarized into three categories of mechanisms [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1008389.ref030">30</xref>]: 1D scanning, 3D looping, and 3D diffusion. 1D scanning refers to the spread of chromatin states along an entire chromosome, but 1D scanning is rare, with only a few known examples such as X-chromosome inactivation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1008389.ref030">30</xref>]. Hence, 1D scanning is unlikely to be the mechanism responsible for the broad linkage effect discovered here. 3D looping refers to the phenomenon that a chromosome often forms loops to bring far-separated loci into contact, whereas 3D diffusion refers to chromosome communication by local diffusion of transcription-related proteins. For tightly linked loci, our data do not allow a clear distinction between 3D looping and 3D diffusion in causing the linkage effect discovered here. But 3D diffusion seems more likely for the long-range effect, because the range of 3D looping seems limited to loci separated by no more than 200 kb simply due to the rapid decrease of the contact frequency with the physical distance between two loci [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1008389.ref042">42</xref>], evident in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen.1008389.g003">Fig 3C</xref> (note the log scale of the Y-axis). It has been estimated that loci separated by 10 Mb behave essentially the same as two loci that are on different chromosomes in terms of the contact frequency [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1008389.ref030">30</xref>], and any contact-based mechanism is unlikely to be long-range (e.g., topologically associating domains) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1008389.ref041">41</xref>]. Therefore, the most likely cause of our observed long-range linkage effect is 3D diffusion.</p>
<p>In the 3D diffusion mechanism, which molecule is most likely responsible for the observed long-range linkage effect on expression co-fluctuation? If the chemical influencing transcription has a diffusion time in the nucleus much shorter than the interval between transcriptional bursts, two genes have essentially the same environment with respect to that chemical regardless of their 3D distance [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1008389.ref043">43</xref>] and hence no linkage effect is expected (top cell in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen.1008389.g003">Fig 3I</xref>). On the contrary, if the chemical diffuses too slowly, the linkage effect will be local [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1008389.ref043">43</xref>] and hence cannot be chromosome-wide (bottom cell in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen.1008389.g003">Fig 3I</xref>). Therefore, the diffusion rate of the chemical responsible for the long-range linkage effect cannot be too low or too high such that they become evenly distributed in a chromosome territory but not the whole nucleus in a time comparable to the interval between transcriptional bursts (middle cell in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen.1008389.g003">Fig 3I</xref>). The typical transcriptional burst interval is 18&#8211;50 minutes in mammalian cells [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1008389.ref037">37</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1008389.ref038">38</xref>]. The time for a chemical to distribute evenly in a given volume with radius <italic>R</italic> is on the order of <italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup>/<italic>D</italic>, where <italic>D</italic> is the diffusion coefficient of the chemical [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1008389.ref034">34</xref>]. Most molecules in the nucleus are rapidly diffused. For example, transcription factors typically have a diffusion coefficient of 0.5&#8211;5 &#956;m<sup>2</sup>/s in the nucleus [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1008389.ref034">34</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1008389.ref044">44</xref>], meaning that they can diffuse across the whole nucleus in about 3 to 30 seconds. By contrast, core histone proteins such as H2B proteins diffuse extremely slowly due to their tight binding to DNA. They are usually considered immobilized because diffusion is rarely observed during the course of an experiment [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1008389.ref044">44</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1008389.ref045">45</xref>]. Therefore, none of these molecules are responsible for the long-range linkage effect observed. Interestingly, linker histones, which include five subtypes of H1 histones in mouse that play important roles in chromatin structure and transcription regulation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1008389.ref046">46</xref>], have a diffusion coefficient of about 0.01 &#956;m<sup>2</sup>/s [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1008389.ref047">47</xref>]. Thus, it takes H1 proteins 25&#8211;100 seconds to diffuse through a chromosome territory, but about 30 minutes to diffuse across the whole nucleus. The former time but not the latter is much smaller than the typical transcriptional burst interval. Hence, it is possible that H1 diffusion in the nucleus is the ultimate cause of the linkage effect. We provide empirical evidence for this hypothesis in a later section.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec005">
<title>Beneficial linkage of genes encoding components of the same protein complex</title>
<p>Our finding that chromosomal linkage leads to gene expression co-fluctuation implies that linkage between genes could be selected for when expression co-fluctuation is advantageous. Due to the complexity of biology, it is generally difficult to predict whether the expression co-fluctuation of a pair of genes is beneficial, neutral, or deleterious. However, the expression co-fluctuation of genes encoding components of the same protein complex is likely advantageous. To see why this is the case, let us consider a dimer composed of one molecule of protein A and one molecule of protein B; the heterodimer is functional but monomers are not. We denote the concentration of dissociated protein A as [A], the concentration of dissociated protein B as [B], and the concentration of protein complex AB as [AB]. At the steady state, [AB] = <italic>K</italic>[A][B], where <italic>K</italic> is the association constant [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1008389.ref048">48</xref>]. Furthermore, the total concentration of protein A, [A]<sub>t</sub>, equals [A] + [AB], while the total concentration of protein B, [B]<sub>t</sub>, equals [B] + [AB]. Based on these relationships, we simulated 10,000 cells, where the mean and coefficient of variation (CV) are respectively 1 and 0.2 for both [A]<sub>t</sub> and [B]<sub>t</sub> (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="sec007">Materials and Methods</xref>). We assumed <italic>K</italic> = 10<sup>5</sup> based on empirical <italic>K</italic> values of stable protein complexes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1008389.ref049">49</xref>]. We found that, as the correlation between [A]<sub>t</sub> and [B]<sub>t</sub> increases, mean [AB] of the 10,000 cells rises (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen.1008389.g004">Fig 4A</xref>). We also considered a wide range of other <italic>K</italic> values (10<sup>&#8722;1</sup>, 10<sup>0</sup>, 10<sup>1</sup>, 10<sup>2</sup>, 10<sup>3</sup>, and 10<sup>4</sup>) and found the result largely unchanged. The lower-bound mean [AB] is about 3% higher under co-fluctuation than under no co-fluctuation. Furthermore, the effect size rises substantially with CV. For example, when CV = 0.5, which is not unusual in eukaryotes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1008389.ref049">49</xref>], the effect increases to 20%. We also considered protein complexes with other stoichiometries and the scenario when the mean [A]<sub>t</sub> to mean [B]<sub>t</sub> ratio deviates from the stoichiometry (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="sec007">Materials and Methods</xref>). In all parameter combinations examined, the mean [AB] increases with the correlation between [A]<sub>t</sub> and [B]<sub>t</sub>, albeit with a wide range of effect size (0.001% to 27% higher mean [AB] under co-fluctuation than under no co-fluctuation). If we assume that fitness rises with [AB], the co-fluctuation of [A]<sub>t</sub> and [B]<sub>t</sub> is beneficial, compared with independent fluctuations of [A]<sub>t</sub> and [B]<sub>t</sub>. In addition, because mean [A] and mean [B] must decrease with the rise of mean [AB], the co-fluctuation of [A]<sub>t</sub> and [B]<sub>t</sub> could also be advantageous because it lowers the concentrations of the unbound monomers that may be toxic. Indeed, past studies found better expression co-fluctuations of genes encoding members of the same protein complex than random gene pairs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1008389.ref050">50</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1008389.ref051">51</xref>], suggesting that expression co-fluctuation of members of the same protein complex is selectively favored. Because our simulation considers protein concentrations instead of gene expressions, it directly applies to both haploid and diploid cells. The only difference is that protein concentrations such as [A]<sub>t</sub> and [B]<sub>t</sub> have a lower CV in diploid than haploid cells [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1008389.ref006">6</xref>]. Further, as shown in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1008389.s003">S3 Fig</xref>, mouse cells analyzed here do show a higher correlation in the total expression level of two alleles between linked than unlinked genes.</p>
<fig id="pgen.1008389.g004" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1008389.g004</object-id>
<label>Fig 4</label>
<caption>
<title>Genes encoding components of the same protein complex tend to be chromosomally linked.</title>
<p>(A) Mean concentration of the protein complex AB ([AB]) in 10,000 cells increases with the co-fluctuation of the concentrations of its two components measured by the correlation of the total concentration of protein A ([A]<sub>t</sub>) and that of B ([B]<sub>t</sub>). (B-C) The frequency distribution of the number of pairs of linked genes encoding components of the same protein complex (B) and components of different protein complexes (C) in 10,000 randomly shuffled genomes. Arrows indicate the observed values. (D-E) The frequency distribution of the median distance between two linked genes that encode components of the same protein complex (D) and components of different protein complexes (E) in 10,000 randomly shuffled genomes. Arrows indicate the observed values. (F) Test of the hypothesis of protein complex-driven evolution of gene linkage, which asserts that the probability for an originally unlinked pair of genes to become linked is higher when they encode members of the same protein complex than when they do not. Of 875 pairs of genes that are unlinked in both human and rat and encode members of the same protein complex in both human and mouse, 25 become linked in mouse, as indicated by the arrow. The bars show the frequency distribution of the corresponding expected number under the null hypothesis. (G) Protein complex genes that are linked with at least one gene encoding a member of the same complex tend to be highly expressed in tissues with low abundances of linker histones. Y-axis shows the correlation in expression level between protein complex genes and the linker histone genes across tissues.</p>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" position="float" ns0:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1008389.g004" ns0:type="simple" />
</fig>
<p>To test if genes encoding components of the same protein complex tend to be linked, we used the mouse protein complex data from CORUM and downloaded the chromosomal positions of all mouse protein-coding genes from Ensembl [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1008389.ref052">52</xref>]. Because genes may be linked due to their origins from tandem duplication [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1008389.ref053">53</xref>], the data were pre-processed to produce a set of duplicate-free mouse protein-coding genes (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="sec007">Materials and Methods</xref>). We then randomly shuffled the genomic positions of the retained genes encoding protein complex components among all possible positions of the duplicate-free mouse protein-coding genes. The observed number of linked pairs of genes encoding components of the same protein complex is significantly greater than the random expectation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen.1008389.g004">Fig 4B</xref>). For comparison, we also computed the number of linked pairs of genes encoding components of different protein complexes. This number is not significantly greater than the random expectation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen.1008389.g004">Fig 4C</xref>). Thus, the enrichment in gene linkage is specifically related to coding for subunits of the same protein complex. Interestingly, the observed median distance between the TSSs of two linked genes encoding protein complex subunits is not significantly different from the random expectation, regardless of whether subunits of the same (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen.1008389.g004">Fig 4D</xref>) or different (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen.1008389.g004">Fig 4E</xref>) protein complexes are considered.</p>
<p>The phenomenon that members of the same protein complex tend to be encoded by linked genes could have arisen for one or both of the following reasons. First, selection for co-fluctuation among proteins of the same complex has driven the evolution of gene linkage. Second, due to their co-fluctuation, products of linked genes may have been preferentially recruited to the same protein complex in evolution. Under the first hypothesis, originally unlinked genes encoding members of the same protein complex are more likely to become linked in evolution than originally unlinked genes that do not encode members of the same complex. To verify this prediction, we examined mouse genes using rat and human as outgroups (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen.1008389.g004">Fig 4F</xref>), because our <italic>&#948;</italic><sub>e</sub> estimates are from the mouse. We obtained pairs of genes encoding components of the same protein complex in both human and mouse. Hence, these pairs likely encode members of the same protein complex in the common ancestor of the three species. Among them, 875 pairs are unlinked in human and rat, suggesting that they were unlinked in the common ancestor of the three species. Of the 875 pairs, 25 pairs become linked in the mouse genome, significantly more than the random expectation under no requirement for gene pairs to encode members of the same complex (<italic>P</italic> = 0.005; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen.1008389.g004">Fig 4F</xref>; see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="sec007">Materials and Methods</xref>). Therefore, the first hypothesis is supported. Under this hypothesis, the result in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen.1008389.g004">Fig 4D</xref> may be explained by the long-range linkage effect on expression co-fluctuation, such that once two genes encoding components of the same protein complex move to the same chromosome, selection is not strong enough to drive them closer to each other. To test the second hypothesis, we need gene pairs encoding proteins that belong to the same protein complex in mouse but not in human nor rat, which require such low false negative errors in protein complex identification that no current method can meet. Hence, we leave the test of the second hypothesis to future studies.</p>
<p>Note that the above tests have two caveats. First, it is possible that some tandem duplicates remain in our data, which will compromise the analysis in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen.1008389.g004">Fig 4B</xref>. However, the result in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen.1008389.g004">Fig 4F</xref> is robust to such potential errors because the gene pairs concerned are originally unlinked so could not have arisen by tandem duplication. Thus, our evidence for positive selection for gene linkage holds even when the data are contaminated by tandem duplicates. Second, we inferred ancestral gene linkage by the parsimony principle, which may occasionally be incorrect. But such errors add only random noise to our analysis, suggesting that the actual strength of evidence for our hypothesis is likely stronger than what is shown here.</p>
<p>As mentioned, our theoretical consideration suggests that, due to their intermediate diffusion coefficients, H1 histones may be responsible for the observed chromosome-wide expression co-fluctuation. Because the local H1 concentration fluctuates more when its cellular concentration is lower, we predict that the benefit and the selection coefficient for linkage of genes encoding members of the same protein complex are greater in tissues with lower H1 concentrations. Given that gene expression is costly, for a given gene, it is reasonable to assume that the relative importance of its function in a tissue increases with its expression level in the tissue [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1008389.ref054">54</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1008389.ref055">55</xref>]. Hence, we predict that, the more negative the across-tissue expression correlation is between a protein complex member gene and H1 histones, the higher the likelihood that the gene is driven to be linked with other genes encoding members of the same protein complex. To verify the above prediction, we used a recently published RNA-seq dataset [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1008389.ref056">56</xref>] to measure Pearson's correlation between the mRNA concentration of a gene that encodes a protein complex subunit and the mean mRNA concentration of all H1 histone genes across 13 mouse tissues. Indeed, the linked protein complex genes show more negative correlations than the unlinked protein complex genes (<italic>P</italic> = 0.012, one-tailed Mann-Whitney <italic>U</italic> test; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen.1008389.g004">Fig 4G</xref>). The disparity is even more pronounced when we compare linked protein complex genes that become linked in the mouse lineage with unlinked protein complex genes (<italic>P</italic> = 0.00068, one-tailed Mann-Whitney <italic>U</italic> test; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen.1008389.g004">Fig 4G</xref>). This is likely owing to the enrichment of genes that are linked due to the linkage effect in the group of evolved linked protein complex genes (<inline-formula id="pgen.1008389.e001"><alternatives><graphic id="pgen.1008389.e001g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" ns0:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1008389.e001" ns0:type="simple" /><ns1:math display="inline" id="M1"><ns1:mfrac><ns1:mrow><ns1:mi mathvariant="normal">O</ns1:mi><ns1:mi mathvariant="normal">b</ns1:mi><ns1:mi mathvariant="normal">s</ns1:mi><ns1:mi mathvariant="normal">e</ns1:mi><ns1:mi mathvariant="normal">r</ns1:mi><ns1:mi mathvariant="normal">v</ns1:mi><ns1:mi mathvariant="normal">e</ns1:mi><ns1:mi mathvariant="normal">d</ns1:mi><ns1:mo>&#8722;</ns1:mo><ns1:mi mathvariant="normal">n</ns1:mi><ns1:mi mathvariant="normal">u</ns1:mi><ns1:mi mathvariant="normal">l</ns1:mi><ns1:mi mathvariant="normal">l</ns1:mi><ns1:mspace width="0.25em" /><ns1:mi mathvariant="normal">e</ns1:mi><ns1:mi mathvariant="normal">x</ns1:mi><ns1:mi mathvariant="normal">p</ns1:mi><ns1:mi mathvariant="normal">e</ns1:mi><ns1:mi mathvariant="normal">c</ns1:mi><ns1:mi mathvariant="normal">t</ns1:mi><ns1:mi mathvariant="normal">a</ns1:mi><ns1:mi mathvariant="normal">t</ns1:mi><ns1:mi mathvariant="normal">i</ns1:mi><ns1:mi mathvariant="normal">o</ns1:mi><ns1:mi mathvariant="normal">n</ns1:mi></ns1:mrow><ns1:mrow><ns1:mi mathvariant="normal">n</ns1:mi><ns1:mi mathvariant="normal">u</ns1:mi><ns1:mi mathvariant="normal">l</ns1:mi><ns1:mi mathvariant="normal">l</ns1:mi><ns1:mspace width="0.25em" /><ns1:mi mathvariant="normal">e</ns1:mi><ns1:mi mathvariant="normal">x</ns1:mi><ns1:mi mathvariant="normal">p</ns1:mi><ns1:mi mathvariant="normal">e</ns1:mi><ns1:mi mathvariant="normal">c</ns1:mi><ns1:mi mathvariant="normal">t</ns1:mi><ns1:mi mathvariant="normal">a</ns1:mi><ns1:mi mathvariant="normal">t</ns1:mi><ns1:mi mathvariant="normal">i</ns1:mi><ns1:mi mathvariant="normal">o</ns1:mi><ns1:mi mathvariant="normal">n</ns1:mi></ns1:mrow></ns1:mfrac><ns1:mo>=</ns1:mo><ns1:mfrac><ns1:mrow><ns1:mn>25</ns1:mn><ns1:mo>&#8722;</ns1:mo><ns1:mn>13</ns1:mn></ns1:mrow><ns1:mrow><ns1:mn>13</ns1:mn></ns1:mrow></ns1:mfrac><ns1:mo>=</ns1:mo><ns1:mn>92</ns1:mn><ns1:mi>%</ns1:mi></ns1:math></alternatives></inline-formula>) when compared with the group of linked protein complex genes (<inline-formula id="pgen.1008389.e002"><alternatives><graphic id="pgen.1008389.e002g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" ns0:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1008389.e002" ns0:type="simple" /><ns1:math display="inline" id="M2"><ns1:mfrac><ns1:mrow><ns1:mi mathvariant="normal">O</ns1:mi><ns1:mi mathvariant="normal">b</ns1:mi><ns1:mi mathvariant="normal">s</ns1:mi><ns1:mi mathvariant="normal">e</ns1:mi><ns1:mi mathvariant="normal">r</ns1:mi><ns1:mi mathvariant="normal">v</ns1:mi><ns1:mi mathvariant="normal">e</ns1:mi><ns1:mi mathvariant="normal">d</ns1:mi><ns1:mo>&#8722;</ns1:mo><ns1:mi mathvariant="normal">n</ns1:mi><ns1:mi mathvariant="normal">u</ns1:mi><ns1:mi mathvariant="normal">l</ns1:mi><ns1:mi mathvariant="normal">l</ns1:mi><ns1:mspace width="0.25em" /><ns1:mi mathvariant="normal">e</ns1:mi><ns1:mi mathvariant="normal">x</ns1:mi><ns1:mi mathvariant="normal">p</ns1:mi><ns1:mi mathvariant="normal">e</ns1:mi><ns1:mi mathvariant="normal">c</ns1:mi><ns1:mi mathvariant="normal">t</ns1:mi><ns1:mi mathvariant="normal">a</ns1:mi><ns1:mi mathvariant="normal">t</ns1:mi><ns1:mi mathvariant="normal">i</ns1:mi><ns1:mi mathvariant="normal">o</ns1:mi><ns1:mi mathvariant="normal">n</ns1:mi></ns1:mrow><ns1:mrow><ns1:mi mathvariant="normal">n</ns1:mi><ns1:mi mathvariant="normal">u</ns1:mi><ns1:mi mathvariant="normal">l</ns1:mi><ns1:mi mathvariant="normal">l</ns1:mi><ns1:mspace width="0.25em" /><ns1:mi mathvariant="normal">e</ns1:mi><ns1:mi mathvariant="normal">x</ns1:mi><ns1:mi mathvariant="normal">p</ns1:mi><ns1:mi mathvariant="normal">e</ns1:mi><ns1:mi mathvariant="normal">c</ns1:mi><ns1:mi mathvariant="normal">t</ns1:mi><ns1:mi mathvariant="normal">a</ns1:mi><ns1:mi mathvariant="normal">t</ns1:mi><ns1:mi mathvariant="normal">i</ns1:mi><ns1:mi mathvariant="normal">o</ns1:mi><ns1:mi mathvariant="normal">n</ns1:mi></ns1:mrow></ns1:mfrac><ns1:mo>=</ns1:mo><ns1:mfrac><ns1:mrow><ns1:mn>200</ns1:mn><ns1:mo>&#8722;</ns1:mo><ns1:mn>161</ns1:mn></ns1:mrow><ns1:mrow><ns1:mn>161</ns1:mn></ns1:mrow></ns1:mfrac><ns1:mo>=</ns1:mo><ns1:mn>24</ns1:mn><ns1:mi>%</ns1:mi></ns1:math></alternatives></inline-formula>). The above three groups of genes (evolved linked protein complex genes, linked protein complex genes, and unlinked protein complex genes) were constructed using stratified sampling to ensure that their mean expression levels across tissues are not significantly different (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="sec007">Materials and Methods</xref>). For comparison, we performed the same analysis but replaced H1 histones with TFIIB, a general transcription factor that is involved in the formation of the RNA polymerase II preinitiation complex and has a high diffusion rate [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1008389.ref057">57</xref>]. The trends shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen.1008389.g004">Fig 4G</xref> no longer holds (unlinked vs. linked: <italic>P</italic> = 0.11, one-tailed Mann-Whitney <italic>U</italic> test; unlinked vs. evolved linked: <italic>P</italic> = 0.63, one-tailed Mann-Whitney <italic>U</italic> test). We also performed the same analysis but replaced H1 histones with core histone proteins, which are immobilized [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1008389.ref045">45</xref>]. Again, the trends in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen.1008389.g004">Fig 4G</xref> disappeared (unlinked vs. linked: <italic>P</italic> = 0.48, one-tailed Mann-Whitney <italic>U</italic> test; unlinked vs evolved linked: <italic>P</italic> = 0.89, one-tailed Mann-Whitney <italic>U</italic> test). These results support our hypothesis about the role of H1 histones in the linkage effect of expression co-fluctuation.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec006" sec-type="conclusions">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>Using allele-specific single-cell RNA-seq data, we discovered chromosome-wide expression co-fluctuation of linked genes in mammalian cells. We hypothesize and provide evidence that genes on the same chromosome tend to have close 3D proximity, which results in a shared chemical environment for transcription and leads to expression co-fluctuation. While the linkage effect on expression co-fluctuation is likely an intrinsic cellular property, when the expression co-fluctuation of certain genes improves fitness, natural selection may drive the relocation of these genes to the same chromosome. Indeed, we provide evidence suggesting that the chromosomal linkage of genes encoding protein complex subunits is beneficial owing to the resultant expression co-fluctuation that minimizes the dosage imbalance among these subunits and has been selected for in genome evolution.</p>
<p>Although many statistical results in this study are highly significant, the effect sizes appear small in several analyses, most notably the <italic>&#948;</italic><sub>e</sub> and <italic>&#948;</italic><sub>a</sub> values for linked genes. The small effect sizes are generally due to the large noise in the data, less ideal types of data used, and mismatches between the data sets co-analyzed. For instance, <italic>&#948;</italic><sub>e</sub> between linked genes estimated here (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen.1008389.g002">Fig 2D</xref>) is much smaller than what was previously estimated for a pair of linked florescent protein genes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1008389.ref021">21</xref>], due in a large part to the inherently large error in quantifying mRNA concentrations by single-cell RNA-seq [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1008389.ref058">58</xref>]. The small size of <italic>&#948;</italic><sub>a</sub> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen.1008389.g003">Fig 3E</xref>) is likely caused at least in part by the low efficiency of ATAC-seq in detecting open chromatin (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="sec007">Materials and Methods</xref>). The positive correlation between <italic>trans</italic>-<italic>r</italic><sub>a</sub> and <italic>trans</italic>-<italic>r</italic><sub>e</sub> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen.1008389.g003">Fig 3G</xref>) is likely an underestimate due to the use of different cell types in RNA-seq and ATAC-seq. As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen.1008389.g002">Fig 2E and 2F</xref>, the actual effect sizes would be much larger should better experimental methods and/or data become available. Hence, it is likely that many effects are underestimated in this study. Indeed, we estimated that the true effect sizes of <italic>&#948;</italic><sub>e</sub> and <italic>&#948;</italic><sub>a</sub> are at least an order of magnitude larger than observed (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="sec007">Materials and Methods</xref>). In addition, the co-fluctuation effect detected by Raj et al. may be unusually large because in that study the chromosomal distance between the two genes was extremely small and the two genes used identical regulatory elements [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1008389.ref021">21</xref>]. Regardless, we stress that whether an effect is large/important depends on whether it is detectable by natural selection, and our results in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen.1008389.g004">Fig 4</xref> suggest that the effects appear visible to natural selection, as reflected in the preferential chromosomal linkage of genes encoding protein complex subunits. Note that natural selection can detect a selective differential as small as the inverse of the effective population size, which is about 70,000 in mouse [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1008389.ref059">59</xref>].</p>
<p>Because the expression co-fluctuation of two genes can be achieved by the sharing of regulatory elements and/or linkage, it is important to understand the relative contributions of the two mechanisms. But this question is generally difficult to answer because the extent to which two genes share regulatory elements is usually unknown. However, a lower bound contribution of the linkage effect can be estimated by examining two (equally regulated) alleles of the same gene. In this extreme case, the contribution of the linkage effect on expression co-fluctuation is about one thirteenth the contribution of sharing regulatory elements (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="sec007">Materials and Methods</xref>). Although linkage likely makes a smaller contribution than regulatory element sharing to the expression co-fluctuation of genes, linkage can increase the expression co-fluctuation to a level that regulatory element sharing alone cannot reach. This additional improvement can be important under certain circumstances, as shown recently for genes encoding enzymes of the yeast galactose use pathway [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1008389.ref060">60</xref>].</p>
<p>Because we used RNA-seq to measure expression co-fluctuation, our results apply to the co-fluctuation of mRNA concentrations. In the case of protein complex components, it is presumably the co-fluctuation of protein concentrations rather than mRNA concentrations that is directly beneficial. Although the degree of covariation between mRNA and protein concentrations is under debate [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1008389.ref061">61</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1008389.ref062">62</xref>], the two concentrations correlate well at the steady state [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1008389.ref021">21</xref>]. One key factor in this correlation is the protein half-life, because, when the protein half-life is long, mRNA and protein concentrations may not correlate well due to the delay in the effect of a change in mRNA concentration on protein concentration [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1008389.ref021">21</xref>]. It is interesting to note that in Raj et al.'s study [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1008389.ref021">21</xref>], mRNA and protein concentrations still correlate reasonably well (<italic>r</italic> = 0.43) when the protein half-life is 25 hours, which is much longer than the reported mean protein half-life of 9 hours in mammalian cells [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1008389.ref063">63</xref>]. Corroborating this finding is the recent report [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1008389.ref064">64</xref>] that mRNA and protein concentrations correlate well across single cells in the steady state (mean <italic>r</italic> = 0.732). Note that, although the correlation between mRNA and protein concentrations measured at the same moment may not be high when the protein half-life is long, the current protein level can still correlate well with a past mRNA level [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1008389.ref065">65</xref>]. Because our study focuses on cells at the steady state, co-fluctuation of mRNA concentrations is expected to lead to co-fluctuation of protein concentrations.</p>
<p>We attributed the preferential linkage of genes encoding protein complex subunits to the benefit of expression co-fluctuation, while a similar phenomenon of linkage was previously reported in yeast and attributed to the potential benefit of co-expression of protein complex subunits across environments [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1008389.ref066">66</xref>], where co-expression refers to the correlation in mean expression level. In mammalian cells, our hypothesis is more plausible than the co-expression hypothesis for five reasons. First, across-environment (or among-tissue) variation in mean mRNA concentration does not translate well to the corresponding variation in mean protein concentration [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1008389.ref062">62</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1008389.ref067">67</xref>], but mRNA concentration fluctuation explains protein concentration fluctuation quite well [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1008389.ref021">21</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1008389.ref064">64</xref>]. Hence, gene linkage, which enhances mRNA concentration co-fluctuation and by extension protein concentration co-fluctuation, may not improve protein co-expression across environments. Second, co-expression of linked genes appears to occur at a much smaller genomic distance than the linkage effect on co-fluctuation detected here [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1008389.ref068">68</xref>]. Thus, if selection on co-expression were the cause for the non-random distribution of protein complex genes, these genes should be closely linked. This, however, is not observed (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen.1008389.g004">Fig 4D</xref>). Hence, the previous finding that genes encoding members of (usually not the same) protein complexes tend to be clustered is best explained by the fact that certain chromosomal regions have inherently low expression noise and that these regions attract genes encoding protein complex members because stochastic expressions of these genes are especially harmful (i.e., the noise reduction hypothesis) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1008389.ref004">4</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1008389.ref069">69</xref>]. Third, the protein complex stoichiometry often differs among environments, which makes co-expression of complex components disfavored in the face of environmental changes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1008389.ref070">70</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1008389.ref071">71</xref>]. Nonetheless, under a given environment, protein concentration co-fluctuation remains beneficial because of the presence of an optimal stoichiometry at each steady state. Fourth, gene linkage is not necessary for the purpose of co-expression, because the genes involved can use similar <italic>cis</italic>-regulatory sequences to ensure co-expression even when they are unlinked. In fact, a large fraction of co-expression of linked genes is due to tandem duplicates [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1008389.ref068">68</xref>], which have similar regulatory sequences by descent. However, even for genes with the same regulatory sequences, linkage improves expression co-fluctuation at the steady state. Finally, the co-expression hypothesis or noise reduction hypothesis cannot explain our observation of the relationship between the expression levels of H1 histones and those of linked genes encoding protein complex members across tissues (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen.1008389.g004">Fig 4G</xref>). Taken together, these considerations suggest that it is most likely the selection for expression co-fluctuation rather than co-expression across environments that has driven the evolution of linkage of genes encoding members of the same protein complex.</p>
<p>Several previous studies reported long-range coordination of gene expression [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1008389.ref062">62</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1008389.ref072">72</xref>&#8211;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1008389.ref079">79</xref>], but most of them was about co-expression above explained. One study used fluorescent in situ hybridization of intronic RNA to detect nascent transcripts in individual cells [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1008389.ref072">72</xref>]. The authors reported independent transcriptions of most linked genes with the exception of two genes about 14 Mb apart that exhibit a negative correlation in transcription. Their observations are not contradictory to ours, because they measured the nearly instantaneous rate of transcription, whereas we measured the mRNA concentration that is the accumulated result of many transcriptional bursts. As explained, having a similar biochemical environment makes the activation/inactivation cycles of linked genes coordinated to some extent, even though the stochastic transcriptional bursts in the activation period may still look independent.</p>
<p>Our work suggests several future directions of research regarding expression co-fluctuation and its functional implications. First, it would be interesting to know if the linkage effect on expression co-fluctuation varies across chromosomes. Although we analyzed individual chromosomes (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1008389.s005">S5 Fig</xref>), addressing this question fully requires better single-cell expression data, because the current single-cell RNA-seq data are noisy. This also makes it difficult to detect any unusual chromosomal segment in its <italic>&#948;</italic><sub>e</sub> distribution. Second, our results suggest that 3D proximity is a major cause for the linkage effect on expression co-fluctuation. In particular, diffusion of proteins with intermediate diffusion coefficients such as H1 histones is likely one mechanistic basis of the effect. However, the diffusion behaviors of most proteins involved in transcription are largely unknown. A thorough research on the diffusion behaviors of proteins inside the nucleus will help us identify other proteins that are important in the linkage effect. As mentioned, our data do not allow a clear distinction between 3D looping and 3D diffusion in causing the linkage effect on tightly linked genes. To distinguish between these two mechanisms definitively, we would need allele-specific models of mouse chromosome conformation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1008389.ref080">80</xref>], which require more advanced algorithms and more sensitive allele-specific Hi-C methods. Third, our study highlights the importance of the impact of sub-nucleus spatial heterogeneity in gene expression. This can be studied more thoroughly via real-time imaging and spatial modeling of chemical reactions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1008389.ref043">43</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1008389.ref081">81</xref>]. The lack of knowledge about the details of transcription reactions prevents us from constructing an accurate quantitative model of gene expression, which can be achieved only by more accurate measurement and more advanced computational modeling. Fourth, we used protein complexes as an example to demonstrate how the linkage effect on expression co-fluctuation influences the evolution of gene order. Protein complex genes are by no means the only group of genes for which expression co-fluctuation can be advantageous. Previous work suggested that expression co-fluctuation of genes on the same signaling or metabolic pathway can be beneficial [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1008389.ref082">82</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1008389.ref083">83</xref>], which was recently experimentally confirmed for the yeast galactose catabolism pathway [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1008389.ref060">60</xref>]. But, to understand the broader evolutionary impact of the linkage effect, a general prediction of the fitness consequence of expression co-fluctuation is necessary. To achieve this goal, whole-cell modeling may be required [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1008389.ref084">84</xref>]. Note that some other mechanisms such as cell cycle [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1008389.ref085">85</xref>] can also lead to gene expression co-fluctuation, so should be considered in the study of the relationship between gene expression and fitness. Fifth, physical proximity might impact aspects of gene expression regulation other than co-fluctuation. For instance, previous research found that selective expression of genes that are clustered on the same chromosome (i.e., stochastic gene choice) is strongly dependent on intrachromosomal looping, which alters the pairwise physical distance between genes in the same gene array [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1008389.ref086">86</xref>&#8211;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1008389.ref088">88</xref>]. It will be interesting to explore whether the principle that governs the linkage effect studied here applies to stochastic gene choice. Sixth, because expression co-fluctuation could be beneficial or harmful, an alteration of expression co-fluctuation should be considered as a potential mechanism of disease caused by mutations that relocate genes in the genome. Seventh, our analysis focused on highly expressed genes more than lowly expressed ones due to the limited sensitivity of single-cell RNA-seq. Because lowly expressed genes are affected more than highly expressed genes by expression noise [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1008389.ref089">89</xref>], expression co-fluctuation may be more important to lowly expressed genes than highly expressed ones. More sensitive and accurate single-cell expression profiling methods are needed to study the expression co-fluctuation of lowly expressed genes. Eighth, we focused on mouse fibroblast cells because of the limited availability of allele-specific single-cell RNA-seq data. To study how expression co-fluctuation impacts the evolution of gene order, it will be important to have data from multiple cell types and species. Last but not least, as we start designing and synthesizing genomes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1008389.ref090">90</xref>], it will be important to consider how gene order affects expression co-fluctuation and potentially fitness. It is possible that the fitness effect associated with expression co-fluctuation is quite large when one compares an ideal gene order with a random one. It is our hope that our discovery will stimulate future researches in above areas.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec007" sec-type="materials|methods">
<title>Materials and methods</title>
<sec id="sec008">
<title>High-throughput sequencing data</title>
<p>The processed allele-specific single-cell RNA-seq data were downloaded from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://github.com/RickardSandberg/Reinius_et_al_Nature_Genetics_2016?files=1" ns0:type="simple">https://github.com/RickardSandberg/Reinius_et_al_Nature_Genetics_2016?files=1</ext-link> (mouse.c57.counts.rds and mouse.cast.counts.rds). The Hi-C data [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1008389.ref033">33</xref>] were downloaded from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/query/acc.cgi?acc=GSE72697" ns0:type="simple">https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/query/acc.cgi?acc=GSE72697</ext-link>, and we analyzed the 500kb-resolution Hi-C interaction matrix with high SNP density (iced-snpFiltered). The processed ATAC-seq data were provided by authors [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1008389.ref039">39</xref>], and the data from 16 NPC populations were analyzed. All analyses were performed using custom programs in R or python.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec009">
<title>Protein complex data and pre-processing</title>
<p>The mouse protein complex data were downloaded from the CORUM database (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://mips.helmholtz-muenchen.de/corum/" ns0:type="simple">http://mips.helmholtz-muenchen.de/corum/</ext-link>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1008389.ref091">91</xref>]. The coordinates for all mouse protein-coding genes were downloaded from Ensembl BioMart (GRC38m.p5) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1008389.ref052">52</xref>]. To produce duplicate-free gene pairs, we also downloaded all paralogous gene pairs from Ensembl BioMart. Note that these gene pairs can be redundant, meaning that a gene may be paralogous with multiple other genes and appear in multiple gene pairs. We then iteratively removed duplicate genes based on the following rules. First, if one gene in a pair of duplicate genes has been removed, the other gene is retained. Second, if neither gene in a duplicate pair has been removed and neither encodes a protein complex component, one of them is randomly removed. Third, if neither gene in a duplicate pair has been removed and only one of them encodes a protein complex member, we remove the other gene. Fourth, if neither gene in a duplicate pair has been removed and both genes encode protein complex components, one of them is randomly removed. Applying the above rules resulted in a set of duplicate-free genes with as many of them encoding protein complex members as possible.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec010">
<title>Gibbs sampling for testing protein complex-driven evolution of gene order</title>
<p>We obtained all mouse genes that have one-to-one orthologs in both human and rat, and acquired from Ensembl their chromosomal locations in human, mouse, and rat. Gene pairs are formed if their products belong to the same protein complex in human as well as mouse, based on protein complex information in the CORUM database mentioned above. Among them, 875 gene pairs from 342 genes are unlinked in both human and rat, of which 25 pairs become linked in mouse. To test whether the number 25 is more than expected by chance, we compared these 342 genes with a random set of 342 genes that also form 875 unlinked gene pairs in human and rat. These unlinked pairs are highly unlikely to encode members of the same complex, so serve as a negative control. Because of the difficulty in randomly sampling 342 genes that form 875 unlinked gene pairs, we adopted Gibbs sampling [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1008389.ref092">92</xref>], one kind of Markov-Chain Monte-Carlo sampling [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1008389.ref093">93</xref>]. The procedure was as follows. Starting from the observed 342 genes, represented by the vector of (gene 1, gene 2, &#8230;, gene 342), we swapped gene 1 with a randomly picked gene from the mouse genome such that the 342 genes still satisfied all conditions of the original 342 genes described above. We then similarly swapped gene 2, gene 3, &#8230;, and finally gene 342, at which point a new gene set was produced. To allow the Markov chain to reach the stationary phase, we discarded the first 1000 gene sets generated. Starting the 1001st gene set, we retained a set every 50 sets produced until 1000 sets were retained; this ensured relative independence among the 1000 retained sets. In each of these 1000 sets, we counted the number of gene pairs that are linked in mouse. The fraction of sets having the number equal to or greater than 25 was the probability reported in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen.1008389.g004">Fig 4F</xref>.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec011">
<title>Chromatin co-accessibility among cells vs. among cell populations</title>
<p>Let us consider the chromatin accessibilities of two genomic regions, <italic>A</italic> and <italic>B</italic>, in a population of <italic>N</italic> cells (<italic>N</italic> = 50,000 in the data analyzed) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1008389.ref039">39</xref>]. Let us denote the chromatin accessibilities for the two regions in cell <italic>i</italic> by random variables <italic>A</italic><sub><italic>i</italic></sub> and <italic>B</italic><sub><italic>i</italic></sub>, respectively, where <italic>i =</italic> 1, 2, 3, &#8230;, and <italic>N</italic>. We further denote the corresponding total accessibilities in the population as random variables <italic>AT</italic> and <italic>BT</italic>, respectively. We assume that <italic>A</italic><sub><italic>i</italic></sub> follows the distribution <italic>X</italic>, while <italic>B</italic><sub><italic>i</italic></sub> follows the distribution <italic>Y</italic>. We then have the following equations.
<disp-formula id="pgen.1008389.e003">
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pgen.1008389.e003g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" ns0:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1008389.e003" ns0:type="simple" />
<ns1:math display="block" id="M3">
<ns1:mrow><ns1:mi>A</ns1:mi><ns1:mi>T</ns1:mi><ns1:mo>=</ns1:mo><ns1:mstyle displaystyle="false"><ns1:msubsup><ns1:mo>&#8721;</ns1:mo><ns1:mrow><ns1:mi>i</ns1:mi><ns1:mo>=</ns1:mo><ns1:mn>1</ns1:mn></ns1:mrow><ns1:mi>N</ns1:mi></ns1:msubsup></ns1:mstyle><ns1:msub><ns1:mi>A</ns1:mi><ns1:mi>i</ns1:mi></ns1:msub><ns1:mspace width="0.25em" /><ns1:mi mathvariant="normal">and</ns1:mi><ns1:mspace width="0.25em" /><ns1:mi>B</ns1:mi><ns1:mi>T</ns1:mi><ns1:mo>=</ns1:mo><ns1:mstyle displaystyle="false"><ns1:msubsup><ns1:mo>&#8721;</ns1:mo><ns1:mrow><ns1:mi>i</ns1:mi><ns1:mo>=</ns1:mo><ns1:mn>1</ns1:mn></ns1:mrow><ns1:mi>N</ns1:mi></ns1:msubsup></ns1:mstyle><ns1:msub><ns1:mi>B</ns1:mi><ns1:mi>i</ns1:mi></ns1:msub><ns1:mo>.</ns1:mo></ns1:mrow>
</ns1:math>
</alternatives>
<label>(1)</label>
</disp-formula>
Pearson's correlation between <italic>AT</italic> and <italic>BT</italic> across cell populations all of size <italic>N</italic> is
<disp-formula id="pgen.1008389.e004">
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pgen.1008389.e004g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" ns0:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1008389.e004" ns0:type="simple" />
<ns1:math display="block" id="M4">
<ns1:mrow><ns1:mi>C</ns1:mi><ns1:mi>o</ns1:mi><ns1:mi>r</ns1:mi><ns1:mi>r</ns1:mi><ns1:mrow><ns1:mo>(</ns1:mo><ns1:mrow><ns1:mi>A</ns1:mi><ns1:mi>T</ns1:mi><ns1:mo>,</ns1:mo><ns1:mi>B</ns1:mi><ns1:mi>T</ns1:mi></ns1:mrow><ns1:mo>)</ns1:mo></ns1:mrow><ns1:mo>=</ns1:mo><ns1:mfrac><ns1:mrow><ns1:mi>E</ns1:mi><ns1:mrow><ns1:mo>(</ns1:mo><ns1:mrow><ns1:mi>A</ns1:mi><ns1:mi>T</ns1:mi><ns1:mo>&#8901;</ns1:mo><ns1:mi>B</ns1:mi><ns1:mi>T</ns1:mi></ns1:mrow><ns1:mo>)</ns1:mo></ns1:mrow><ns1:mo>&#8722;</ns1:mo><ns1:mi>E</ns1:mi><ns1:mrow><ns1:mo>(</ns1:mo><ns1:mrow><ns1:mi>A</ns1:mi><ns1:mi>T</ns1:mi></ns1:mrow><ns1:mo>)</ns1:mo></ns1:mrow><ns1:mi>E</ns1:mi><ns1:mrow><ns1:mo>(</ns1:mo><ns1:mrow><ns1:mi>B</ns1:mi><ns1:mi>T</ns1:mi></ns1:mrow><ns1:mo>)</ns1:mo></ns1:mrow></ns1:mrow><ns1:mrow><ns1:msqrt><ns1:mrow><ns1:mi>V</ns1:mi><ns1:mi>a</ns1:mi><ns1:mi>r</ns1:mi><ns1:mrow><ns1:mo>(</ns1:mo><ns1:mrow><ns1:mi>A</ns1:mi><ns1:mi>T</ns1:mi></ns1:mrow><ns1:mo>)</ns1:mo></ns1:mrow><ns1:mi>V</ns1:mi><ns1:mi>a</ns1:mi><ns1:mi>r</ns1:mi><ns1:mrow><ns1:mo>(</ns1:mo><ns1:mrow><ns1:mi>B</ns1:mi><ns1:mi>T</ns1:mi></ns1:mrow><ns1:mo>)</ns1:mo></ns1:mrow></ns1:mrow></ns1:msqrt></ns1:mrow></ns1:mfrac><ns1:mo>=</ns1:mo><ns1:mfrac><ns1:mrow><ns1:mi>E</ns1:mi><ns1:mo stretchy="false">(</ns1:mo><ns1:msubsup><ns1:mo>&#8721;</ns1:mo><ns1:mrow><ns1:mi>i</ns1:mi><ns1:mo>=</ns1:mo><ns1:mn>1</ns1:mn></ns1:mrow><ns1:mi>N</ns1:mi></ns1:msubsup><ns1:msubsup><ns1:mo>&#8721;</ns1:mo><ns1:mrow><ns1:mi>j</ns1:mi><ns1:mo>=</ns1:mo><ns1:mn>1</ns1:mn></ns1:mrow><ns1:mi>N</ns1:mi></ns1:msubsup><ns1:msub><ns1:mi>A</ns1:mi><ns1:mi>i</ns1:mi></ns1:msub><ns1:msub><ns1:mi>B</ns1:mi><ns1:mi>j</ns1:mi></ns1:msub><ns1:mo stretchy="false">)</ns1:mo><ns1:mo>&#8722;</ns1:mo><ns1:msup><ns1:mi>N</ns1:mi><ns1:mn>2</ns1:mn></ns1:msup><ns1:mi>E</ns1:mi><ns1:mrow><ns1:mo>(</ns1:mo><ns1:mi>X</ns1:mi><ns1:mo>)</ns1:mo></ns1:mrow><ns1:mi>E</ns1:mi><ns1:mrow><ns1:mo>(</ns1:mo><ns1:mi>Y</ns1:mi><ns1:mo>)</ns1:mo></ns1:mrow></ns1:mrow><ns1:mrow><ns1:msqrt><ns1:mrow><ns1:msup><ns1:mi>N</ns1:mi><ns1:mn>2</ns1:mn></ns1:msup><ns1:mi>V</ns1:mi><ns1:mi>a</ns1:mi><ns1:mi>r</ns1:mi><ns1:mrow><ns1:mo>(</ns1:mo><ns1:mi>X</ns1:mi><ns1:mo>)</ns1:mo></ns1:mrow><ns1:mi>V</ns1:mi><ns1:mi>a</ns1:mi><ns1:mi>r</ns1:mi><ns1:mrow><ns1:mo>(</ns1:mo><ns1:mi>Y</ns1:mi><ns1:mo>)</ns1:mo></ns1:mrow></ns1:mrow></ns1:msqrt></ns1:mrow></ns1:mfrac><ns1:mo>=</ns1:mo><ns1:mfrac><ns1:mrow><ns1:msubsup><ns1:mo>&#8721;</ns1:mo><ns1:mrow><ns1:mi>i</ns1:mi><ns1:mo>=</ns1:mo><ns1:mn>1</ns1:mn></ns1:mrow><ns1:mi>N</ns1:mi></ns1:msubsup><ns1:msubsup><ns1:mo>&#8721;</ns1:mo><ns1:mrow><ns1:mi>j</ns1:mi><ns1:mo>=</ns1:mo><ns1:mn>1</ns1:mn></ns1:mrow><ns1:mi>N</ns1:mi></ns1:msubsup><ns1:mi>E</ns1:mi><ns1:mrow><ns1:mo>(</ns1:mo><ns1:mrow><ns1:msub><ns1:mi>A</ns1:mi><ns1:mi>i</ns1:mi></ns1:msub><ns1:msub><ns1:mi>B</ns1:mi><ns1:mi>j</ns1:mi></ns1:msub></ns1:mrow><ns1:mo>)</ns1:mo></ns1:mrow><ns1:mo>&#8722;</ns1:mo><ns1:msup><ns1:mi>N</ns1:mi><ns1:mn>2</ns1:mn></ns1:msup><ns1:mi>E</ns1:mi><ns1:mrow><ns1:mo>(</ns1:mo><ns1:mi>X</ns1:mi><ns1:mo>)</ns1:mo></ns1:mrow><ns1:mi>E</ns1:mi><ns1:mrow><ns1:mo>(</ns1:mo><ns1:mi>Y</ns1:mi><ns1:mo>)</ns1:mo></ns1:mrow></ns1:mrow><ns1:mrow><ns1:mi>N</ns1:mi><ns1:msqrt><ns1:mrow><ns1:mi>V</ns1:mi><ns1:mi>a</ns1:mi><ns1:mi>r</ns1:mi><ns1:mrow><ns1:mo>(</ns1:mo><ns1:mi>X</ns1:mi><ns1:mo>)</ns1:mo></ns1:mrow><ns1:mi>V</ns1:mi><ns1:mi>a</ns1:mi><ns1:mi>r</ns1:mi><ns1:mrow><ns1:mo>(</ns1:mo><ns1:mi>Y</ns1:mi><ns1:mo>)</ns1:mo></ns1:mrow></ns1:mrow></ns1:msqrt></ns1:mrow></ns1:mfrac><ns1:mo>.</ns1:mo></ns1:mrow>
</ns1:math>
</alternatives>
<label>(2)</label>
</disp-formula>
Because cells are independent from one another, when <italic>i</italic> &#8800; <italic>j</italic>,
<disp-formula id="pgen.1008389.e005">
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pgen.1008389.e005g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" ns0:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1008389.e005" ns0:type="simple" />
<ns1:math display="block" id="M5">
<ns1:mrow><ns1:mi>E</ns1:mi><ns1:mrow><ns1:mo>(</ns1:mo><ns1:mrow><ns1:msub><ns1:mi>A</ns1:mi><ns1:mi>i</ns1:mi></ns1:msub><ns1:msub><ns1:mi>B</ns1:mi><ns1:mi>j</ns1:mi></ns1:msub></ns1:mrow><ns1:mo>)</ns1:mo></ns1:mrow><ns1:mo>=</ns1:mo><ns1:mi>E</ns1:mi><ns1:mrow><ns1:mo>(</ns1:mo><ns1:mrow><ns1:msub><ns1:mi>A</ns1:mi><ns1:mi>i</ns1:mi></ns1:msub></ns1:mrow><ns1:mo>)</ns1:mo></ns1:mrow><ns1:mi>E</ns1:mi><ns1:mrow><ns1:mo>(</ns1:mo><ns1:mrow><ns1:msub><ns1:mi>B</ns1:mi><ns1:mi>j</ns1:mi></ns1:msub></ns1:mrow><ns1:mo>)</ns1:mo></ns1:mrow><ns1:mo>.</ns1:mo></ns1:mrow>
</ns1:math>
</alternatives>
<label>(3)</label>
</disp-formula>
Thus,
<disp-formula id="pgen.1008389.e006">
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pgen.1008389.e006g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" ns0:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1008389.e006" ns0:type="simple" />
<ns1:math display="block" id="M6">
<ns1:mrow><ns1:msubsup><ns1:mstyle displaystyle="false"><ns1:mo>&#8721;</ns1:mo></ns1:mstyle><ns1:mrow><ns1:mi>i</ns1:mi><ns1:mo>=</ns1:mo><ns1:mn>1</ns1:mn></ns1:mrow><ns1:mi>N</ns1:mi></ns1:msubsup><ns1:msubsup><ns1:mstyle displaystyle="false"><ns1:mo>&#8721;</ns1:mo></ns1:mstyle><ns1:mrow><ns1:mi>j</ns1:mi><ns1:mo>=</ns1:mo><ns1:mn>1</ns1:mn></ns1:mrow><ns1:mi>N</ns1:mi></ns1:msubsup><ns1:mi>E</ns1:mi><ns1:mrow><ns1:mo>(</ns1:mo><ns1:mrow><ns1:msub><ns1:mi>A</ns1:mi><ns1:mi>i</ns1:mi></ns1:msub><ns1:msub><ns1:mi>B</ns1:mi><ns1:mi>j</ns1:mi></ns1:msub></ns1:mrow><ns1:mo>)</ns1:mo></ns1:mrow><ns1:mo>=</ns1:mo><ns1:msubsup><ns1:mstyle displaystyle="false"><ns1:mo>&#8721;</ns1:mo></ns1:mstyle><ns1:mrow><ns1:mi>i</ns1:mi><ns1:mo>=</ns1:mo><ns1:mn>1</ns1:mn></ns1:mrow><ns1:mi>N</ns1:mi></ns1:msubsup><ns1:mi>E</ns1:mi><ns1:mo stretchy="false">(</ns1:mo><ns1:msub><ns1:mi>A</ns1:mi><ns1:mi>i</ns1:mi></ns1:msub><ns1:msub><ns1:mi>B</ns1:mi><ns1:mi>i</ns1:mi></ns1:msub><ns1:mo stretchy="false">)</ns1:mo><ns1:mo>+</ns1:mo><ns1:msubsup><ns1:mstyle displaystyle="false"><ns1:mo>&#8721;</ns1:mo></ns1:mstyle><ns1:mrow><ns1:mi>i</ns1:mi><ns1:mo>=</ns1:mo><ns1:mn>1</ns1:mn></ns1:mrow><ns1:mi>N</ns1:mi></ns1:msubsup><ns1:msubsup><ns1:mstyle displaystyle="false"><ns1:mo>&#8721;</ns1:mo></ns1:mstyle><ns1:mrow><ns1:mtable><ns1:mtr><ns1:mtd><ns1:mrow><ns1:mi>j</ns1:mi><ns1:mo>=</ns1:mo><ns1:mn>1</ns1:mn></ns1:mrow></ns1:mtd></ns1:mtr><ns1:mtr><ns1:mtd><ns1:mrow><ns1:mi>j</ns1:mi><ns1:mo>&#8800;</ns1:mo><ns1:mi>i</ns1:mi></ns1:mrow></ns1:mtd></ns1:mtr></ns1:mtable></ns1:mrow><ns1:mi>N</ns1:mi></ns1:msubsup><ns1:mi>E</ns1:mi><ns1:mrow><ns1:mo>(</ns1:mo><ns1:mrow><ns1:msub><ns1:mi>A</ns1:mi><ns1:mi>i</ns1:mi></ns1:msub></ns1:mrow><ns1:mo>)</ns1:mo></ns1:mrow><ns1:mi>E</ns1:mi><ns1:mrow><ns1:mo>(</ns1:mo><ns1:mrow><ns1:msub><ns1:mi>B</ns1:mi><ns1:mi>i</ns1:mi></ns1:msub></ns1:mrow><ns1:mo>)</ns1:mo></ns1:mrow><ns1:mo>=</ns1:mo><ns1:mi>N</ns1:mi><ns1:mi>E</ns1:mi><ns1:mrow><ns1:mo>(</ns1:mo><ns1:mrow><ns1:mi>X</ns1:mi><ns1:mi>Y</ns1:mi></ns1:mrow><ns1:mo>)</ns1:mo></ns1:mrow><ns1:mo>+</ns1:mo><ns1:mrow><ns1:mo>(</ns1:mo><ns1:mrow><ns1:msup><ns1:mi>N</ns1:mi><ns1:mn>2</ns1:mn></ns1:msup><ns1:mo>&#8722;</ns1:mo><ns1:mi>N</ns1:mi></ns1:mrow><ns1:mo>)</ns1:mo></ns1:mrow><ns1:mi>E</ns1:mi><ns1:mrow><ns1:mo>(</ns1:mo><ns1:mi>X</ns1:mi><ns1:mo>)</ns1:mo></ns1:mrow><ns1:mi>E</ns1:mi><ns1:mrow><ns1:mo>(</ns1:mo><ns1:mi>Y</ns1:mi><ns1:mo>)</ns1:mo></ns1:mrow><ns1:mo>.</ns1:mo></ns1:mrow>
</ns1:math>
</alternatives>
<label>(4)</label>
</disp-formula>
Combining Eq (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pgen.1008389.e004">2</xref>) with Eq (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pgen.1008389.e006">4</xref>), we have
<disp-formula id="pgen.1008389.e007">
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pgen.1008389.e007g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" ns0:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1008389.e007" ns0:type="simple" />
<ns1:math display="block" id="M7">
<ns1:mrow><ns1:mi>C</ns1:mi><ns1:mi>o</ns1:mi><ns1:mi>r</ns1:mi><ns1:mi>r</ns1:mi><ns1:mrow><ns1:mo>(</ns1:mo><ns1:mrow><ns1:mi>A</ns1:mi><ns1:mi>T</ns1:mi><ns1:mo>,</ns1:mo><ns1:mi>B</ns1:mi><ns1:mi>T</ns1:mi></ns1:mrow><ns1:mo>)</ns1:mo></ns1:mrow><ns1:mo>=</ns1:mo><ns1:mfrac><ns1:mrow><ns1:mi>N</ns1:mi><ns1:mi>E</ns1:mi><ns1:mrow><ns1:mo>(</ns1:mo><ns1:mrow><ns1:mi>X</ns1:mi><ns1:mi>Y</ns1:mi></ns1:mrow><ns1:mo>)</ns1:mo></ns1:mrow><ns1:mo>&#8722;</ns1:mo><ns1:mi>N</ns1:mi><ns1:mi>E</ns1:mi><ns1:mrow><ns1:mo>(</ns1:mo><ns1:mi>X</ns1:mi><ns1:mo>)</ns1:mo></ns1:mrow><ns1:mi>E</ns1:mi><ns1:mrow><ns1:mo>(</ns1:mo><ns1:mi>Y</ns1:mi><ns1:mo>)</ns1:mo></ns1:mrow></ns1:mrow><ns1:mrow><ns1:mi>N</ns1:mi><ns1:msqrt><ns1:mrow><ns1:mi>V</ns1:mi><ns1:mi>a</ns1:mi><ns1:mi>r</ns1:mi><ns1:mrow><ns1:mo>(</ns1:mo><ns1:mi>A</ns1:mi><ns1:mo>)</ns1:mo></ns1:mrow><ns1:mo>&#8901;</ns1:mo><ns1:mi>V</ns1:mi><ns1:mi>a</ns1:mi><ns1:mi>r</ns1:mi><ns1:mrow><ns1:mo>(</ns1:mo><ns1:mi>B</ns1:mi><ns1:mo>)</ns1:mo></ns1:mrow></ns1:mrow></ns1:msqrt></ns1:mrow></ns1:mfrac><ns1:mo>=</ns1:mo><ns1:mfrac><ns1:mrow><ns1:mi>E</ns1:mi><ns1:mrow><ns1:mo>(</ns1:mo><ns1:mrow><ns1:mi>X</ns1:mi><ns1:mi>Y</ns1:mi></ns1:mrow><ns1:mo>)</ns1:mo></ns1:mrow><ns1:mo>&#8722;</ns1:mo><ns1:mi>E</ns1:mi><ns1:mrow><ns1:mo>(</ns1:mo><ns1:mi>X</ns1:mi><ns1:mo>)</ns1:mo></ns1:mrow><ns1:mi>E</ns1:mi><ns1:mrow><ns1:mo>(</ns1:mo><ns1:mi>Y</ns1:mi><ns1:mo>)</ns1:mo></ns1:mrow></ns1:mrow><ns1:mrow><ns1:msqrt><ns1:mrow><ns1:mi>V</ns1:mi><ns1:mi>a</ns1:mi><ns1:mi>r</ns1:mi><ns1:mrow><ns1:mo>(</ns1:mo><ns1:mi>X</ns1:mi><ns1:mo>)</ns1:mo></ns1:mrow><ns1:mo>&#8901;</ns1:mo><ns1:mi>V</ns1:mi><ns1:mi>a</ns1:mi><ns1:mi>r</ns1:mi><ns1:mrow><ns1:mo>(</ns1:mo><ns1:mi>Y</ns1:mi><ns1:mo>)</ns1:mo></ns1:mrow></ns1:mrow></ns1:msqrt></ns1:mrow></ns1:mfrac><ns1:mo>=</ns1:mo><ns1:mi>C</ns1:mi><ns1:mi>o</ns1:mi><ns1:mi>r</ns1:mi><ns1:mi>r</ns1:mi><ns1:mrow><ns1:mo>(</ns1:mo><ns1:mrow><ns1:mi>X</ns1:mi><ns1:mo>,</ns1:mo><ns1:mi>Y</ns1:mi></ns1:mrow><ns1:mo>)</ns1:mo></ns1:mrow><ns1:mo>.</ns1:mo></ns1:mrow>
</ns1:math>
</alternatives>
<label>(5)</label>
</disp-formula>
Hence, if the number of cells per population is a constant and there is no measurement error, correlation of chromatin accessibilities of two loci among cells is expected to equal the correlation of total chromatin accessibilities per population of cells among cell populations.</p>
<p>To examine how violations of some of the above conditions affect the accuracy of Eq (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pgen.1008389.e007">5</xref>), we conducted computer simulations. We assume that the accessibility of a genomic region in a single cell is either 1 (accessible) or 0 (inaccessible). This assumption is supported by previous single-cell ATAC-seq data [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1008389.ref040">40</xref>], where the number of reads mapped to each peak in a cell is nearly binary. Now let us consider two genomic regions whose chromatin states are denoted by <italic>A</italic> and <italic>B</italic>, respectively. The probabilities of the four possible states of this system are as follows.
<disp-formula id="pgen.1008389.e008">
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pgen.1008389.e008g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" ns0:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1008389.e008" ns0:type="simple" />
<ns1:math display="block" id="M8">
<ns1:mrow><ns1:mtable columnalign="left"><ns1:mtr><ns1:mtd><ns1:mspace width="2.5em" /><ns1:mrow><ns1:mi mathvariant="normal">Pr</ns1:mi><ns1:mrow><ns1:mo>(</ns1:mo><ns1:mrow><ns1:mi>A</ns1:mi><ns1:mo>=</ns1:mo><ns1:mn>0</ns1:mn><ns1:mo>,</ns1:mo><ns1:mi>B</ns1:mi><ns1:mo>=</ns1:mo><ns1:mn>0</ns1:mn></ns1:mrow><ns1:mo>)</ns1:mo></ns1:mrow><ns1:mo>=</ns1:mo><ns1:mi>p</ns1:mi><ns1:mo>,</ns1:mo></ns1:mrow></ns1:mtd></ns1:mtr><ns1:mtr><ns1:mtd><ns1:mspace width="2.5em" /><ns1:mrow><ns1:mi mathvariant="normal">Pr</ns1:mi><ns1:mrow><ns1:mo>(</ns1:mo><ns1:mrow><ns1:mi>A</ns1:mi><ns1:mo>=</ns1:mo><ns1:mn>0</ns1:mn><ns1:mo>,</ns1:mo><ns1:mi>B</ns1:mi><ns1:mo>=</ns1:mo><ns1:mn>1</ns1:mn></ns1:mrow><ns1:mo>)</ns1:mo></ns1:mrow><ns1:mo>=</ns1:mo><ns1:mi>q</ns1:mi><ns1:mo>,</ns1:mo></ns1:mrow></ns1:mtd></ns1:mtr><ns1:mtr><ns1:mtd><ns1:mspace width="2.5em" /><ns1:mrow><ns1:mi mathvariant="normal">Pr</ns1:mi><ns1:mrow><ns1:mo>(</ns1:mo><ns1:mrow><ns1:mi>A</ns1:mi><ns1:mo>=</ns1:mo><ns1:mn>1</ns1:mn><ns1:mo>,</ns1:mo><ns1:mi>B</ns1:mi><ns1:mo>=</ns1:mo><ns1:mn>0</ns1:mn></ns1:mrow><ns1:mo>)</ns1:mo></ns1:mrow><ns1:mo>=</ns1:mo><ns1:mi>r</ns1:mi><ns1:mo>,</ns1:mo></ns1:mrow></ns1:mtd></ns1:mtr><ns1:mtr><ns1:mtd><ns1:mrow><ns1:mi mathvariant="normal">and</ns1:mi><ns1:mspace width="1em" /><ns1:mi mathvariant="normal">Pr</ns1:mi><ns1:mrow><ns1:mo>(</ns1:mo><ns1:mrow><ns1:mi>A</ns1:mi><ns1:mo>=</ns1:mo><ns1:mn>1</ns1:mn><ns1:mo>,</ns1:mo><ns1:mi>B</ns1:mi><ns1:mo>=</ns1:mo><ns1:mn>1</ns1:mn></ns1:mrow><ns1:mo>)</ns1:mo></ns1:mrow><ns1:mo>=</ns1:mo><ns1:mi>s</ns1:mi><ns1:mo>,</ns1:mo></ns1:mrow></ns1:mtd></ns1:mtr></ns1:mtable></ns1:mrow>
</ns1:math>
</alternatives>
<label>(6)</label>
</disp-formula>
where <italic>p</italic> + <italic>q</italic> + <italic>r</italic> + <italic>s</italic> = 1. Hence, we have
<disp-formula id="pgen.1008389.e009">
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pgen.1008389.e009g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" ns0:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1008389.e009" ns0:type="simple" />
<ns1:math display="block" id="M9">
<ns1:mrow><ns1:mtable columnalign="left"><ns1:mtr><ns1:mtd><ns1:mrow><ns1:mi>E</ns1:mi><ns1:mrow><ns1:mo>(</ns1:mo><ns1:mi>A</ns1:mi><ns1:mo>)</ns1:mo></ns1:mrow><ns1:mo>=</ns1:mo><ns1:mi>r</ns1:mi><ns1:mo>+</ns1:mo><ns1:mi>s</ns1:mi><ns1:mo>,</ns1:mo></ns1:mrow></ns1:mtd></ns1:mtr><ns1:mtr><ns1:mtd><ns1:mrow><ns1:mi>E</ns1:mi><ns1:mrow><ns1:mo>(</ns1:mo><ns1:mi>B</ns1:mi><ns1:mo>)</ns1:mo></ns1:mrow><ns1:mo>=</ns1:mo><ns1:mi>q</ns1:mi><ns1:mo>+</ns1:mo><ns1:mi>s</ns1:mi><ns1:mo>,</ns1:mo></ns1:mrow></ns1:mtd></ns1:mtr><ns1:mtr><ns1:mtd><ns1:mrow><ns1:mi>E</ns1:mi><ns1:mrow><ns1:mo>(</ns1:mo><ns1:mrow><ns1:mi>A</ns1:mi><ns1:mi>B</ns1:mi></ns1:mrow><ns1:mo>)</ns1:mo></ns1:mrow><ns1:mo>=</ns1:mo><ns1:mi>s</ns1:mi><ns1:mo>,</ns1:mo></ns1:mrow></ns1:mtd></ns1:mtr><ns1:mtr><ns1:mtd><ns1:mrow><ns1:mi>V</ns1:mi><ns1:mi>a</ns1:mi><ns1:mi>r</ns1:mi><ns1:mrow><ns1:mo>(</ns1:mo><ns1:mi>A</ns1:mi><ns1:mo>)</ns1:mo></ns1:mrow><ns1:mo>=</ns1:mo><ns1:mrow><ns1:mo>(</ns1:mo><ns1:mrow><ns1:mi>r</ns1:mi><ns1:mo>+</ns1:mo><ns1:mi>s</ns1:mi></ns1:mrow><ns1:mo>)</ns1:mo></ns1:mrow><ns1:mrow><ns1:mo>(</ns1:mo><ns1:mrow><ns1:mi>p</ns1:mi><ns1:mo>+</ns1:mo><ns1:mi>q</ns1:mi></ns1:mrow><ns1:mo>)</ns1:mo></ns1:mrow><ns1:mo>,</ns1:mo></ns1:mrow></ns1:mtd></ns1:mtr><ns1:mtr><ns1:mtd><ns1:mrow><ns1:mi>V</ns1:mi><ns1:mi>a</ns1:mi><ns1:mi>r</ns1:mi><ns1:mrow><ns1:mo>(</ns1:mo><ns1:mi>B</ns1:mi><ns1:mo>)</ns1:mo></ns1:mrow><ns1:mo>=</ns1:mo><ns1:mrow><ns1:mo>(</ns1:mo><ns1:mrow><ns1:mi>q</ns1:mi><ns1:mo>+</ns1:mo><ns1:mi>s</ns1:mi></ns1:mrow><ns1:mo>)</ns1:mo></ns1:mrow><ns1:mrow><ns1:mo>(</ns1:mo><ns1:mrow><ns1:mi>p</ns1:mi><ns1:mo>+</ns1:mo><ns1:mi>r</ns1:mi></ns1:mrow><ns1:mo>)</ns1:mo></ns1:mrow><ns1:mo>.</ns1:mo></ns1:mrow></ns1:mtd></ns1:mtr></ns1:mtable></ns1:mrow>
</ns1:math>
</alternatives>
<label>(7)</label>
</disp-formula>
With Eq (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pgen.1008389.e009">7</xref>), we can compute <italic>Corr</italic>(<italic>A</italic>,<italic>B</italic>). In other words, for any given set of <italic>p</italic>, <italic>q</italic>, <italic>r</italic>, and <italic>s</italic>, we can compute the among-cell correlation in chromatin accessibility between the two regions.</p>
<p>We then generated 10,000 random sets of <italic>p</italic>, <italic>q</italic>, <italic>r</italic>, <italic>s</italic> from a Dirichlet distribution. For each set of <italic>p</italic>, <italic>q</italic>, <italic>r</italic>, and <italic>s</italic>, we simulated the state of a cell by a random sampling from the four possible states. We did this for 16 cells as well as 16 cell populations each composed of 50,000 cells. We computed the total accessibility of each region in each cell population by summing up the corresponding accessibility of each cell. As expected, the among-cell correlation between the two regions in accessibility matches the true correlation (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1008389.s006">S6A Fig</xref>). The deviation from the true correlation is due to sampling error. Based on Eq (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pgen.1008389.e007">5</xref>), the among-cell-population correlation between the two regions in total accessibility approximates the true correlation, which is indeed observed in our simulation (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1008389.s006">S6B Fig</xref>).</p>
<p>Nevertheless, accessibility of a region may be undetected due to low detection efficiencies of high-throughput methods, which makes the observed correlation between the accessibilities of two regions lower than the true correlation. To assess the impact of such low detection efficiencies on the correlation, we simulated a scenario with a 10% detection efficiency, which is common in high-throughput methods [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1008389.ref058">58</xref>]. That is, for every accessible region, it is detected as accessible with a 10% chance and inaccessible with a 90% chance; every inaccessible region is detected as inaccessible with a 100% chance. Our simulation showed that the observed correlation between the accessibilities of two regions is weaker than the true correlation regardless of whether the data are from individual cells (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1008389.s006">S6C Fig</xref>) or cell populations (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1008389.s006">S6D Fig</xref>).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec012">
<title>True <italic>&#948;</italic><sub>a</sub> vs. observed <italic>&#948;</italic><sub>a</sub></title>
<p>The framework developed in the above section allows using computer simulation to acquire a lower-bound estimate of the true <italic>&#948;</italic><sub>a</sub>. We simulated <italic>&#948;</italic><sub>a</sub> by considering two pairs of regions simultaneously. For each pair of regions, we first randomly sampled <italic>p</italic>, <italic>q</italic>, <italic>r</italic>, and <italic>s</italic>, followed by the computation of the true correlation using Eq (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pgen.1008389.e009">7</xref>). The difference between the true correlations of the two pairs of regions is equivalent to the true <italic>&#948;</italic><sub>a.</sub> Then, for each pair of regions, we can obtain the estimated <italic>&#948;</italic><sub>a</sub> from estimated correlations using simulation. In our allele-specific ATAC-seq data, only 55% of all reads are allele-specific. Given that in high-throughput sequencing data, the detection efficiency is 10 to 20% when all reads are considered [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1008389.ref094">94</xref>], we choose 8.25% (= 0.15 &#215; 0.55) as the detection efficiency in our simulation. We repeated this procedure 10,000 times and plotted the result in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1008389.s007">S7A Fig</xref>. We inferred the corresponding true <italic>&#948;</italic><sub>a</sub> from the observed median <italic>&#948;</italic><sub>a</sub> in the actual data using the regression in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1008389.s007">S7A Fig</xref>.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec013">
<title>True <italic>&#948;</italic><sub>e</sub> vs. observed <italic>&#948;</italic><sub>e</sub></title>
<p>To obtain a lower-bound estimate of the true <italic>&#948;</italic><sub>e</sub>, we performed a simulation incorporating the known parameters of single-cell RNA-seq in our dataset. The simulation was performed as follows. First, we determined the mean expression levels for a pair of genes, <italic>A</italic> and <italic>B</italic>, by sampling from the distribution of mean expression levels of genes analyzed, which was obtained based on the estimation that 1 RPKM corresponds to 1 transcript per cell in the original dataset [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1008389.ref023">23</xref>]. Note that the mean expression level of each allele (<italic>A</italic><sub>1</sub>, <italic>A</italic><sub>2</sub>, <italic>B</italic><sub>1</sub>, and <italic>B</italic><sub>2</sub>) is one half the above sampled value. Second, we generated the expression levels across 60 cells for a pair of alleles (<italic>A</italic><sub>1</sub> and <italic>B</italic><sub>1</sub>) from the joint multivariate normal distribution. The multivariate normal distribution can be uniquely determined once the correlation coefficient between the two alleles and their CV are chosen. We fixed the CV of the two alleles at 0.5, based on sm-FISH experiments in mammalian cells for genes whose expression levels are similar to the genes we analyzed [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1008389.ref095">95</xref>]. Note that the CV used here is the mRNA CV, not the protein CV. The correlation between the two alleles was randomly sampled from the range (-1, 1). We name this correlation <italic>r</italic><sub>1</sub>. Third, for each allele in each cell, we used binomial sampling to determine the detected transcript level. In our data set, only 17% of the reads are allele-specific. Because the capturing efficiency is around 10&#8211;20% for full-length single cell RNA-seq data [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1008389.ref094">94</xref>], we used 2.55% (= 0.15 &#215; 0.17) as the sampling probability. Fourth, we computed the observed correlation between <italic>A</italic><sub>1</sub> and <italic>B</italic><sub>1</sub> across cells after binomial sampling. Fifth, we repeated the above steps 2 to 4. We named the newly sampled correlation <italic>r</italic><sub>2</sub>. The true <italic>&#948;</italic><sub>e</sub> would be <italic>r</italic><sub>1</sub>&#8722;<italic>r</italic><sub>2</sub>, and the observed <italic>&#948;</italic><sub>e</sub> is the difference between the observed correlations. Sixth, we repeated 10,000 times steps 1 to 5, with all true <italic>&#948;</italic><sub>e</sub> and observed <italic>&#948;</italic><sub>e</sub> recorded (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1008389.s007">S7B Fig</xref>). We inferred the corresponding true <italic>&#948;</italic><sub>e</sub> from the observed median <italic>&#948;</italic><sub>e</sub> in the actual data using the regression in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1008389.s007">S7B Fig</xref>.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec014">
<title>Simulation of protein complex concentrations</title>
<p>Let the concentration of protein complex AB be [AB]. To study the average [AB] across cells in a population, we first simulated the concentrations of subunit A and subunit B in each cell. We assumed that the total concentrations of A and B, denoted by [A]<sub>t</sub> and [B]<sub>t</sub> respectively, are both normally distributed with mean = 1 and <italic>CV</italic> = 0.2. We used <italic>CV</italic> = 0.2 because this is the median expression noise measured by <italic>CV</italic> for enzymes in yeast [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1008389.ref006">6</xref>], the only eukaryote with genome-wide protein expression noise data [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1008389.ref015">15</xref>]. Thus, the joint distribution of [A]<sub>t</sub> and [B]<sub>t</sub> is multivariate normal, which can be specified if the correlation (<italic>r</italic>) between [A]<sub>t</sub> and [B]<sub>t</sub> is known. With a given <italic>r</italic>, we simulated [A]<sub>t</sub> and [B]<sub>t</sub> for 10,000 cells by sampling from the joint distribution. We set the concentration to 0 if the simulated value is negative. We computed [AB] in each cell by solving the following set of equations.
<disp-formula id="pgen.1008389.e010">
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pgen.1008389.e010g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" ns0:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1008389.e010" ns0:type="simple" />
<ns1:math display="block" id="M10">
<ns1:msub><ns1:mrow><ns1:mo>[</ns1:mo><ns1:mi>A</ns1:mi><ns1:mo>]</ns1:mo></ns1:mrow><ns1:mrow><ns1:mi>t</ns1:mi></ns1:mrow></ns1:msub><ns1:mo>=</ns1:mo><ns1:mo>[</ns1:mo><ns1:mrow><ns1:mi>A</ns1:mi></ns1:mrow><ns1:mo>]</ns1:mo><ns1:mo>+</ns1:mo><ns1:mo>[</ns1:mo><ns1:mrow><ns1:mi>A</ns1:mi><ns1:mi>B</ns1:mi></ns1:mrow><ns1:mo>]</ns1:mo><ns1:mo>,</ns1:mo><ns1:mspace width="0.25em" /><ns1:msub><ns1:mrow><ns1:mo>[</ns1:mo><ns1:mi>B</ns1:mi><ns1:mo>]</ns1:mo></ns1:mrow><ns1:mrow><ns1:mi>t</ns1:mi></ns1:mrow></ns1:msub><ns1:mo>=</ns1:mo><ns1:mo>[</ns1:mo><ns1:mrow><ns1:mi>B</ns1:mi></ns1:mrow><ns1:mo>]</ns1:mo><ns1:mo>+</ns1:mo><ns1:mo>[</ns1:mo><ns1:mrow><ns1:mi>A</ns1:mi><ns1:mi>B</ns1:mi></ns1:mrow><ns1:mo>]</ns1:mo><ns1:mo>,</ns1:mo><ns1:mspace width="0.25em" /><ns1:mi mathvariant="normal">and</ns1:mi><ns1:mspace width="0.25em" /><ns1:mo>[</ns1:mo><ns1:mrow><ns1:mi>A</ns1:mi><ns1:mi>B</ns1:mi></ns1:mrow><ns1:mo>]</ns1:mo><ns1:mo>=</ns1:mo><ns1:mi>K</ns1:mi><ns1:mo>[</ns1:mo><ns1:mrow><ns1:mi>A</ns1:mi></ns1:mrow><ns1:mo>]</ns1:mo><ns1:mo>[</ns1:mo><ns1:mrow><ns1:mi>B</ns1:mi></ns1:mrow><ns1:mo>]</ns1:mo><ns1:mo>,</ns1:mo>
</ns1:math>
</alternatives>
<label>(8)</label>
</disp-formula>
where we used <italic>K</italic> = 10<sup>5</sup> based on the empirical values of association constants of stable protein complexes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1008389.ref049">49</xref>]. The mean complex concentration is the average [AB] among all cells. We also performed the simulation with other <italic>K</italic> values (10<sup>&#8722;2</sup>, 10<sup>&#8722;1</sup>, 10<sup>0</sup>, 10<sup>1</sup>, 10<sup>2</sup>, 10<sup>3</sup>, and 10<sup>4</sup>).</p>
<p>The above simulation can be extended for studying protein complexes with various stoichiometries. In general, for protein complex A<sub>M</sub>B<sub>N</sub>, we have
<disp-formula id="pgen.1008389.e011">
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pgen.1008389.e011g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" ns0:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1008389.e011" ns0:type="simple" />
<ns1:math display="block" id="M11">
<ns1:msub><ns1:mrow><ns1:mo>[</ns1:mo><ns1:mi>A</ns1:mi><ns1:mo>]</ns1:mo></ns1:mrow><ns1:mrow><ns1:mi>t</ns1:mi></ns1:mrow></ns1:msub><ns1:mo>=</ns1:mo><ns1:mo>[</ns1:mo><ns1:mrow><ns1:mi>A</ns1:mi></ns1:mrow><ns1:mo>]</ns1:mo><ns1:mo>+</ns1:mo><ns1:mi>M</ns1:mi><ns1:mo>[</ns1:mo><ns1:mrow><ns1:msub><ns1:mrow><ns1:mi>A</ns1:mi></ns1:mrow><ns1:mrow><ns1:mi>M</ns1:mi></ns1:mrow></ns1:msub><ns1:msub><ns1:mrow><ns1:mi>B</ns1:mi></ns1:mrow><ns1:mrow><ns1:mi>N</ns1:mi></ns1:mrow></ns1:msub></ns1:mrow><ns1:mo>]</ns1:mo><ns1:mo>,</ns1:mo><ns1:mspace width="0.25em" /><ns1:msub><ns1:mrow><ns1:mo>[</ns1:mo><ns1:mi>B</ns1:mi><ns1:mo>]</ns1:mo></ns1:mrow><ns1:mrow><ns1:mi>t</ns1:mi></ns1:mrow></ns1:msub><ns1:mo>=</ns1:mo><ns1:mo>[</ns1:mo><ns1:mrow><ns1:mi>B</ns1:mi></ns1:mrow><ns1:mo>]</ns1:mo><ns1:mo>+</ns1:mo><ns1:mi>N</ns1:mi><ns1:mo>[</ns1:mo><ns1:mrow><ns1:msub><ns1:mrow><ns1:mi>A</ns1:mi></ns1:mrow><ns1:mrow><ns1:mi>M</ns1:mi></ns1:mrow></ns1:msub><ns1:msub><ns1:mrow><ns1:mi>B</ns1:mi></ns1:mrow><ns1:mrow><ns1:mi>N</ns1:mi></ns1:mrow></ns1:msub></ns1:mrow><ns1:mo>]</ns1:mo><ns1:mo>,</ns1:mo><ns1:mspace width="0.25em" /><ns1:mi mathvariant="normal">and</ns1:mi><ns1:mspace width="0.25em" /><ns1:mo>[</ns1:mo><ns1:mrow><ns1:msub><ns1:mrow><ns1:mi>A</ns1:mi></ns1:mrow><ns1:mrow><ns1:mi>M</ns1:mi></ns1:mrow></ns1:msub><ns1:msub><ns1:mrow><ns1:mi>B</ns1:mi></ns1:mrow><ns1:mrow><ns1:mi>N</ns1:mi></ns1:mrow></ns1:msub></ns1:mrow><ns1:mo>]</ns1:mo><ns1:mo>=</ns1:mo><ns1:mi>K</ns1:mi><ns1:msup><ns1:mrow><ns1:mo>[</ns1:mo><ns1:mi>A</ns1:mi><ns1:mo>]</ns1:mo></ns1:mrow><ns1:mrow><ns1:mi>M</ns1:mi></ns1:mrow></ns1:msup><ns1:mo>[</ns1:mo><ns1:msup><ns1:mrow><ns1:mi>B</ns1:mi><ns1:mo>]</ns1:mo></ns1:mrow><ns1:mrow><ns1:mi>N</ns1:mi></ns1:mrow></ns1:msup><ns1:mo>.</ns1:mo>
</ns1:math>
</alternatives>
<label>(9)</label>
</disp-formula>
We considered (<italic>M</italic>, <italic>N</italic>) = (1, 1), (1, 2), (1, 3), (2, 2), (2, 3), and (3, 3), respectively.</p>
<p>In addition, we studied the consequence of having suboptimal mean [A]<sub>t</sub> or mean [B]<sub>t</sub>. That is, we set the ratio of mean [A]<sub>t</sub> to mean [B]<sub>t</sub> at <italic>M</italic>/<italic>N</italic>, 2<italic>M</italic>/<italic>N</italic>, or 0.5<italic>M</italic>/<italic>N</italic>. We considered CV = 0.2 or 0.5.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec015">
<title>Relationship in expression level between protein complex genes and linker histone genes across tissues</title>
<p>This analysis used the RNA-seq data from 13 mouse tissues [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1008389.ref056">56</xref>] as well as the protein complex data aforementioned. We divided all protein complex genes into three groups: unlinked genes, linked genes, and evolved linked genes. The first two groups are from duplicate-free protein complex gene pairs. A gene is assigned to the "linked" group if it is linked with at least one gene that encodes a member of the same protein complex. We found that the gene expression levels tend to be higher for the "linked" group than the "unlinked" group. To allow a fair comparison between these two groups, we computed the mean expression level of each gene across tissues and performed a stratified sampling as follows. We lumped all genes from the two groups and divided them into 20 bins based on their expression levels. For each bin, we counted the numbers of linked and unlinked genes respectively, and randomly down-sampled the larger group to the size of the smaller group. After the downsampling, the expression levels of the two groups of genes are comparable (<italic>P</italic> = 0.9, two-tailed Mann-Whitney <italic>U</italic> test). The third gene group contains genes that are linked in mouse but not in human nor in rat (i.e., "evolved linked"). We did not require them to be duplicate-free, but they were ancestrally unlinked so could not have resulted from tandem duplication. The expression levels of the third group of genes are not significantly different from those of the first two groups after the stratified sampling (<italic>P</italic> = 0.68).</p>
<p>After obtaining the three groups of genes, we examined the among-tissue correlation between the expression level of each of these genes and the total expression level of all 11 H1 histone genes in mouse [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1008389.ref096">96</xref>]. For control, we performed the same analysis but replaced H1 histones with TFIIB, a rapidly diffused transcription factor. In another control, we replaced H1 histones with immobilized core histones (H2A, H2B, H3, and H4). H2A, H2B, H3, and H4 genes are obtained from Mouse Genome Informatics (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://www.informatics.jax.org/" ns0:type="simple">http://www.informatics.jax.org/</ext-link>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1008389.ref097">97</xref>]:</p>
<p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://www.informatics.jax.org/vocab/pirsf/PIRSF002048" ns0:type="simple">http://www.informatics.jax.org/vocab/pirsf/PIRSF002048</ext-link></p>
<p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://www.informatics.jax.org/vocab/pirsf/PIRSF002050" ns0:type="simple">http://www.informatics.jax.org/vocab/pirsf/PIRSF002050</ext-link></p>
<p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://www.informatics.jax.org/vocab/pirsf/PIRSF002051" ns0:type="simple">http://www.informatics.jax.org/vocab/pirsf/PIRSF002051</ext-link></p>
<p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://www.informatics.jax.org/vocab/pirsf/PIRSF002052" ns0:type="simple">http://www.informatics.jax.org/vocab/pirsf/PIRSF002052</ext-link></p>
<sec id="sec016">
<title>Contribution of the linkage effect relative to that of regulatory element sharing to expression co-fluctuation</title>
<p>The maximum effect of sharing regulatory elements on expression co-fluctuation, referred to as <italic>&#948;</italic><sub>re</sub>, can be estimated by the median correlation coefficient in expression level between two alleles of the same gene minus the corresponding value for two alleles of different genes. We found that median <italic>&#948;</italic><sub>e</sub> is approximately one thirteenth of <italic>&#948;</italic><sub>re</sub>. Thus, the linkage effect improves expression co-fluctuation brought by regulatory element sharing by at least one thirteenth.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec017">
<title>Data and software availability</title>
<p>Software used and the underlying numerical data for all figures can be downloaded from Github (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://github.com/mengysun/Linked_noise" ns0:type="simple">https://github.com/mengysun/Linked_noise</ext-link>).</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec018">
<title>Supporting information</title>
<supplementary-material id="pgen.1008389.s001" mimetype="application/pdf" position="float" ns0:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1008389.s001" ns0:type="simple">
<label>S1 Fig</label>
<caption>
<title>Probability distributions of the correlation coefficient in expression level between alleles of two linked genes.</title>
<p>(A) The distribution of <italic>cis</italic>-correlations for alleles on C57BL/6J-derived chromosomes. (B) The distribution of <italic>cis</italic>-correlations for alleles on CAST/EiJ-derived chromosomes. (C) The distribution of <italic>trans</italic>-correlation for the C57BL/6J-derived allele at a gene and the CAST/EiJ-derived allele at another gene.</p>
<p>(PDF)</p>
</caption>
</supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material id="pgen.1008389.s002" mimetype="application/pdf" position="float" ns0:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1008389.s002" ns0:type="simple">
<label>S2 Fig</label>
<caption>
<title>The linkage effect on expression co-fluctuation in clone 6 cells and non-clonal cells.</title>
<p>(A) Fraction of gene pairs with positive <italic>&#948;</italic><sub><italic>e</italic></sub> in clone 6. The red line represents the null expectation under no linkage effect. <italic>P</italic>-values from binomial tests on independent gene pairs are presented. (B) In clone 6, median <italic>&#948;</italic><sub><italic>e</italic></sub> in a bin decreases as the median genomic distance between linked genes in the bin rises. All bins have the same distance interval. TSS, transcription start site. The red line shows <italic>&#948;</italic><sub><italic>e</italic></sub> = 0. The blue line shows the linear regression of binned data. Spearman's <italic>&#961;</italic> from unbinned data and associated <italic>P</italic>-value determined by a shuffling test are presented. (C) Fraction of gene pairs with positive <italic>&#948;</italic><sub><italic>e</italic></sub> in non-clonal mouse fibroblast cells. The red line represents the null expectation under no linkage effect. <italic>P</italic>-values from binomial tests on independent gene pairs are presented. (D) In non-clonal cells, median <italic>&#948;</italic><sub><italic>e</italic></sub> in a bin decreases as the median genomic distance between linked genes in the bin rises. All bins have the same distance interval. The red line shows <italic>&#948;</italic><sub><italic>e</italic></sub> = 0. The blue line shows the linear regression of binned data. Spearman's <italic>&#961;</italic> from unbinned data and associated <italic>P</italic>-value determined by a shuffling test are presented.</p>
<p>(PDF)</p>
</caption>
</supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material id="pgen.1008389.s003" mimetype="application/pdf" position="float" ns0:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1008389.s003" ns0:type="simple">
<label>S3 Fig</label>
<caption>
<title>The linkage effect on expression co-fluctuation in clone 7 cells analyzed using total reads of two alleles per locus.</title>
<p>(A) Median &#9651;<sub><italic>e</italic></sub> in a bin decreases with the median genomic distance between linked genes in the bin. &#9651;<sub><italic>e</italic></sub> for a linked gene pair is the correlation in RNA-seq read number between the two genes minus the median correlation for pairs of unlinked genes. All bins have the same distance interval. TSS, transcription start site. The red line shows &#9651;<sub><italic>e</italic></sub> = 0. The blue line shows the linear regression of binned data. Spearman's <italic>&#961;</italic> of unbinned data and associated <italic>P</italic>-value determined by a shuffling test are presented. (B) Median <inline-formula id="pgen.1008389.e012"><alternatives><graphic id="pgen.1008389.e012g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" ns0:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1008389.e012" ns0:type="simple" /><ns1:math display="inline" id="M12"><ns1:msubsup><ns1:mrow><ns1:mo>&#9651;</ns1:mo></ns1:mrow><ns1:mrow><ns1:mi>e</ns1:mi></ns1:mrow><ns1:mrow><ns1:mo>&#8242;</ns1:mo></ns1:mrow></ns1:msubsup></ns1:math></alternatives></inline-formula> in a bin decreases with the corresponding median genomic distance between linked genes in the bin. <inline-formula id="pgen.1008389.e013"><alternatives><graphic id="pgen.1008389.e013g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" ns0:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1008389.e013" ns0:type="simple" /><ns1:math display="inline" id="M13"><ns1:msubsup><ns1:mrow><ns1:mo>&#9651;</ns1:mo></ns1:mrow><ns1:mrow><ns1:mi>e</ns1:mi></ns1:mrow><ns1:mrow><ns1:mo>&#8242;</ns1:mo></ns1:mrow></ns1:msubsup></ns1:math></alternatives></inline-formula> for a linked gene pair is the correlation in expression level measured by RPKM (Reads Per Kilobase per Million mapped reads) between the two genes minus the corresponding median correlation for pairs of unlinked genes. The blue line shows the linear regression of binned data. Spearman's <italic>&#961;</italic> from unbinned data and associated <italic>P</italic>-value determined by a shuffling test are presented.</p>
<p>(PDF)</p>
</caption>
</supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material id="pgen.1008389.s004" mimetype="application/pdf" position="float" ns0:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1008389.s004" ns0:type="simple">
<label>S4 Fig</label>
<caption>
<title><italic>&#948;</italic><sub><italic>e</italic></sub> for pairs of neighboring genes with different orientations.</title>
<p>The lower and upper edges of a box represent the first (qu1) and third (qu3) quartiles, respectively, the horizontal line inside the box indicates the median (md), the whiskers extend to the most extreme values inside inner fences, md&#177;1.5(qu3-qu1), and the dots represent values outside the inner fences (outliers). The nearest pairs were identified using the coordinates downloaded from Ensembl. After requiring a minimal read number of 10 for each allele, we separate neighboring gene pairs into three categories according to the orientations of their transcription directions. NS, <italic>P</italic> &gt; 0.05, Wilcoxon rank-sum test.</p>
<p>(PDF)</p>
</caption>
</supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material id="pgen.1008389.s005" mimetype="application/pdf" position="float" ns0:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1008389.s005" ns0:type="simple">
<label>S5 Fig</label>
<caption>
<title><italic>&#948;</italic><sub><italic>e</italic></sub> decreases with distance between genes on each mouse chromosome.</title>
<p>Blue lines show linear regressions for binned data. All bins have the same distance intervals, while different chromosomes contain different numbers of bins depending on the chromosome length. Spearman's correlations from unbinned data and associated nominal <italic>P</italic>-values determined by shuffling tests are presented. Upon multiple testing correction, the correlations remain significant for chromosomes 1, 2, 5, 6, 11, and 12.</p>
<p>(PDF)</p>
</caption>
</supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material id="pgen.1008389.s006" mimetype="application/pdf" position="float" ns0:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1008389.s006" ns0:type="simple">
<label>S6 Fig</label>
<caption>
<title>Simulation-based analysis of chromatin co-accessibility between two ATAC peaks quantified using single cells vs. using cell populations.</title>
<p>(A) The correlations quantified using single-cell-based measurements are close to their corresponding true correlations when the capturing efficiency is 100%. (B) The correlations quantified using cell-population-based measurements are close to the true correlations when the capturing efficiency is 100%. (C) The correlations quantified using single-cell-based measurements tend to be weaker than their corresponding true correlations when the capturing efficiency is 10%. (D) The correlations quantified using cell population-based measurements tend to be weaker than the true correlations when the capturing efficiency is 10%.</p>
<p>(PDF)</p>
</caption>
</supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material id="pgen.1008389.s007" mimetype="application/pdf" position="float" ns0:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1008389.s007" ns0:type="simple">
<label>S7 Fig</label>
<caption>
<title>Simulations show that low capturing efficiencies lead to underestimation of <italic>&#948;</italic><sub><italic>a</italic></sub> and <italic>&#948;</italic><sub><italic>e</italic></sub>.</title>
<p>(A) The magnitude of <italic>&#948;</italic><sub><italic>a</italic></sub> estimated from allele-specific ATAC-seq is much smaller than the true <italic>&#948;</italic><sub><italic>a</italic></sub>. (B) The magnitude of <italic>&#948;</italic><sub><italic>e</italic></sub> estimated from allele-specific single-cell RNA-seq is much smaller than the true <italic>&#948;</italic><sub><italic>e</italic></sub>.</p>
<p>(PDF)</p>
</caption>
</supplementary-material>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ack>
<p>We thank members of the Zhang lab and three reviewers for valuable comments.</p>
</ack>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="pgen.1008389.ref001"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" ns0:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Elowitz</surname> <given-names>MB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Levine</surname> <given-names>AJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Siggia</surname> <given-names>ED</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Swain</surname> <given-names>PS</given-names></name>. <article-title>Stochastic gene expression in a single cell</article-title>. <source>Science</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>297</volume>(<issue>5584</issue>):<fpage>1183</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>6</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://doi.org/10.1126/science.1070919" ns0:type="simple">10.1126/science.1070919</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">12183631</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1008389.ref002"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" ns0:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Raser</surname> <given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>O'shea</surname> <given-names>EK</given-names></name>. <article-title>Noise in gene expression: origins, consequences, and control</article-title>. <source>Science</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>309</volume>(<issue>5743</issue>):<fpage>2010</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>3</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://doi.org/10.1126/science.1105891" ns0:type="simple">10.1126/science.1105891</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">16179466</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1008389.ref003"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" ns0:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Blake</surname> <given-names>WJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>K&#230;rn</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cantor</surname> <given-names>CR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Collins</surname> <given-names>JJ</given-names></name>. <article-title>Noise in eukaryotic gene expression</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>422</volume>(<issue>6932</issue>):<fpage>633</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>7</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://doi.org/10.1038/nature01546" ns0:type="simple">10.1038/nature01546</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">12687005</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1008389.ref004"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" ns0:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Batada</surname> <given-names>NN</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hurst</surname> <given-names>LD</given-names></name>. <article-title>Evolution of chromosome organization driven by selection for reduced gene expression noise</article-title>. <source>Nat Genet</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>39</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>945</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://doi.org/10.1038/ng2071" ns0:type="simple">10.1038/ng2071</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">17660811</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1008389.ref005"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" ns0:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lehner</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name>. <article-title>Selection to minimise noise in living systems and its implications for the evolution of gene expression</article-title>. <source>Mol Syst Biol</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>4</volume>:<fpage>170</fpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://doi.org/10.1038/msb.2008.11" ns0:type="simple">10.1038/msb.2008.11</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">18319722</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1008389.ref006"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" ns0:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname> <given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>. <article-title>Impact of gene expression noise on organismal fitness and the efficacy of natural selection</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>108</volume>(<issue>16</issue>):<fpage>E67</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>76</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.1100059108" ns0:type="simple">10.1073/pnas.1100059108</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">21464323</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1008389.ref007"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" ns0:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bahar</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hartmann</surname> <given-names>CH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rodriguez</surname> <given-names>KA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Denny</surname> <given-names>AD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Busuttil</surname> <given-names>RA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dolle</surname> <given-names>ME</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Increased cell-to-cell variation in gene expression in ageing mouse heart</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>441</volume>(<issue>7096</issue>):<fpage>1011</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>4</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://doi.org/10.1038/nature04844" ns0:type="simple">10.1038/nature04844</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">16791200</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1008389.ref008"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" ns0:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kemkemer</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schrank</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vogel</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gruler</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kaufmann</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>. <article-title>Increased noise as an effect of haploinsufficiency of the tumor-suppressor gene neurofibromatosis type 1 in vitro</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>99</volume>(<issue>21</issue>):<fpage>13783</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>8</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.212386999" ns0:type="simple">10.1073/pnas.212386999</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">12368469</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1008389.ref009"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" ns0:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Veening</surname> <given-names>J-W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Smits</surname> <given-names>WK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kuipers</surname> <given-names>OP</given-names></name>. <article-title>Bistability, epigenetics, and bet-hedging in bacteria</article-title>. <source>Annu Rev Microbiol</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>62</volume>:<fpage>193</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>210</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://doi.org/10.1146/annurev.micro.62.081307.163002" ns0:type="simple">10.1146/annurev.micro.62.081307.163002</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">18537474</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1008389.ref010"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" ns0:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname> <given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Qian</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>. <article-title>Positive selection for elevated gene expression noise in yeast</article-title>. <source>Mol Syst Biol</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>5</volume>:<fpage>299</fpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://doi.org/10.1038/msb.2009.58" ns0:type="simple">10.1038/msb.2009.58</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">19690568</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1008389.ref011"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" ns0:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Turing</surname> <given-names>AM</given-names></name>. <article-title>The chemical basis of morphogenesis</article-title>. <source>Philos Trans R Soc Lond B Biol Sci</source>. <year>1952</year>;<volume>237</volume>(<issue>641</issue>):<fpage>37</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>72</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1008389.ref012"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" ns0:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chang</surname> <given-names>HH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hemberg</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Barahona</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ingber</surname> <given-names>DE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>. <article-title>Transcriptome-wide noise controls lineage choice in mammalian progenitor cells</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>453</volume>(<issue>7194</issue>):<fpage>544</fpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://doi.org/10.1038/nature06965" ns0:type="simple">10.1038/nature06965</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">18497826</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1008389.ref013"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" ns0:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>. <article-title>Non-genetic heterogeneity of cells in development: more than just noise</article-title>. <source>Development</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>136</volume>(<issue>23</issue>):<fpage>3853</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>62</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://doi.org/10.1242/dev.035139" ns0:type="simple">10.1242/dev.035139</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">19906852</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1008389.ref014"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" ns0:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Taniguchi</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Choi</surname> <given-names>PJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname> <given-names>GW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Babu</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hearn</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Quantifying E. coli proteome and transcriptome with single-molecule sensitivity in single cells</article-title>. <source>Science</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>329</volume>(<issue>5991</issue>):<fpage>533</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>8</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://doi.org/10.1126/science.1188308" ns0:type="simple">10.1126/science.1188308</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">20671182</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1008389.ref015"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" ns0:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Newman</surname> <given-names>JR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ghaemmaghami</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ihmels</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Breslow</surname> <given-names>DK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Noble</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>DeRisi</surname> <given-names>JL</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Single-cell proteomic analysis of S. cerevisiae reveals the architecture of biological noise</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>441</volume>(<issue>7095</issue>):<fpage>840</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>6</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://doi.org/10.1038/nature04785" ns0:type="simple">10.1038/nature04785</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">16699522</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1008389.ref016"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" ns0:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stewart-Ornstein</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Weissman</surname> <given-names>JS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>El-Samad</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>. <article-title>Cellular noise regulons underlie fluctuations in Saccharomyces cerevisiae</article-title>. <source>Mol Cell</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>45</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>483</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>93</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.molcel.2011.11.035" ns0:type="simple">10.1016/j.molcel.2011.11.035</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">22365828</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1008389.ref017"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" ns0:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stewart-Ornstein</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nelson</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>DeRisi</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Weissman</surname> <given-names>JS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>El-Samad</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>. <article-title>Msn2 coordinates a stoichiometric gene expression program</article-title>. <source>Curr Biol</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>23</volume>(<issue>23</issue>):<fpage>2336</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>45</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cub.2013.09.043" ns0:type="simple">10.1016/j.cub.2013.09.043</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">24210615</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1008389.ref018"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" ns0:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Raj</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>van Oudenaarden</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>. <article-title>Nature, nurture, or chance: stochastic gene expression and its consequences</article-title>. <source>Cell</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>135</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>216</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>26</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cell.2008.09.050" ns0:type="simple">10.1016/j.cell.2008.09.050</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">18957198</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1008389.ref019"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" ns0:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sanchez</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Choubey</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kondev</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>. <article-title>Regulation of noise in gene expression</article-title>. <source>Annu Rev Biophys</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>42</volume>:<fpage>469</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>91</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://doi.org/10.1146/annurev-biophys-083012-130401" ns0:type="simple">10.1146/annurev-biophys-083012-130401</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">23527780</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1008389.ref020"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" ns0:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Brown</surname> <given-names>CR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mao</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Falkovskaia</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jurica</surname> <given-names>MS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Boeger</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>. <article-title>Linking stochastic fluctuations in chromatin structure and gene expression</article-title>. <source>PLoS Biol</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>11</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>e1001621</fpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.1001621" ns0:type="simple">10.1371/journal.pbio.1001621</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">23940458</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1008389.ref021"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" ns0:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Raj</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Peskin</surname> <given-names>CS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tranchina</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vargas</surname> <given-names>DY</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tyagi</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>. <article-title>Stochastic mRNA synthesis in mammalian cells</article-title>. <source>PLoS Biol</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>4</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>e309</fpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.0040309" ns0:type="simple">10.1371/journal.pbio.0040309</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">17048983</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1008389.ref022"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" ns0:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Becskei</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kaufmann</surname> <given-names>BB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>van Oudenaarden</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>. <article-title>Contributions of low molecule number and chromosomal positioning to stochastic gene expression</article-title>. <source>Nat Genet</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>37</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>937</fpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://doi.org/10.1038/ng1616" ns0:type="simple">10.1038/ng1616</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">16086016</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1008389.ref023"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" ns0:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Reinius</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mold</surname> <given-names>JE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ramskold</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Deng</surname> <given-names>Q</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Johnsson</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Michaelsson</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Analysis of allelic expression patterns in clonal somatic cells by single-cell RNA-seq</article-title>. <source>Nat Genet</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>48</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>1430</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>5</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://doi.org/10.1038/ng.3678" ns0:type="simple">10.1038/ng.3678</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">27668657</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1008389.ref024"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" ns0:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Picelli</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Faridani</surname> <given-names>OR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bj&#246;rklund</surname> <given-names>&#197;K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Winberg</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sagasser</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sandberg</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>. <article-title>Full-length RNA-seq from single cells using Smart-seq2</article-title>. <source>Nat Protoc</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>9</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>171</fpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://doi.org/10.1038/nprot.2014.006" ns0:type="simple">10.1038/nprot.2014.006</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">24385147</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1008389.ref025"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" ns0:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Macosko</surname> <given-names>EZ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Basu</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Satija</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nemesh</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shekhar</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Goldman</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Highly parallel genome-wide expression profiling of individual cells using nanoliter droplets</article-title>. <source>Cell</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>161</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>1202</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>14</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cell.2015.05.002" ns0:type="simple">10.1016/j.cell.2015.05.002</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">26000488</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1008389.ref026"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" ns0:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hashimshony</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Senderovich</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Avital</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Klochendler</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>de Leeuw</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Anavy</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>CEL-Seq2: sensitive highly-multiplexed single-cell RNA-Seq</article-title>. <source>Genome Biol</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>17</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>77</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1008389.ref027"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" ns0:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Raj</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Van Den Bogaard</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rifkin</surname> <given-names>SA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Van Oudenaarden</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tyagi</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>. <article-title>Imaging individual mRNA molecules using multiple singly labeled probes</article-title>. <source>Nat Methods</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>5</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>877</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://doi.org/10.1038/nmeth.1253" ns0:type="simple">10.1038/nmeth.1253</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">18806792</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1008389.ref028"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" ns0:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yan</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pocetti</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bai</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>. <article-title>Regulation of cell-to-cell variability in divergent gene expression</article-title>. <source>Nat Commun</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>7</volume>:<fpage>11099</fpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://doi.org/10.1038/ncomms11099" ns0:type="simple">10.1038/ncomms11099</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">27010670</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1008389.ref029"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" ns0:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nasheuer</surname> <given-names>HP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bauerschmidt</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Grosse</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Weisshart</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name>. <article-title>Initiation of eukaryotic DNA replication: regulation and mechanisms</article-title>. <source>Prog Nucleic Acid Res Mol Biol</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>72</volume>:<fpage>41</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>94</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">12206458</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1008389.ref030"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" ns0:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dekker</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mirny</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>. <article-title>The 3D genome as moderator of chromosomal communication</article-title>. <source>Cell</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>164</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>1110</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>21</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cell.2016.02.007" ns0:type="simple">10.1016/j.cell.2016.02.007</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">26967279</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1008389.ref031"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" ns0:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Belton</surname> <given-names>J-M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McCord</surname> <given-names>RP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gibcus</surname> <given-names>JH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Naumova</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhan</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dekker</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>. <article-title>Hi&#8211;C: a comprehensive technique to capture the conformation of genomes</article-title>. <source>Methods</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>58</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>268</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>76</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ymeth.2012.05.001" ns0:type="simple">10.1016/j.ymeth.2012.05.001</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">22652625</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1008389.ref032"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" ns0:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dekker</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Marti-Renom</surname> <given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mirny</surname> <given-names>LA</given-names></name>. <article-title>Exploring the three-dimensional organization of genomes: interpreting chromatin interaction data</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Genet</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>14</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>390</fpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://doi.org/10.1038/nrg3454" ns0:type="simple">10.1038/nrg3454</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">23657480</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1008389.ref033"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" ns0:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Giorgetti</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lajoie</surname> <given-names>BR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Carter</surname> <given-names>AC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Attia</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhan</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Structural organization of the inactive X chromosome in the mouse</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>535</volume>(<issue>7613</issue>):<fpage>575</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://doi.org/10.1038/nature18589" ns0:type="simple">10.1038/nature18589</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">27437574</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1008389.ref034"><label>34</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" ns0:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Phillips</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Theriot</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kondev</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Garcia</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>. <source>Physical biology of the cell: Garland Science</source>; <year>2012</year>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1008389.ref035"><label>35</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" ns0:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Buenrostro</surname> <given-names>JD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chang</surname> <given-names>HY</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Greenleaf</surname> <given-names>WJ</given-names></name>. <article-title>ATAC&#8208;seq: a method for assaying chromatin accessibility genome&#8208;wide</article-title>. <source>Curr Protoc Mol Biol</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>109</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>21</fpage>.29.1&#8211;9</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1008389.ref036"><label>36</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" ns0:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bahar Halpern</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tanami</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Landen</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chapal</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Szlak</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hutzler</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Bursty gene expression in the intact mammalian liver</article-title>. <source>Mol Cell</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>58</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>147</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>56</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.molcel.2015.01.027" ns0:type="simple">10.1016/j.molcel.2015.01.027</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">25728770</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1008389.ref037"><label>37</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" ns0:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dar</surname> <given-names>RD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Razooky</surname> <given-names>BS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Singh</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Trimeloni</surname> <given-names>TV</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McCollum</surname> <given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cox</surname> <given-names>CD</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Transcriptional burst frequency and burst size are equally modulated across the human genome</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>109</volume>(<issue>43</issue>):<fpage>17454</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.1213530109" ns0:type="simple">10.1073/pnas.1213530109</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">23064634</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1008389.ref038"><label>38</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" ns0:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Suter</surname> <given-names>DM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Molina</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gatfield</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schneider</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schibler</surname> <given-names>U</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Naef</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name>. <article-title>Mammalian genes are transcribed with widely different bursting kinetics</article-title>. <source>Science</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>332</volume>(<issue>6028</issue>):<fpage>472</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>4</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://doi.org/10.1126/science.1198817" ns0:type="simple">10.1126/science.1198817</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">21415320</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1008389.ref039"><label>39</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" ns0:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Carter</surname> <given-names>AC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gendrel</surname> <given-names>A-V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Attia</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Loftus</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Greenleaf</surname> <given-names>WJ</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Landscape of monoallelic DNA accessibility in mouse embryonic stem cells and neural progenitor cells</article-title>. <source>Nat Genet</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>49</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>377</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>86</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://doi.org/10.1038/ng.3769" ns0:type="simple">10.1038/ng.3769</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">28112738</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1008389.ref040"><label>40</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" ns0:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Buenrostro</surname> <given-names>JD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Litzenburger</surname> <given-names>UM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ruff</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gonzales</surname> <given-names>ML</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Snyder</surname> <given-names>MP</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Single-cell chromatin accessibility reveals principles of regulatory variation</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>523</volume>(<issue>7561</issue>):<fpage>486</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>90</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://doi.org/10.1038/nature14590" ns0:type="simple">10.1038/nature14590</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">26083756</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1008389.ref041"><label>41</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" ns0:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dixon</surname> <given-names>JR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Selvaraj</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yue</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shen</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Topological domains in mammalian genomes identified by analysis of chromatin interactions</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>485</volume>(<issue>7398</issue>):<fpage>376</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>80</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://doi.org/10.1038/nature11082" ns0:type="simple">10.1038/nature11082</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">22495300</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1008389.ref042"><label>42</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" ns0:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hahn</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>. <article-title>Physical origin of the contact frequency in chromosome conformation capture data</article-title>. <source>Biophys J</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>105</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>1786</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>95</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.bpj.2013.08.043" ns0:type="simple">10.1016/j.bpj.2013.08.043</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">24138854</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1008389.ref043"><label>43</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" ns0:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mahmutovic</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fange</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Berg</surname> <given-names>OG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Elf</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>. <article-title>Lost in presumption: stochastic reactions in spatial models.</article-title> <source>Nat Methods</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>9</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>1163</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>6</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://doi.org/10.1038/nmeth.2253" ns0:type="simple">10.1038/nmeth.2253</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">23223170</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1008389.ref044"><label>44</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" ns0:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hager</surname> <given-names>GL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McNally</surname> <given-names>JG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Misteli</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name>. <article-title>Transcription dynamics</article-title>. <source>Mol Cell</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>35</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>741</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>53</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.molcel.2009.09.005" ns0:type="simple">10.1016/j.molcel.2009.09.005</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">19782025</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1008389.ref045"><label>45</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" ns0:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lever</surname> <given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Th'ng</surname> <given-names>JP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname> <given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hendzel</surname> <given-names>MJ</given-names></name>. <article-title>Rapid exchange of histone H1.1 on chromatin in living human cells</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>408</volume>(<issue>6814</issue>):<fpage>873</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>6</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://doi.org/10.1038/35048603" ns0:type="simple">10.1038/35048603</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">11130728</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1008389.ref046"><label>46</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" ns0:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fyodorov</surname> <given-names>DV</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname> <given-names>B-R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Skoultchi</surname> <given-names>AI</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bai</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name>. <article-title>Emerging roles of linker histones in regulating chromatin structure and function</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Mol Cell Biol</source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>19</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>192</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>206</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://doi.org/10.1038/nrm.2017.94" ns0:type="simple">10.1038/nrm.2017.94</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">29018282</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1008389.ref047"><label>47</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" ns0:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bernas</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brutkowski</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zar&#281;bski</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dobrucki</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>. <article-title>Spatial heterogeneity of dynamics of H1 linker histone</article-title>. <source>Eur Biophys J</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>43</volume>(<issue>6&#8211;7</issue>):<fpage>287</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>300</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://doi.org/10.1007/s00249-014-0962-0" ns0:type="simple">10.1007/s00249-014-0962-0</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">24830851</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1008389.ref048"><label>48</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" ns0:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Veitia</surname> <given-names>RA</given-names></name>. <article-title>A generalized model of gene dosage and dominant negative effects in macromolecular complexes</article-title>. <source>FASEB J</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>24</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>994</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1002</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://doi.org/10.1096/fj.09-146969" ns0:type="simple">10.1096/fj.09-146969</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">20007508</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1008389.ref049"><label>49</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" ns0:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Milo</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jorgensen</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Moran</surname> <given-names>U</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Weber</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Springer</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>. <article-title>BioNumbers&#8212;the database of key numbers in molecular and cell biology</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>38</volume>(<issue>suppl_1</issue>):<fpage>D750</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>3</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1008389.ref050"><label>50</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" ns0:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sigal</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Milo</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cohen</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Geva-Zatorsky</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Klein</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liron</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Variability and memory of protein levels in human cells</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>444</volume>(<issue>7119</issue>):<fpage>643</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>6</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://doi.org/10.1038/nature05316" ns0:type="simple">10.1038/nature05316</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">17122776</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1008389.ref051"><label>51</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" ns0:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Budnik</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Levy</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Harmange</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Slavov</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name>. <article-title>Mass-spectrometry of single mammalian cells quantifies proteome heterogeneity during cell differentiation</article-title>. <source>bioRxiv</source>. <year>2018</year>:<fpage>102681</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1008389.ref052"><label>52</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" ns0:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Aken</surname> <given-names>BL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Achuthan</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Akanni</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Amode</surname> <given-names>MR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bernsdorff</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bhai</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Ensembl 2017</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>45</volume>(<issue>D1</issue>):<fpage>D635</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>42</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://doi.org/10.1093/nar/gkw1104" ns0:type="simple">10.1093/nar/gkw1104</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">27899575</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1008389.ref053"><label>53</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" ns0:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ibn-Salem</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Muro</surname> <given-names>EM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Andrade-Navarro</surname> <given-names>MA</given-names></name>. <article-title>Co-regulation of paralog genes in the three-dimensional chromatin architecture</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>45</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>81</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>91</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://doi.org/10.1093/nar/gkw813" ns0:type="simple">10.1093/nar/gkw813</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">27634932</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1008389.ref054"><label>54</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" ns0:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cherry</surname> <given-names>JL</given-names></name>. <article-title>Expression level, evolutionary rate, and the cost of expression</article-title>. <source>Genome Biol Evol</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>2</volume>:<fpage>757</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>69</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://doi.org/10.1093/gbe/evq059" ns0:type="simple">10.1093/gbe/evq059</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">20884723</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1008389.ref055"><label>55</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" ns0:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gout</surname> <given-names>JF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kahn</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Duret</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>. <article-title>The relationship among gene expression, the evolution of gene dosage, and the rate of protein evolution</article-title>. <source>PLoS Genet</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>6</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>e1000944</fpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pgen.1000944" ns0:type="simple">10.1371/journal.pgen.1000944</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">20485561</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1008389.ref056"><label>56</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" ns0:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>S&#246;llner</surname> <given-names>JF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Leparc</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hildebrandt</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Klein</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Thomas</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stupka</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>An RNA-Seq atlas of gene expression in mouse and rat normal tissues</article-title>. <source>Scientific Data</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>4</volume>:<fpage>170185</fpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://doi.org/10.1038/sdata.2017.185" ns0:type="simple">10.1038/sdata.2017.185</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">29231921</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1008389.ref057"><label>57</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" ns0:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vosnakis</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Koch</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Scheer</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kessler</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>M&#233;ly</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Didier</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Coactivators and general transcription factors have two distinct dynamic populations dependent on transcription</article-title>. <source>EMBO J</source>. <year>2017</year>:<fpage>e201696035</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1008389.ref058"><label>58</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" ns0:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Marinov</surname> <given-names>GK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Williams</surname> <given-names>BA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McCue</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schroth</surname> <given-names>GP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gertz</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Myers</surname> <given-names>RM</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>From single-cell to cell-pool transcriptomes: stochasticity in gene expression and RNA splicing</article-title>. <source>Genome Res</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>24</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>496</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>510</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://doi.org/10.1101/gr.161034.113" ns0:type="simple">10.1101/gr.161034.113</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">24299736</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1008389.ref059"><label>59</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" ns0:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Phifer-Rixey</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bonhomme</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Boursot</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Churchill</surname> <given-names>GA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pi&#225;lek</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tucker</surname> <given-names>PK</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Adaptive evolution and effective population size in wild house mice</article-title>. <source>Mol Biol Evol</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>29</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>2949</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>55</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://doi.org/10.1093/molbev/mss105" ns0:type="simple">10.1093/molbev/mss105</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">22490822</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1008389.ref060"><label>60</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" ns0:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname> <given-names>J-J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname> <given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jin</surname> <given-names>Y-S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>. <article-title>Synchronization of stochastic expressions drives the clustering of functionally related genes</article-title>. <source>Sci Adv</source>. <year>2019</year>; in press.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1008389.ref061"><label>61</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" ns0:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Beyer</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Aebersold</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>. <article-title>On the dependency of cellular protein levels on mRNA abundance</article-title>. <source>Cell</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>165</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>535</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>50</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cell.2016.03.014" ns0:type="simple">10.1016/j.cell.2016.03.014</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">27104977</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1008389.ref062"><label>62</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" ns0:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kustatscher</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Grabowski</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rappsilber</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>. <article-title>Pervasive coexpression of spatially proximal genes is buffered at the protein level</article-title>. <source>Mol Syst Biol</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>13</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>937</fpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://doi.org/10.15252/msb.20177548" ns0:type="simple">10.15252/msb.20177548</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">28835372</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1008389.ref063"><label>63</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" ns0:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Eden</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Geva-Zatorsky</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Issaeva</surname> <given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cohen</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dekel</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Danon</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Proteome half-life dynamics in living human cells</article-title>. <source>Science</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>331</volume>(<issue>6018</issue>):<fpage>764</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>8</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://doi.org/10.1126/science.1199784" ns0:type="simple">10.1126/science.1199784</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">21233346</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1008389.ref064"><label>64</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" ns0:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Popovic</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Koch</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kueblbeck</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ellenberg</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pelkmans</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>. <article-title>Multivariate control of transcript to protein variability in single mammalian cells</article-title>. <source>Cell Syst</source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>7</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>398</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>411</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cels.2018.09.001" ns0:type="simple">10.1016/j.cels.2018.09.001</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">30342881</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1008389.ref065"><label>65</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" ns0:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gedeon</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bokes</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>. <article-title>Delayed protein synthesis reduces the correlation between mRNA and protein fluctuations</article-title>. <source>Biophys J</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>103</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>377</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>85</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.bpj.2012.06.025" ns0:type="simple">10.1016/j.bpj.2012.06.025</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">22947853</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1008389.ref066"><label>66</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" ns0:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Teichmann</surname> <given-names>SA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Veitia</surname> <given-names>RA</given-names></name>. <article-title>Genes encoding subunits of stable complexes are clustered on the yeast chromosomes</article-title>. <source>Genetics</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>167</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>2121</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>5</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://doi.org/10.1534/genetics.103.024505" ns0:type="simple">10.1534/genetics.103.024505</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">15342545</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1008389.ref067"><label>67</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" ns0:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Franks</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Airoldi</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Slavov</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name>. <article-title>Post-transcriptional regulation across human tissues</article-title>. <source>PLoS Comput Biol</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>13</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>e1005535</fpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1005535" ns0:type="simple">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1005535</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">28481885</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1008389.ref068"><label>68</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" ns0:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hurst</surname> <given-names>LD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>P&#225;l</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lercher</surname> <given-names>MJ</given-names></name>. <article-title>The evolutionary dynamics of eukaryotic gene order</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Genet</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>5</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>299</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>310</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://doi.org/10.1038/nrg1319" ns0:type="simple">10.1038/nrg1319</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">15131653</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1008389.ref069"><label>69</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" ns0:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname> <given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>. <article-title>The genomic landscape of position effects on protein expression level and noise in yeast</article-title>. <source>Cell Syst</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>2</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>347</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>54</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cels.2016.03.009" ns0:type="simple">10.1016/j.cels.2016.03.009</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">27185547</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1008389.ref070"><label>70</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" ns0:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ori</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Iskar</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Buczak</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kastritis</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Parca</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Andr&#233;s-Pons</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Spatiotemporal variation of mammalian protein complex stoichiometries</article-title>. <source>Genome Biol</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>17</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>47</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1008389.ref071"><label>71</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" ns0:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Slavov</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Semrau</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Airoldi</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Budnik</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>van Oudenaarden</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>. <article-title>Differential stoichiometry among core ribosomal proteins</article-title>. <source>Cell Rep</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>13</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>865</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>73</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.celrep.2015.09.056" ns0:type="simple">10.1016/j.celrep.2015.09.056</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">26565899</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1008389.ref072"><label>72</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" ns0:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Levesque</surname> <given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Raj</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>. <article-title>Single-chromosome transcriptional profiling reveals chromosomal gene expression regulation</article-title>. <source>Nat Methods</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>10</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>246</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>8</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://doi.org/10.1038/nmeth.2372" ns0:type="simple">10.1038/nmeth.2372</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">23416756</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1008389.ref073"><label>73</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" ns0:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fukuoka</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Inaoka</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kohane</surname> <given-names>IS</given-names></name>. <article-title>Inter-species differences of co-expression of neighboring genes in eukaryotic genomes</article-title>. <source>BMC Genomics</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>5</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>4</fpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://doi.org/10.1186/1471-2164-5-4" ns0:type="simple">10.1186/1471-2164-5-4</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">14718066</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1008389.ref074"><label>74</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" ns0:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Singer</surname> <given-names>GA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lloyd</surname> <given-names>AT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Huminiecki</surname> <given-names>LB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wolfe</surname> <given-names>KH</given-names></name>. <article-title>Clusters of co-expressed genes in mammalian genomes are conserved by natural selection</article-title>. <source>Mol Biol Evol</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>22</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>767</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>75</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://doi.org/10.1093/molbev/msi062" ns0:type="simple">10.1093/molbev/msi062</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">15574806</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1008389.ref075"><label>75</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" ns0:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>S&#233;mon</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Duret</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>. <article-title>Evolutionary origin and maintenance of coexpressed gene clusters in mammals</article-title>. <source>Mol Biol Evol</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>23</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>1715</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>23</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://doi.org/10.1093/molbev/msl034" ns0:type="simple">10.1093/molbev/msl034</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">16757654</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1008389.ref076"><label>76</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" ns0:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lercher</surname> <given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hurst</surname> <given-names>LD</given-names></name>. <article-title>Co-expressed yeast genes cluster over a long range but are not regularly spaced</article-title>. <source>J Mol Biol</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>359</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>825</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>31</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jmb.2006.03.051" ns0:type="simple">10.1016/j.jmb.2006.03.051</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">16631793</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1008389.ref077"><label>77</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" ns0:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Spellman</surname> <given-names>PT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rubin</surname> <given-names>GM</given-names></name>. <article-title>Evidence for large domains of similarly expressed genes in the Drosophila genome</article-title>. <source>J Biol</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>1</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>5</fpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">12144710</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1008389.ref078"><label>78</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" ns0:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ghanbarian</surname> <given-names>AT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hurst</surname> <given-names>LD</given-names></name>. <article-title>Neighboring genes show correlated evolution in gene expression</article-title>. <source>Mol Biol Evol</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>32</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>1748</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>66</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://doi.org/10.1093/molbev/msv053" ns0:type="simple">10.1093/molbev/msv053</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">25743543</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1008389.ref079"><label>79</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" ns0:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liao</surname> <given-names>B-Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>. <article-title>Coexpression of linked genes in mammalian genomes is generally disadvantageous</article-title>. <source>Mol Biol Evol</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>25</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>1555</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>65</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://doi.org/10.1093/molbev/msn101" ns0:type="simple">10.1093/molbev/msn101</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">18440951</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1008389.ref080"><label>80</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" ns0:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Naumova</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Imakaev</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fudenberg</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhan</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lajoie</surname> <given-names>BR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mirny</surname> <given-names>LA</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Organization of the mitotic chromosome</article-title>. <source>Science</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>342</volume>(<issue>6161</issue>):<fpage>948</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>53</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://doi.org/10.1126/science.1236083" ns0:type="simple">10.1126/science.1236083</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">24200812</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1008389.ref081"><label>81</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" ns0:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Elf</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Barkefors</surname> <given-names>I</given-names></name>. <article-title>Single-molecule kinetics in living cells</article-title>. <source>Annu Rev Biochem</source>. <year>2018</year>; <volume>88</volume>:<fpage>635</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>59</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://doi.org/10.1146/annurev-biochem-013118-110801" ns0:type="simple">10.1146/annurev-biochem-013118-110801</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">30359080</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1008389.ref082"><label>82</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" ns0:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Veitia</surname> <given-names>RA</given-names></name>. <article-title>Gene dosage balance in cellular pathways: implications for dominance and gene duplicability</article-title>. <source>Genetics</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>168</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>569</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>74</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://doi.org/10.1534/genetics.104.029785" ns0:type="simple">10.1534/genetics.104.029785</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">15454568</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1008389.ref083"><label>83</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" ns0:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>McGary</surname> <given-names>KL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Slot</surname> <given-names>JC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rokas</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>. <article-title>Physical linkage of metabolic genes in fungi is an adaptation against the accumulation of toxic intermediate compounds</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>110</volume>(<issue>28</issue>):<fpage>11481</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>6</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.1304461110" ns0:type="simple">10.1073/pnas.1304461110</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">23798424</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1008389.ref084"><label>84</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" ns0:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Carrera</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Covert</surname> <given-names>MW</given-names></name>. <article-title>Why build whole-cell models?</article-title> <source>Trends Cell Biol</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>25</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>719</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>22</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.tcb.2015.09.004" ns0:type="simple">10.1016/j.tcb.2015.09.004</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">26471224</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1008389.ref085"><label>85</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" ns0:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rustici</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mata</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kivinen</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Li&#243;</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Penkett</surname> <given-names>CJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Burns</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Periodic gene expression program of the fission yeast cell cycle</article-title>. <source>Nat Genet</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>36</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>809</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>17</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://doi.org/10.1038/ng1377" ns0:type="simple">10.1038/ng1377</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">15195092</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1008389.ref086"><label>86</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" ns0:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Esumi</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kakazu</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Taguchi</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hirayama</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sasaki</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hirabayashi</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Monoallelic yet combinatorial expression of variable exons of the protocadherin-alpha gene cluster in single neurons</article-title>. <source>Nat Genet</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>37</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>171</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>6</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://doi.org/10.1038/ng1500" ns0:type="simple">10.1038/ng1500</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">15640798</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1008389.ref087"><label>87</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" ns0:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wada</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wallerich</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Becskei</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>. <article-title>Stochastic Gene Choice during Cellular Differentiation</article-title>. <source>Cell Rep</source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>24</volume>(<issue>13</issue>):<fpage>3503</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>12</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.celrep.2018.08.074" ns0:type="simple">10.1016/j.celrep.2018.08.074</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">30257211</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1008389.ref088"><label>88</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" ns0:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Monahan</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gertz</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Varley</surname> <given-names>KE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>CTCF/cohesin-mediated DNA looping is required for protocadherin alpha promoter choice</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>109</volume>(<issue>51</issue>):<fpage>21081</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>6</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.1219280110" ns0:type="simple">10.1073/pnas.1219280110</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">23204437</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1008389.ref089"><label>89</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" ns0:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Raj</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rifkin</surname> <given-names>SA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Andersen</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Van Oudenaarden</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>. <article-title>Variability in gene expression underlies incomplete penetrance</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>463</volume>(<issue>7283</issue>):<fpage>913</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>8</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://doi.org/10.1038/nature08781" ns0:type="simple">10.1038/nature08781</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">20164922</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1008389.ref090"><label>90</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" ns0:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Baker</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>. <article-title>Synthetic genomes: The next step for the synthetic genome</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>473</volume>(<issue>7347</issue>):<fpage>403</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>8</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://doi.org/10.1038/473403a" ns0:type="simple">10.1038/473403a</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">21593873</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1008389.ref091"><label>91</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" ns0:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ruepp</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Waegele</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lechner</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brauner</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dunger-Kaltenbach</surname> <given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fobo</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>CORUM: the comprehensive resource of mammalian protein complexes&#8212;2009</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>38</volume>(<issue>suppl_1</issue>):<fpage>D497</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>501</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1008389.ref092"><label>92</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" ns0:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Geman</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Geman</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>. <article-title>Stochastic relaxation, Gibbs distributions, and the Bayesian restoration of images</article-title>. <source>Readings in Computer Vision: Elsevier</source>; <year>1987</year>. p. <fpage>564</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>84</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1008389.ref093"><label>93</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" ns0:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gilks</surname> <given-names>WR</given-names></name>. <article-title>Markov chain monte carlo</article-title>. <source>Encyclopedia of Biostatistics</source>. <year>2005</year>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1008389.ref094"><label>94</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" ns0:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hwang</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname> <given-names>JH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bang</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>. <article-title>Single-cell RNA sequencing technologies and bioinformatics pipelines</article-title>. <source>Exp Mol Med</source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>50</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>96</fpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s12276-018-0071-8" ns0:type="simple">10.1038/s12276-018-0071-8</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">30089861</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1008389.ref095"><label>95</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" ns0:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Battich</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stoeger</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pelkmans</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>. <article-title>Control of transcript variability in single mammalian cells</article-title>. <source>Cell</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>163</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>1596</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>610</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cell.2015.11.018" ns0:type="simple">10.1016/j.cell.2015.11.018</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">26687353</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1008389.ref096"><label>96</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" ns0:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Medrzycki</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cao</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fan</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name>. <article-title>Expression analysis of mammalian linker-histone subtypes. Journal of visualized experiments</article-title>. <source>JoVE</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>61</volume>:<fpage>3577</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1008389.ref097"><label>97</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" ns0:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bult</surname> <given-names>CJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Eppig</surname> <given-names>JT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kadin</surname> <given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Richardson</surname> <given-names>JE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Blake</surname> <given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Group</surname> <given-names>MGD</given-names></name>. <article-title>The Mouse Genome Database (MGD): mouse biology and model systems</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>36</volume>(<issue>suppl_1</issue>):<fpage>D724</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>8</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
<sub-article article-type="aggregated-review-documents" id="pgen.1008389.r001" specific-use="decision-letter">
<front-stub>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1008389.r001</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title>Decision Letter 0</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Payseur</surname>
<given-names>Bret</given-names>
</name>
<role>Section Editor: Evolution</role>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Bai</surname>
<given-names>Lu</given-names>
</name>
<role>Guest Editor</role>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<permissions>
<copyright-year>2019</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>Payseur, Bai</copyright-holder>
<license ns0:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
<license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" ns0:type="simple">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<related-object document-id="10.1371/journal.pgen.1008389" document-id-type="doi" document-type="article" id="rel-obj001" link-type="peer-reviewed-article" />
<custom-meta-group>
<custom-meta>
<meta-name>Submission Version</meta-name>
<meta-value>0</meta-value>
</custom-meta>
</custom-meta-group>
</front-stub>
<body>
<p>
<named-content content-type="letter-date">10 Jul 2019</named-content>
</p>
<p>* Please note while forming your response, if your article is accepted, you may have the opportunity to make the peer review history publicly available. The record will include editor decision letters (with reviews) and your responses to reviewer comments. If eligible, we will contact you to opt in or out. *</p>
<p>Dear Dr Zhang:</p>
<p>Thank you very much for submitting your Research Article entitled 'Chromosome-wide co-fluctuation of stochastic gene expression in mammalian cells' to PLOS Genetics. Your manuscript was fully evaluated at the editorial level and by three independent peer reviewers. The reviewers appreciated the attention to an important topic but identified some aspects of the manuscript that should be improved.</p>
<p>We therefore ask you to modify the manuscript according to the review recommendations before we can consider your manuscript for acceptance. Your revisions should address the specific points made by each reviewer.</p>
<p>In addition we ask that you:</p>
<p>1) Provide a detailed list of your responses to the review comments and a description of the changes you have made in the manuscript.</p>
<p>2) Upload a Striking Image with a corresponding caption to accompany your manuscript if one is available (either a new image or an existing one from within your manuscript). If this image is judged to be suitable, it may be featured on our website. Images should ideally be high resolution, eye-catching, single panel square images. For examples, please browse our <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://www.plosgenetics.org/article/browse/volume" ns0:type="simple">archive</ext-link>. If your image is from someone other than yourself, please ensure that the artist has read and agreed to the terms and conditions of the Creative Commons Attribution License. Note: we cannot publish copyrighted images.</p>
<p>We hope to receive your revised manuscript within the next 30 days. If you anticipate any delay in its return, we would ask you to let us know the expected resubmission date by email to <email ns0:type="simple">plosgenetics@plos.org</email>.</p>
<p>If present, accompanying reviewer attachments should be included with this email; please notify the journal office if any appear to be missing. They will also be available for download from the link below. You can use this link to log into the system when you are ready to submit a revised version, having first consulted our <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://journals.plos.org/plosgenetics/s/submit-now#loc-submission-checklist" ns0:type="simple">Submission Checklist</ext-link>.</p>
<p>While revising your submission, please upload your figure files to the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://pace.apexcovantage.com/" ns0:type="simple">Preflight Analysis and Conversion Engine</ext-link>&#160;(PACE) digital diagnostic tool. PACE helps ensure that figures meet PLOS requirements. To use PACE, you must first register as a user. Then, login and navigate to the UPLOAD tab, where you will find detailed instructions on how to use the tool. If you encounter any issues or have any questions when using PACE, please email us at <email ns0:type="simple">figures@plos.org</email>.</p>
<p>Please be aware that our&#160;<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://journals.plos.org/plosgenetics/s/data-availability" ns0:type="simple">data availability policy</ext-link>&#160;requires that all numerical data underlying graphs or summary statistics are included with the submission, and you will need to provide this upon resubmission if not already present. In addition, we do not permit the inclusion of phrases such as "data not shown" or "unpublished results" in manuscripts. All points should be backed up by data provided with the submission.</p>
<p>PLOS has incorporated <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://www.crossref.org/crosscheck.html" ns0:type="simple">Similarity Check</ext-link>, powered by iThenticate, into its journal-wide submission system in order to screen submitted content for originality before publication. Each PLOS journal undertakes screening on a proportion of submitted articles. You will be contacted if needed following the screening process.</p>
<p>To resubmit, you will need to go to the link below and 'Revise Submission' in the 'Submissions Needing Revision' folder.</p>
<p>[LINK]</p>
<p>Please let us know if you have any questions while making these revisions.</p>
<p>Yours sincerely,</p>
<p>Lu Bai</p>
<p>Guest Editor</p>
<p>PLOS Genetics</p>
<p>Bret Payseur</p>
<p>Section Editor: Evolution</p>
<p>PLOS Genetics</p>
<p>Reviewer's Responses to Questions</p>
<p><bold>Comments to the Authors:</bold></p>
<p><bold>Please note here if the review is uploaded as an attachment.</bold></p>
<p>Reviewer #1: The study of Sun &amp; Zhang reveals an interesting coupling between gene positioning along a chromosome and fluctuations, indicating that cis-correlations are higher than trans-correlations in the context of homologous chromosomes. The majority of tests are convincing, in particular the one showing that the effect becomes more prominent when they focus on highly expressed genes. The fact that the authors study the differential behavior of linked genes in comparison to their homologous counterparts (within a certain cell type) is clear in some but not in other contexts. Therefore, I suggest addressing the points below before the publication of the manuscript.</p>
<p>Major remarks</p>
<p>1) The comparison of expression fluctuations with chromosomal looping and chromatin accessibility clearly follows physical models of gene expression. However, the hypothesized link between expression fluctuations and protein complexes &#8220; the expression co-fluctuation of genes encoding components of the same protein complex is likely advantageous.&#8221; should be examined in more detail. The authors implicitly assume the formation of protein complexes is enhanced when the subunits expressed in a coordinated fashion, irrespective of the basis of comparison. However, it is possible that there is no difference in the correlation with homologous and heterologous interchromosomal fluctuations. This is important since each subunit of the dimer is expressed from a maternal and paternal chromosome even if they are positioned on homologous and heterologous chromosomes. Therefore, either the simulations should include different scenarios of chromosomal fluctuations or the above conclusion should be explained statistically more rigorously.</p>
<p>Minor remarks:</p>
<p>2) A. The authors compare stochastic intra-chromosomal and inter-chromosomal correlations. This is important because most studies (as mentioned in the discussion) do not distinguish intra-chromosomal effect. This is mentioned at several places, notably in the abstract, in the last paragraph of the introduction , first section of the results,&#8230;. However, the authors should not assume that the general audience understands the term &#8220;linked&#8221; and should explain that in more general terms in the author summary. For example, the authors could explain in the author summary that each individual receives a maternal and paternal copy of the same chromosome.</p>
<p>B. Figure 1 or Figure 2A should include the full depiction of pair(s) of homologous chromosomes so that it becomes clear what the authors mean.</p>
<p>3) The interchromosomal fluctuations may have a substantially stronger effect on gene choice than on protein complexes. Therefore, I suggest the authors discussing stochastic gene choice in the context of their results. The Protocadhering gene array is prototypical example where stochastic gene expression is very strongly depends on intrachromosomal looping controlled by the binding of the looping factor CTCF in neuronal progenitors (PMID: 15640798, 30257211). Therefore, the intrachromosomal fluctuations and conformational changes may have a strong impact on the choice and number of expressed protein isoforms of this membrane protein, which can underscore the biological relevance of the fluctuations studied by the authors.</p>
<p>Reviewer #2: RE: PGENETICS-D-19-00916</p>
<p>In this study, the authors investigated co-fluctuation of chromosomally-linked genes. This phenomenon was first discovered experimentally by a previous study using fluorescent reporters (Raj et al, 2006). Here the authors analyzed the existing single-cell RNA seq data and showed that this could be a genome-wide phenomenon. To this end, they showed statistically the expression correlations between linked alleles (on the same chromosome) of two genes are greater than those between unlinked alleles. With the support of additional analysis, they further demonstrated that the 3D proximity and chromatin co-accessibility could be the underlying mechanism of this effect. Finally, they proposed that, through natural selection, genes encoding components of the same complexes might be organized onto the same chromosomes to correlate their expression.</p>
<p>I find this paper well-written and scientifically interesting. Gene expression coordination in single cells has been an important topic of research. The authors performed a careful analysis of existing data and raised an intriguing model. I would recommend the acceptance of this manuscript for publication shall the concerns below be addressed.</p>
<p>1. I would think that the most direct way to coordinate gene expression of functionally-related genes in individual cells is through sharing the same trans or cis-regulatory factors. Is there a way to quantitively compare the contribution of this mechanism with the contribution of chromosomal linkage? I suspect that the former one might play a major role. The paper is interesting either way, but a careful discussion and comparison will be helpful.</p>
<p>2. Related to point 1, for natural selection, would sharing regulatory elements provide more plasticity than reorganizing the genome? Again, a careful discussion would be needed. Genome re-organization does not seem like the more intuitive way to ensure gene expression coordination.</p>
<p>3. In addition to genes encoding components of the same complexes, I wonder whether the same organization rule can be applied to the genes encoding components of the same signaling or metabolic pathways? If not, why?</p>
<p>Reviewer #3: The manuscript from Mengyi Sun and Jianzhi Zhang lays out the novel and provocative idea that coordinated fluctuations in gene expression stem from fluctuations in local histone H1 concentrations.</p>
<p>In support of this idea, they show that expression of "linked" (immediate nearest neighbors along the same chromosome) genes is more correlated than expression of the same pair of genes across homologous chromosomes. Suprisingly, this is true even when the two genes are seperated by over 100Mb, suggesting a 3D, not 1D, cause. Consistent with this, but unsuprisingly, alleles on the same chrommosome are more frequently in physical contact with each other than alleles on homologous chromosomes.</p>
<p>As a mechanism they propose local diffusion of H1, and in support of this mechanism they find that protein complex members whose expression is negativly correlated with H1 mRNA levels are more likely to be linked.</p>
<p>The ideas are provocative and, while, as the authors point out, the effect sizes are weak, some of this may be due to imperfect matches between experimental data and experimental error. In addition, evolution can act on weak effect sizes.</p>
<p>However, their model makes a major prediction that I'm suprised they didn't test, and I would like to see tested before the paper is published. The authors propose that 1D distance doesn't matter; only 3D distance. This predicts that the correlation shown in Fig1D should be even stronger if 3D distance is plotted on the X axis. Furthremore, being nearest neighbors (linked) shouldn't be the most predictive feature. HiC contact frequency should be.</p>
<p>If you recalculate something like Figure 1B but bin into multiple groups, binning genes by contact frequency and/or distance in 3D space, instead of only into linked vs unlinked, does the effect still hold?</p>
<p>In other words, genes that are unlinked, but still close in 3D space, should exhibit equally strong co-expression.</p>
<p>Minor Point:</p>
<p>"While each of the four correlations could be positive or negative, in the large data analyzed below, they are mostly positive and show approximately normal distributions across gene pairs examined."</p>
<p>I'd like to see the histograms of these four correlations (re(A1,B1), re(A2,B2), etc)</p>
<p>"All statistical analyses were performed using custom R and python scripts that are available upon request."</p>
<p>It's 2019; this should no longer be acceptable. Please put all code and intermediate (processed) data on github or some other repository.</p>
<p>The PLoS Genetics data availibility guidelines state that, if the data are not made publically availible, "The reasons for restrictions on public data deposition must also be specified. "</p>
<p>**********</p>
<p><bold>Have all data underlying the figures and results presented in the manuscript been provided?</bold></p>
<p>Large-scale datasets should be made available via a public repository as described in the <italic>PLOS Genetics</italic> <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://journals.plos.org/plosgenetics/s/data-availability" ns0:type="simple">data availability policy</ext-link>, and numerical data that underlies graphs or summary statistics should be provided in spreadsheet form as supporting information.</p>
<p>Reviewer #1: Yes</p>
<p>Reviewer #2: None</p>
<p>Reviewer #3: No: "All statistical analyses were performed using custom R and python scripts that are available upon request."</p>
<p>It's 2019; this should no longer be acceptable. Please put all code and intermediate (processed) data on github or some other repository.</p>
<p>The PLoS Genetics data availibility guidelines state that, if the data are not made publically availible, "The reasons for restrictions on public data deposition must also be specified. "</p>
<p>**********</p>
<p>PLOS authors have the option to publish the peer review history of their article (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://journals.plos.org/plosgenetics/s/editorial-and-peer-review-process#loc-peer-review-history" ns0:type="simple">what does this mean?</ext-link>). If published, this will include your full peer review and any attached files.</p>
<p>If you choose &#8220;no&#8221;, your identity will remain anonymous but your review may still be made public.</p>
<p><bold>Do you want your identity to be public for this peer review?</bold> For information about this choice, including consent withdrawal, please see our <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://www.plos.org/privacy-policy" ns0:type="simple">Privacy Policy</ext-link>.</p>
<p>Reviewer #1: No</p>
<p>Reviewer #2: No</p>
<p>Reviewer #3: Yes: Lucas Carey</p>
</body>
</sub-article>
<sub-article article-type="author-comment" id="pgen.1008389.r002">
<front-stub>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1008389.r002</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title>Author response to Decision Letter 0</article-title>
</title-group>
<related-object document-id="10.1371/journal.pgen.1008389" document-id-type="doi" document-type="peer-reviewed-article" id="rel-obj002" link-type="rebutted-decision-letter" object-id="10.1371/journal.pgen.1008389.r001" object-id-type="doi" object-type="decision-letter" />
<custom-meta-group>
<custom-meta>
<meta-name>Submission Version</meta-name>
<meta-value>1</meta-value>
</custom-meta>
</custom-meta-group>
</front-stub>
<body>
<p>
<named-content content-type="author-response-date">5 Aug 2019</named-content>
</p>
<supplementary-material id="pgen.1008389.s008" mimetype="application/pdf" position="float" ns0:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1008389.s008" ns0:type="simple">
<label>Attachment</label>
<caption>
<p>Submitted filename: <named-content content-type="submitted-filename">Response.pdf</named-content></p>
</caption>
</supplementary-material>
</body>
</sub-article>
<sub-article article-type="aggregated-review-documents" id="pgen.1008389.r003" specific-use="decision-letter">
<front-stub>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1008389.r003</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title>Decision Letter 1</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Payseur</surname>
<given-names>Bret</given-names>
</name>
<role>Section Editor: Evolution</role>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Bai</surname>
<given-names>Lu</given-names>
</name>
<role>Guest Editor</role>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<permissions>
<copyright-year>2019</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>Payseur, Bai</copyright-holder>
<license ns0:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
<license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" ns0:type="simple">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<related-object document-id="10.1371/journal.pgen.1008389" document-id-type="doi" document-type="article" id="rel-obj003" link-type="peer-reviewed-article" />
<custom-meta-group>
<custom-meta>
<meta-name>Submission Version</meta-name>
<meta-value>1</meta-value>
</custom-meta>
</custom-meta-group>
</front-stub>
<body>
<p>
<named-content content-type="letter-date">28 Aug 2019</named-content>
</p>
<p>[EXSCINDED]</p>
<p>Dear Dr Zhang,</p>
<p>We are pleased to inform you that your manuscript entitled "Chromosome-wide co-fluctuation of stochastic gene expression in mammalian cells" has been editorially accepted for publication in PLOS Genetics. Congratulations!</p>
<p>There are some minor comments from Reviewer #1 about wording and references, please take that into consideration for the finalized version. Before your submission can be formally accepted and sent to production you will need to complete our formatting changes, which you will receive in a follow up email. Please be aware that it may take several days for you to receive this email; during this time no action is required by you. Please note: the accept date on your published article will reflect the date of this provisional accept, but your manuscript will not be scheduled for publication until the required changes have been made.</p>
<p>Once your paper is formally accepted, an uncorrected proof of your manuscript will be published online ahead of the final version, unless you&#8217;ve already opted out via the online submission form. If, for any reason, you do not want an earlier version of your manuscript published online or are unsure if you have already indicated as such, please let the journal staff know immediately at <email ns0:type="simple">plosgenetics@plos.org</email>.</p>
<p>In the meantime, please log into Editorial Manager at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://www.editorialmanager.com/pgenetics/" ns0:type="simple">https://www.editorialmanager.com/pgenetics/</ext-link>, click the "Update My Information" link at the top of the page, and update your user information to ensure an efficient production and billing process.&#160;Note that&#160;PLOS requires an ORCID iD for all corresponding authors. Therefore, please ensure that you have an ORCID iD and that it is validated in Editorial Manager. To do this, go to &#8216;Update my Information&#8217; (in the upper left-hand corner of the main menu), and click on the Fetch/Validate link next to the ORCID field.&#160; This will take you to the ORCID site and allow you to create a new iD or authenticate a pre-existing iD in Editorial Manager.</p>
<p>If you have a press-related query, or would like to know about one way to make your underlying data available (as you will be aware, this is required for publication), please see the end of this email. If your institution or institutions have a press office, please notify them about your upcoming article at this point, to enable them to help maximise its impact. Inform journal staff as soon as possible if you are preparing a press release for your article and need a publication date.</p>
<p>Thank you again for supporting open-access publishing; we are looking forward to publishing your work in PLOS Genetics!</p>
<p>Yours sincerely,</p>
<p>Lu Bai</p>
<p>Guest Editor</p>
<p>PLOS Genetics</p>
<p>Bret Payseur</p>
<p>Section Editor: Evolution</p>
<p>PLOS Genetics</p>
<p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://www.plosgenetics.org" ns0:type="simple">www.plosgenetics.org</ext-link></p>
<p>Twitter: @PLOSGenetics</p>
<p>----------------------------------------------------</p>
<p>Comments from the reviewers (if applicable):</p>
<p>Reviewer's Responses to Questions</p>
<p><bold>Comments to the Authors:</bold></p>
<p><bold>Please note here if the review is uploaded as an attachment.</bold></p>
<p>Reviewer #1: The authors addressed most of the points raised. In particular, they rewrote the author summary and extended Figure 2 to facilitate readability. They also inserted a brief discussion that the baseline protein noise level may vary with the genomic framework (e..g. haploid and diploid) but this does not change the conclusions. They cite a relevant paper in this context.</p>
<p>They also discuss the looping in the context of gene choice &#8220;For instance, previous research found that selective expression of genes that are clustered on the same chromosome (i.e., gene choice) is strongly dependent on intrachromosomal looping, which alters the pairwise physical distance between genes in the same gene array.&#8220; It would be more precise to state &#8220;stochastic gene choice&#8221; than merely &#8220;gene choice&#8221;. Importantly, the authors omitted to cite the relevant papers to specify the previous research:</p>
<p>Please add these references so that the meaning of these sentences becomes clear.</p>
<p>&#8220;Monoallelic yet combinatorial expression of variable exons of the protocadherin-alpha gene cluster in single neurons.&#8221;</p>
<p>&#8220;Stochastic Gene Choice during Cellular Differentiation.&#8221;</p>
<p>&#8220;CTCF/cohesin-mediated DNA looping is required for protocadherin &#945; promoter choice.&#8221;</p>
<p>These three papers provide preliminary evidence that looping drives stochastic gene choice that the expression frequency correlates with the binding of the looping factor, CTCF, to the respective genes.</p>
<p>Reviewer #2: The revisions have solved all my concerns. I recommend acceptance of this paper for publication.</p>
<p>**********</p>
<p><bold>Have all data underlying the figures and results presented in the manuscript been provided?</bold></p>
<p>Large-scale datasets should be made available via a public repository as described in the <italic>PLOS Genetics</italic> <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://journals.plos.org/plosgenetics/s/data-availability" ns0:type="simple">data availability policy</ext-link>, and numerical data that underlies graphs or summary statistics should be provided in spreadsheet form as supporting information.</p>
<p>Reviewer #1: Yes</p>
<p>Reviewer #2: Yes</p>
<p>**********</p>
<p>PLOS authors have the option to publish the peer review history of their article (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://journals.plos.org/plosgenetics/s/editorial-and-peer-review-process#loc-peer-review-history" ns0:type="simple">what does this mean?</ext-link>). If published, this will include your full peer review and any attached files.</p>
<p>If you choose &#8220;no&#8221;, your identity will remain anonymous but your review may still be made public.</p>
<p><bold>Do you want your identity to be public for this peer review?</bold> For information about this choice, including consent withdrawal, please see our <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://www.plos.org/privacy-policy" ns0:type="simple">Privacy Policy</ext-link>.</p>
<p>Reviewer #1: No</p>
<p>Reviewer #2: No</p>
<p>----------------------------------------------------</p>
<p><bold>Data Deposition</bold></p>
<p>If you have submitted a Research Article or Front Matter that has associated data that are not suitable for deposition in a subject-specific public repository (such as GenBank or ArrayExpress), one way to make that data available is to deposit it in the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://www.datadryad.org" ns0:type="simple">Dryad Digital Repository</ext-link>. As you may recall, we ask all authors to agree to make data available; this is one way to achieve that. A full list of recommended repositories can be found on our <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://journals.plos.org/plosgenetics/s/data-availability#loc-recommended-repositories" ns0:type="simple">website</ext-link>.</p>
<p>The following link will take you to the Dryad record for your article, so you won't have to re&#8208;enter its bibliographic information, and can upload your files directly:&#160;</p>
<p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://datadryad.org/submit?journalID=pgenetics&amp;manu=PGENETICS-D-19-00916R1" ns0:type="simple">http://datadryad.org/submit?journalID=pgenetics&amp;manu=PGENETICS-D-19-00916R1</ext-link></p>
<p>More information about depositing data in Dryad is available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://www.datadryad.org/depositing" ns0:type="simple">http://www.datadryad.org/depositing</ext-link>. If you experience any difficulties in submitting your data, please contact <email ns0:type="simple">help@datadryad.org</email> for support.</p>
<p>Additionally, please be aware that our <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://journals.plos.org/plosgenetics/s/data-availability" ns0:type="simple">data availability policy</ext-link> requires that all numerical data underlying display items are included with the submission, and you will need to provide this before we can formally accept your manuscript, if not already present.</p>
<p>----------------------------------------------------</p>
<p><bold>Press Queries</bold></p>
<p>If you or your institution will be preparing press materials for this manuscript, or if you need to know your paper's publication date for media purposes, please inform the journal staff as soon as possible so that your submission can be scheduled accordingly. Your manuscript will remain under a strict press embargo until the publication date and time. This means an early version of your manuscript will not be published ahead of your final version. PLOS Genetics may also choose to issue a press release for your article. If there's anything the journal should know or you'd like more information, please get in touch via <email ns0:type="simple">plosgenetics@plos.org</email>.</p>
</body>
</sub-article>
<sub-article article-type="editor-report" id="pgen.1008389.r004" specific-use="acceptance-letter">
<front-stub>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1008389.r004</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title>Acceptance letter</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Payseur</surname>
<given-names>Bret</given-names>
</name>
<role>Section Editor: Evolution</role>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Bai</surname>
<given-names>Lu</given-names>
</name>
<role>Guest Editor</role>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<permissions>
<copyright-year>2019</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>Payseur, Bai</copyright-holder>
<license ns0:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
<license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" ns0:type="simple">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<related-object document-id="10.1371/journal.pgen.1008389" document-id-type="doi" document-type="article" id="rel-obj004" link-type="peer-reviewed-article" />
</front-stub>
<body>
<p>
<named-content content-type="letter-date">10 Sep 2019</named-content>
</p>
<p>PGENETICS-D-19-00916R1 </p>
<p>Chromosome-wide co-fluctuation of stochastic gene expression in mammalian cells </p>
<p>Dear Dr Zhang, </p>
<p>We are pleased to inform you that your manuscript entitled "Chromosome-wide co-fluctuation of stochastic gene expression in mammalian cells" has been formally accepted for publication in PLOS Genetics!  Your manuscript is now with our production department and you will be notified of the publication date in due course.</p>
<p>The corresponding author will soon be receiving a typeset proof for review, to ensure errors have not been introduced during production. Please review the PDF proof of your manuscript carefully, as this is the last chance to correct any errors. Please note that major changes, or those which affect the scientific understanding of the work, will likely cause delays to the publication date of your manuscript. </p>
<p>Soon after your final files are uploaded, unless you have opted out or your manuscript is a front-matter piece, the early version of your manuscript will be published online. The date of the early version will be your article's publication date. The final article will be published to the same URL, and all versions of the paper will be accessible to readers.</p>
<p>Thank you again for supporting PLOS Genetics and open-access publishing. We are looking forward to publishing your work! </p>
<p>With kind regards,</p>
<p>Kaitlin Butler</p>
<p>PLOS Genetics</p>
<p>On behalf of:</p>
<p>The PLOS Genetics Team</p>
<p>Carlyle House, Carlyle Road, Cambridge CB4 3DN | United Kingdom</p>
<p><email ns0:type="simple">plosgenetics@plos.org</email> | +44 (0) 1223-442823</p>
<p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://plosgenetics.org" ns0:type="simple">plosgenetics.org</ext-link> | Twitter: @PLOSGenetics</p>
</body>
</sub-article>
</article>