<sub-article xmlns:ns0="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="author-comment" id="pone.0223150.r004">
<front-stub>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0223150.r004</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title>Author response to Decision Letter 1</article-title>
</title-group>
<related-object document-id="10.1371/journal.pone.0223150" document-id-type="doi" document-type="peer-reviewed-article" id="rel-obj004" link-type="rebutted-decision-letter" object-id="10.1371/journal.pone.0223150.r003" object-id-type="doi" object-type="decision-letter" />
<custom-meta-group>
<custom-meta>
<meta-name>Submission Version</meta-name>
<meta-value>2</meta-value>
</custom-meta>
</custom-meta-group>
</front-stub>
<body>
<p>
<named-content content-type="author-response-date">8 Sep 2019</named-content>
</p>
<p>We are grateful for the reviewers&#8217; comments and for the opportunity to improve the manuscript.  </p>
<p>Response to reviewers&#8217;</p>
<p>Reviewers' comments:</p>
<p>Reviewer #1: All my comments from the first round of the review were adequately addressed. There are only 4 minor issues left, that should be worked out prior to publication. </p>
<p>Line 81: missing "to", should be ...for their discharge to home</p>
<p>Response: Thank you, we have added &#8220;to&#8221;.</p>
<p>Line 123: should be ....medicine ward specialised in gastroenterology</p>
<p>Response: Thank you. Corrected.</p>
<p>Line 321: should be "In a systematic review Beattie and colleagues identified 11 instruments measuring patient experience of healthcare quality [26]." or "Beattie and colleagues identified 11 instruments of measuring patient experience of healthcare quality in a systematic review [26]."</p>
<p>Response: Agree. Changed to: In a systematic review Beattie and colleagues identified 11 instruments measuring patient experience of healthcare quality [26]." (line 325-326)</p>
<p>And - sorry for grouching, but - the DOI for Reference 43 leads me to the wrong publication, I cannot retrieve the right publication with the given DOI 10.12788/jhm.3037 via <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://doi.org" ns0:type="simple">doi.org</ext-link>. In the citation 43 as given I can only find another publication, were the title and one authors name match.</p>
<p>The DOI 10.12788/jhm.3037 given in the citation 43 leads to the following publication:</p>
<p>Brotman DJ, Siddiqui Z, Siddiqui Z, Durkin N. Does Patient Experience Predict 30-Day Readmission? A Patient-Level Analysis of HCAHPS Data. Journal of Hospital Medicine. 2018;13. doi:10.12788/jhm.3037</p>
<p>The publication you cited as No. 43 has another DOI, when I look for the title only:</p>
<p>Siddiqui OI. Methods for Computing Missing Item Response in Psychometric Scale Construction. Current Research in Biostatistics. 2015;5: 1&#8211;6. doi:10.3844/amjbsp.2015.1.6</p>
<p>Response: Thank you for your thoroughness! We agree and have corrected to:</p>
<p>&#8220;43. Siddiqui OI. Methods for Computing Missing Item Response in Psychometric Scale Construction. Am J Biostat, 2015. doi:10.3844/amjbsp.2015.1.6&#8221; (line 578-579)</p>
<p>Reviewer #2: One additional suggestion to improve the manuscript content: line 147, add brief details of the search strategy.</p>
<p>Response: Thank you. We agree and have added: &#8220;Our search strategy comprised the following terms: patient experience, patients satisfaction and patient perspective, and further patient discharge, patient transfer, continuity of patient care, patient hand over, patient hand off, primary health care, home based care, nursing homes, community health services and and community based care. (line 147-151).</p>
<p>Line 283: wording should be &#8220;discharge&#8221; </p>
<p>Response: Thank you. We think this sentence was imprecise, and have added &#8220;scores on&#8221; to clarify: &#8220;The relations of scores on DICARES, and the three factors, with readmission within 30 days are shown in Table 3.&#8221; (line 287-288)</p>
<p>We hope that our responses have addressed the comments sufficiently and that our manuscript would be acceptable for publication.</p>
<supplementary-material id="pone.0223150.s007" mimetype="application/vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.wordprocessingml.document" position="float" ns0:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0223150.s007" ns0:type="simple">
<label>Attachment</label>
<caption>
<p>Submitted filename: <named-content content-type="submitted-filename">Response to Reviewers.docx</named-content></p>
</caption>
</supplementary-material>
</body>
</sub-article>
