<sub-article xmlns:ns0="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="editor-report" id="ppat.1007948.r003" specific-use="acceptance-letter">
<front-stub>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1007948.r003</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title>Acceptance letter</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Baumler</surname>
<given-names>Andreas J</given-names>
</name>
<role>Associate Editor</role>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Tsolis</surname>
<given-names>Ren&#233;e M.</given-names>
</name>
<role>Section Editor</role>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<permissions>
<copyright-year>2019</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>Baumler, Tsolis</copyright-holder>
<license ns0:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
<license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" ns0:type="simple">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<related-object document-id="10.1371/journal.ppat.1007948" document-id-type="doi" document-type="article" id="rel-obj003" link-type="peer-reviewed-article" />
</front-stub>
<body>
<p>
<named-content content-type="letter-date">20 Sep 2019</named-content>
</p>
<p>Dear Dr. Canals,</p>
<p>We are delighted to inform you that your manuscript, "The fitness landscape of the African Salmonella Typhimurium ST313 strain D23580 reveals unique properties of the pBT1 plasmid," has been formally accepted for publication in PLOS Pathogens.</p>
<p>We have now passed your article onto the PLOS Production Department who will complete the rest of the pre-publication process. All authors will receive a confirmation email upon publication.</p>
<p>The corresponding author will soon be receiving a typeset proof for review, to ensure errors have not been introduced during production. Please review the PDF proof of your manuscript carefully, as this is the last chance to correct any scientific or type-setting errors. Please note that major changes, or those which affect the scientific understanding of the work, will likely cause delays to the publication date of your manuscript. Note: Proofs for Front Matter articles (Pearls, Reviews, Opinions, etc...) are generated on a different schedule and may not be made available as quickly.</p>
<p>Soon after your final files are uploaded, the early version of your manuscript, if you opted to have an early version of your article, will be published online. The date of the early version will be your article's publication date. The final article will be published to the same URL, and all versions of the paper will be accessible to readers.</p>
<p>Thank you again for supporting open-access publishing; we are looking forward to publishing your work in PLOS Pathogens. </p>
<p>Best regards,</p>
<p>Kasturi Haldar</p>
<p>Editor-in-Chief</p>
<p>PLOS Pathogens</p>
<p>&#8203;<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://orcid.org/0000-0001-5065-158X" ns0:type="simple">orcid.org/0000-0001-5065-158X</ext-link></p>
<p>Grant McFadden</p>
<p>Editor-in-Chief</p>
<p>PLOS Pathogens</p>
<p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://orcid.org/0000-0002-2556-3526" ns0:type="simple">orcid.org/0000-0002-2556-3526</ext-link></p>
</body>
</sub-article>
