<sub-article xmlns:ns0="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="aggregated-review-documents" id="pone.0218230.r001" specific-use="decision-letter">
<front-stub>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0218230.r001</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title>Decision Letter 0</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>van Wijnen</surname>
<given-names>Andre</given-names>
</name>
<role>Academic Editor</role>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<permissions>
<copyright-year>2019</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>Andre van Wijnen</copyright-holder>
<license ns0:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
<license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" ns0:type="simple">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<related-object document-id="10.1371/journal.pone.0218230" document-id-type="doi" document-type="article" id="rel-obj001" link-type="peer-reviewed-article" />
<custom-meta-group>
<custom-meta>
<meta-name>Submission Version</meta-name>
<meta-value>0</meta-value>
</custom-meta>
</custom-meta-group>
</front-stub>
<body>
<p>
<named-content content-type="letter-date">20 Jun 2019</named-content>
</p>
<p>PONE-D-19-14765</p>
<p>Atoh8 acts as a regulator of chondrocyte proliferation and differentiation in endochondral bones</p>
<p>PLOS ONE</p>
<p>Dear Dr. Vortkamp,</p>
<p>Thank you for submitting your manuscript to PLOS ONE. After careful consideration, we feel that it has merit but does not fully meet PLOS ONE&#8217;s publication criteria as it currently stands. Therefore, we invite you to submit a revised version of the manuscript that comprehensively addresses the points raised by both&#160;reviewers.</p>
<p>We would appreciate receiving your revised manuscript by Aug 04 2019 11:59PM. When you are ready to submit your revision, log on to <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://www.editorialmanager.com/pone/" ns0:type="simple">https://www.editorialmanager.com/pone/</ext-link> and select the 'Submissions Needing Revision' folder to locate your manuscript file.</p>
<p>If you would like to make changes to your financial disclosure, please include your updated statement in your cover letter.</p>
<p>To enhance the reproducibility of your results, we recommend that if applicable you deposit your laboratory protocols in protocols.io, where a protocol can be assigned its own identifier (DOI) such that it can be cited independently in the future. For instructions see: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://journals.plos.org/plosone/s/submission-guidelines#loc-laboratory-protocols" ns0:type="simple">http://journals.plos.org/plosone/s/submission-guidelines#loc-laboratory-protocols</ext-link></p>
<p>Please include the following items when submitting your revised manuscript:</p>
<p><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>A rebuttal letter that responds to each point raised by the academic editor and reviewer(s). This letter should be uploaded as separate file and labeled 'Response to Reviewers'.</p></list-item><list-item><p>A marked-up copy of your manuscript that highlights changes made to the original version. This file should be uploaded as separate file and labeled 'Revised Manuscript with Track Changes'.</p></list-item><list-item><p>An unmarked version of your revised paper without tracked changes. This file should be uploaded as separate file and labeled 'Manuscript'.</p></list-item></list></p>
<p>Please note while forming your response, if your article is accepted, you may have the opportunity to make the peer review history publicly available. The record will include editor decision letters (with reviews) and your responses to reviewer comments. If eligible, we will contact you to opt in or out.</p>
<p>We look forward to receiving your revised manuscript.</p>
<p>Kind regards,</p>
<p>Andre van Wijnen</p>
<p>Academic Editor</p>
<p>PLOS ONE</p>
<p>Journal Requirements:</p>
<p>1.&#160; When submitting your revision, we need you to address these additional requirements.</p>
<p>Please ensure that your manuscript meets PLOS ONE's style requirements, including those for file naming. The PLOS ONE style templates can be found at</p>
<p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://www.journals.plos.org/plosone/s/file?id=wjVg/PLOSOne_formatting_sample_main_body.pdf" ns0:type="simple">http://www.journals.plos.org/plosone/s/file?id=wjVg/PLOSOne_formatting_sample_main_body.pdf</ext-link> and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://www.journals.plos.org/plosone/s/file?id=ba62/PLOSOne_formatting_sample_title_authors_affiliations.pdf" ns0:type="simple">http://www.journals.plos.org/plosone/s/file?id=ba62/PLOSOne_formatting_sample_title_authors_affiliations.pdf</ext-link></p>
<p>2.&#160; We note that you have included the phrase &#8220;data not shown&#8221; in your manuscript. Unfortunately, this does not meet our data sharing requirements. PLOS does not permit references to inaccessible data. We require that authors provide all relevant data within the paper, Supporting Information files, or in an acceptable, public repository. Please add a citation to support this phrase or upload the data that corresponds with these findings to a stable repository (such as Figshare or Dryad) and provide and URLs, DOIs, or accession numbers that may be used to access these data. Or, if the data are not a core part of the research being presented in your study, we ask that you remove the phrase that refers to these data.</p>
<p>[Note: HTML markup is below. Please do not edit.]</p>
<p>Reviewers' comments:</p>
<p>Reviewer's Responses to Questions</p>
<p><bold>Comments to the Author</bold></p>
<p>1. Is the manuscript technically sound, and do the data support the conclusions?</p>
<p>The manuscript must describe a technically sound piece of scientific research with data that supports the conclusions. Experiments must have been conducted rigorously, with appropriate controls, replication, and sample sizes. The conclusions must be drawn appropriately based on the data presented. </p>
<p>Reviewer #1: Partly</p>
<p>Reviewer #2: Partly</p>
<p>**********</p>
<p>2. Has the statistical analysis been performed appropriately and rigorously? </p>
<p>Reviewer #1: Yes</p>
<p>Reviewer #2: I Don't Know</p>
<p>**********</p>
<p>3. Have the authors made all data underlying the findings in their manuscript fully available?</p>
<p>The <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://www.plosone.org/static/policies.action#sharing" ns0:type="simple">PLOS Data policy</ext-link> requires authors to make all data underlying the findings described in their manuscript fully available without restriction, with rare exception (please refer to the Data Availability Statement in the manuscript PDF file). The data should be provided as part of the manuscript or its supporting information, or deposited to a public repository. For example, in addition to summary statistics, the data points behind means, medians and variance measures should be available. If there are restrictions on publicly sharing data&#8212;e.g. participant privacy or use of data from a third party&#8212;those must be specified.</p>
<p>Reviewer #1: Yes</p>
<p>Reviewer #2: Yes</p>
<p>**********</p>
<p>4. Is the manuscript presented in an intelligible fashion and written in standard English?</p>
<p>PLOS ONE does not copyedit accepted manuscripts, so the language in submitted articles must be clear, correct, and unambiguous. Any typographical or grammatical errors should be corrected at revision, so please note any specific errors here.</p>
<p>Reviewer #1: Yes</p>
<p>Reviewer #2: Yes</p>
<p>**********</p>
<p>5. Review Comments to the Author</p>
<p>Please use the space provided to explain your answers to the questions above. You may also include additional comments for the author, including concerns about dual publication, research ethics, or publication ethics. (Please upload your review as an attachment if it exceeds 20,000 characters)</p>
<p>Reviewer #1: Atoh8 is a broadly expressed transcription factor affecting differentiation in many organs. Its expression in avian growth plate and mouse limb buds prompted the present study of any role in limb development.</p>
<p>The investigators have knocked out Atoh8 using both Prx-Cre for germline and Col2a1-Cre for chondrocytes. The stages of phenotype development were different for the two. Zones of proliferative and hypertrophic chondrocytes were reduced for both, but the chondrocyte-specific knockouts had shortened bones postnatally whereas the Prx-Cre mice did so already at birth. Evidence was presented of interaction of Atoh8 with IHH signalling and expression levels.</p>
<p>1. The paper is descriptive only , revealing a contributory role for Atoh8 in limb endochondral bone formation but no mechanistic insights. In its technical aspects the work has been carried out to a high standard.</p>
<p>2. The insertion of figure legends in the text is unusual. Maybe it is a policy of the journal? It is a distraction, interrupts the flow of description of Results.</p>
<p>3. Figure 1 needs a better description. Its details and interpretation would not necessarily be obvious to readers of the journal. The zones of limb buds need to be specified clearly in the figure. It is stated that Atoh8 is expressed in the proliferating and hypertrophic zones but especially in prehypertrophic, but it is not so clear in 1C that Atoh8 is expressed in the hypertrophic zone (Col X). Another interpretation is that Atoh8 is not expressed in hypertrophic but appears to be so in prehypertrophic.</p>
<p>4. Fig 1D and E. What do the micromass culture data mean, apart from showing the knockdown of Atoh8?</p>
<p>5. Fig 4C and P 13 lines 366 -373. This explanation of Fig 4C is difficult to understand, especially lines 369-371. The authors might explain carefully just exactly how these measurements were made.</p>
<p>6. Fig 4C. It is impossible to discern any detail in 4C, to the extent that there seems little point in including it iof better images are not available. . This is particularly so in view of the extremely small . although statistically significant, difference between columnar cells of control and Atoh-deficient (Fig 5D).</p>
<p>7. Fig 6 and Discussion, lines 501-510. The negative outcome of this experiment is not conclusive. Atoh8 is located primarily in the nucleus and cannot be detected in cytoplasm with Csa treatment. Excluding the possibility of Csa outside the nucleus would require more throrough investigation, rather than concluding as has been done in Discussion lines 501 et seq.</p>
<p>8. Fig 7 . The quantitative data in Fig 7 are unconvincing, and in 7C the same comment is made as for Fig 4C (above) &#8211; it is impossible to discern any detail in 7C. Furthermore the quantitative data is so weak that it is difficult to accept the conclusions that Atoh 8 acts upstream andin parallel or downstream of Ihh in regulating the onset of hypertrophy and proliferation rate, respectively ( Discussion lines 547-550). Indeed the linkage between Ihh and PTHrP is so strong physiologically that any attempt to reach conclusions about Atoh8 - Ihh relationship in isolation is beset with difficulty.</p>
<p>Reviewer #2: The aim of this study is to uncover the role of atonal homolog 8 (Atoh8) transcription factor in endochondral skeletal growth. The authors first studied expression of Atoh8 in developing limbs by whole mount ISH and conventional ISH on tissue sections, and the qPCR analysis of RNA prepared from micromass cultures of control and Atoh8 CKO. The authors then carried out histological and morphometric analyses of various parameters of control (Cre negative litter mates) and conditional Atoh8 deficient mutant samples (either Col2a1Cre, Atoh8 floxed or Prx1-Cre, Atoh8floxed mice). Expression analysis revealed that Atoh8 was expressed in cartilage in developing skeleton. In addition, ablation of the gene resulted in marked reduction in collagen 2 expression at least in cultured chondrocytes. In contrast, histological and various morphometric analyses of the mutant mice showed very modest differences compared to those in control mice. Though the authors claim the possible role of Atoh8 in regulation of skeletal growth and interaction with Ihh signaling, the reviewer thinks that the study is inconclusive due to a small size of sample number and insufficient information on the mouse strains. They should also consider functional redundancy among other family members and more carefully interpret the results. Otherwise, their conclusion and discussion potentially mislead the readers.</p>
<p>The culturs prepared from E12.5 limb buds contain various cell populations. The results from this culture system should not be interpreted as the phenotype of chondrocytes.</p>
<p>To identify and establish very modest differences in size of skeleton and histomorphometric parameter of growth-plate, the authors need to have appropriate control and analyze enough number of specimens. In this study, the authors always used Cre negative littermates as control, but the strains of the parent mice are not given. If the compound mice generated in this study came from more than 2 strains, they need to consider impact of genetic drift on skeletal growth difference. Col2Cre could be an another control mouse. The sample size for analysis of skeleton length is 3-4, which may not be enough to conclude the growth retardation in the mutant mice. It is not provided how many biological different samples were used for histological analysis although the sample size ranges 10-12?. It should be provided how they define the anatomical landmark to orient the limbs and to secure the longest or same tissue level for measurement of various histological parameters.</p>
<p>By searching &#8220;GenePaint&#8221; database, the reviewer found other members of Atoh families are also expressed in developing skeleton. Are there functional redundancy among other family members? Have you checked expression of other Atoh transcription factors? These points are required to reach conclusion on the exclusive role of Atoh 8 in endochondral ossification.</p>
<p>**********</p>
<p>6. PLOS authors have the option to publish the peer review history of their article (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://journals.plos.org/plosone/s/editorial-and-peer-review-process#loc-peer-review-history" ns0:type="simple">what does this mean?</ext-link>). If published, this will include your full peer review and any attached files.</p>
<p>If you choose &#8220;no&#8221;, your identity will remain anonymous but your review may still be made public.</p>
<p><bold>Do you want your identity to be public for this peer review?</bold> For information about this choice, including consent withdrawal, please see our <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://www.plos.org/privacy-policy" ns0:type="simple">Privacy Policy</ext-link>.</p>
<p>Reviewer #1: No</p>
<p>Reviewer #2: No</p>
<p>[NOTE: If reviewer comments were submitted as an attachment file, they will be attached to this email and accessible via the submission site. Please log into your account, locate the manuscript record, and check for the action link "View Attachments". If this link does not appear, there are no attachment files to be viewed.]</p>
<p>While revising your submission, please upload your figure files to the Preflight Analysis and Conversion Engine (PACE) digital diagnostic tool, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://pacev2.apexcovantage.com/" ns0:type="simple">https://pacev2.apexcovantage.com/</ext-link>. PACE helps ensure that figures meet PLOS requirements. To use PACE, you must first register as a user. Registration is free. Then, login and navigate to the UPLOAD tab, where you will find detailed instructions on how to use the tool. If you encounter any issues or have any questions when using PACE, please email us at <email ns0:type="simple">figures@plos.org</email>. Please note that Supporting Information files do not need this step.</p>
</body>
</sub-article>
