<sub-article xmlns:ns0="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="aggregated-review-documents" id="pone.0222337.r001" specific-use="decision-letter">
<front-stub>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0222337.r001</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title>Decision Letter 0</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Bhadauria</surname>
<given-names>Tunira</given-names>
</name>
<role>Academic Editor</role>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<permissions>
<copyright-year>2019</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>Tunira Bhadauria</copyright-holder>
<license ns0:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
<license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" ns0:type="simple">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<related-object document-id="10.1371/journal.pone.0222337" document-id-type="doi" document-type="article" id="rel-obj001" link-type="peer-reviewed-article" />
<custom-meta-group>
<custom-meta>
<meta-name>Submission Version</meta-name>
<meta-value>0</meta-value>
</custom-meta>
</custom-meta-group>
</front-stub>
<body>
<p>
<named-content content-type="letter-date">5 Jul 2019</named-content>
</p>
<p>PONE-D-19-15357</p>
<p>Pontoscolex corethrurus: a Homeless Invasive Tropical Earthworm?</p>
<p>PLOS ONE</p>
<p>Dear Ceballos</p>
<p>Thank you for submitting your manuscript to PLOS ONE. After careful consideration, we feel that it has merit but does not fully meet PLOS ONE&#8217;s publication criteria as it currently stands. Therefore, we invite you to submit a revised version of the manuscript that addresses the points raised during the review process.</p>
<p>1]The authors have done an interesting study determining the reason as to why P. corethrurus is unable to invade the agricultural niche of B. pearsei?</p>
<p>2]The design of experiment is very appropriate and accurate.</p>
<p>3]But there are some loop holes that need to be plugged for eg: the figure numbers need to be checked and rectified</p>
<p>4]English language needs to be checked by someone with good command over language for clarification in the manuscript</p>
<p>5]Diiscussion should be written more precisely and directly analysing the results obtained in the experiments performed.</p>
<p>6]Other comments have been high lighted in the manuscript and also by the reviewers ,</p>
<p>7]All the comments must be answered to and necessary rectifications made in the manuscript based on the reviewers comments</p>
<p>Therefore manuscript can be accepted for publication only after the major revision.</p>
<p>We would appreciate receiving your revised manuscript by 25 July 2019. When you are ready to submit your revision, log on to <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://www.editorialmanager.com/pone/" ns0:type="simple">https://www.editorialmanager.com/pone/</ext-link> and select the 'Submissions Needing Revision' folder to locate your manuscript file.</p>
<p>If you would like to make changes to your financial disclosure, please include your updated statement in your cover letter.</p>
<p>To enhance the reproducibility of your results, we recommend that if applicable you deposit your laboratory protocols in protocols.io, where a protocol can be assigned its own identifier (DOI) such that it can be cited independently in the future. For instructions see: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://journals.plos.org/plosone/s/submission-guidelines#loc-laboratory-protocols" ns0:type="simple">http://journals.plos.org/plosone/s/submission-guidelines#loc-laboratory-protocols</ext-link></p>
<p>Please include the following items when submitting your revised manuscript:</p>
<p><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>A rebuttal letter that responds to each point raised by the academic editor and reviewer(s). This letter should be uploaded as separate file and labeled 'Response to Reviewers'.</p></list-item><list-item><p>A marked-up copy of your manuscript that highlights changes made to the original version. This file should be uploaded as separate file and labeled 'Revised Manuscript with Track Changes'.</p></list-item><list-item><p>An unmarked version of your revised paper without tracked changes. This file should be uploaded as separate file and labeled 'Manuscript'.</p></list-item></list></p>
<p>Please note while forming your response, if your article is accepted, you may have the opportunity to make the peer review history publicly available. The record will include editor decision letters (with reviews) and your responses to reviewer comments. If eligible, we will contact you to opt in or out.</p>
<p>We look forward to receiving your revised manuscript.</p>
<p>Kind regards,</p>
<p>Tunira Bhadauria, Ph.D.</p>
<p>Academic Editor</p>
<p>PLOS ONE</p>
<p>Journal Requirements:</p>
<p>1. When submitting your revision, we need you to address these additional requirements.</p>
<p>Please ensure that your manuscript meets PLOS ONE's style requirements, including those for file naming. The PLOS ONE style templates can be found at</p>
<p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://www.journals.plos.org/plosone/s/file?id=wjVg/PLOSOne_formatting_sample_main_body.pdf" ns0:type="simple">http://www.journals.plos.org/plosone/s/file?id=wjVg/PLOSOne_formatting_sample_main_body.pdf</ext-link> and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://www.journals.plos.org/plosone/s/file?id=ba62/PLOSOne_formatting_sample_title_authors_affiliations.pdf" ns0:type="simple">http://www.journals.plos.org/plosone/s/file?id=ba62/PLOSOne_formatting_sample_title_authors_affiliations.pdf</ext-link></p>
<p>2. Please upload a copy of Figures 5 and 6, to which you refer in your text on page 11. If the figure is no longer to be included as part of the submission please remove all reference to it within the text.</p>
<p>3. In your Methods section, please provide additional location information of the collection sites, including geographic coordinates for the data set if available.</p>
<p>4. In your Methods section, please provide additional information regarding the permits you obtained for the work. Please ensure you have included the full name of the authority that approved the field site access and, if no permits were required, a brief statement explaining why.</p>
<p>5. Please include your tables as part of your main manuscript and remove the individual files. Please note that supplementary tables (should remain/ be uploaded) as separate "supporting information" files</p>
<p>Additional Editor Comments:</p>
<p>1]The authors have done an interesting study determining the reason as to why P. corethrurus is unable to invade the agricultural niche of B. pearsei?</p>
<p>2]The design of experiment is very appropriate and accurate.</p>
<p>3]But there are some loop holes that need to be plugged for eg: the figure numbers need to be checked and rectified</p>
<p>4]English language needs to be checked by someone with good command over language for clarification in the manuscript</p>
<p>5]Diiscussion should be written more precisely and directly analysing the results obtained in the experiments performed.</p>
<p>6]Other comments have been high lighted in the manuscript and also by the reviewers ,</p>
<p>7]All the comments must be answered to and necessary rectifications made in the manuscript based on the reviewers comments</p>
<p>Therefore manuscript can be accepted for publication only after the major revesion.</p>
<p>[Note: HTML markup is below. Please do not edit.]</p>
<p>Reviewers' comments:</p>
<p>Reviewer's Responses to Questions</p>
<p><bold>Comments to the Author</bold></p>
<p>1. Is the manuscript technically sound, and do the data support the conclusions?</p>
<p>The manuscript must describe a technically sound piece of scientific research with data that supports the conclusions. Experiments must have been conducted rigorously, with appropriate controls, replication, and sample sizes. The conclusions must be drawn appropriately based on the data presented. </p>
<p>Reviewer #1: Partly</p>
<p>**********</p>
<p>2. Has the statistical analysis been performed appropriately and rigorously? </p>
<p>Reviewer #1: Yes</p>
<p>**********</p>
<p>3. Have the authors made all data underlying the findings in their manuscript fully available?</p>
<p>The <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://www.plosone.org/static/policies.action#sharing" ns0:type="simple">PLOS Data policy</ext-link> requires authors to make all data underlying the findings described in their manuscript fully available without restriction, with rare exception (please refer to the Data Availability Statement in the manuscript PDF file). The data should be provided as part of the manuscript or its supporting information, or deposited to a public repository. For example, in addition to summary statistics, the data points behind means, medians and variance measures should be available. If there are restrictions on publicly sharing data&#8212;e.g. participant privacy or use of data from a third party&#8212;those must be specified.</p>
<p>Reviewer #1: Yes</p>
<p>**********</p>
<p>4. Is the manuscript presented in an intelligible fashion and written in standard English?</p>
<p>PLOS ONE does not copyedit accepted manuscripts, so the language in submitted articles must be clear, correct, and unambiguous. Any typographical or grammatical errors should be corrected at revision, so please note any specific errors here.</p>
<p>Reviewer #1: Yes</p>
<p>**********</p>
<p>5. Review Comments to the Author</p>
<p>Please use the space provided to explain your answers to the questions above. You may also include additional comments for the author, including concerns about dual publication, research ethics, or publication ethics. (Please upload your review as an attachment if it exceeds 20,000 characters)</p>
<p>Reviewer #1: The study asks an interesting question given at the end of the introduction&#8212;why hasn&#8217;t P. corethrurus invaded the agricultural niche of B. pearsei? The experiment seems well designed. However, there are some items in the test that need to be corrected (e.g. figure numbers), some revisions for clarity are needed, and the Discussion needs revisions to make it more directly relevant to the experiment that was conducted. These are explained below.</p>
<p>Page 4 line 3, 100-120 of the species?</p>
<p>Last sentence page 4, confusing&#8212;are you switching back to P. corethrurus here?</p>
<p>Page 6, second to last line, 61.9 C/N does not have a percent&#8212;it&#8217;s a ratio</p>
<p>Page 8, mortality, please state the mortality results more systematically, instead of a few selected treatments.</p>
<p>Page 8-9. Figure 1 does not show growth rates, it shows biomass at 100 days with three food sources. In the second sentence it should say &#8216;At 100 days the biomass of invasive and native species&#8230;&#8217; The last sentence appears to actually present growth rate data. Biomass at 100 days is related to the growth rate, but is not the same thing.</p>
<p>Middle of page 10. Fig. 4 does not show cocoon biomass.</p>
<p>Page 10-11, there are no Figs 5 and 6 in the manuscript that I have.</p>
<p>Discussion:</p>
<p>First sentence is incomplete; either say what happens when populations respond to domestication, or delete &#8216;When&#8217; at the beginning of the sentence.</p>
<p>Page 13-14, 275 and 176 species of bacteria?</p>
<p>Page 15, Levis et al 2018 (not 208).</p>
<p>Most of the Discussion (although very interesting) is not about what was studied, and connections between the experiment presented in the results section and discussion topics are weak. For example, does your P. corethrurus belong to one of the four agrotypes mentioned on page 16? Do you know which bacterial taxonomic groups are present in your P. corethrurus?</p>
<p>The statements in the concluding paragraph on page 17 have no direct evidence from your study. Again, it is interesting, and well written, but very speculative as it relates to the study.</p>
<p>There is almost a review paper about evolutionary/agro-history of the earthworm species embedded in the Discussion. Perhaps the authors should consider expanding this and publishing it separately as a review paper! However, for purposes of the manuscript under review, the connections to the experiment are too weak, and this review material should be greatly shortened to one or two paragraphs. In place of most of this material there should be more discussion points related directly to the experimental evidence&#8212;for example comparison to survival rates, attainment of sexual maturity, biomass and cocoon production from other studies of these two earthworm species. Also, the conclusion should have a succinct summary about how the evidence from the experiment answers the question posed at the end of the introduction.</p>
<p>**********</p>
<p>6. PLOS authors have the option to publish the peer review history of their article (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://journals.plos.org/plosone/s/editorial-and-peer-review-process#loc-peer-review-history" ns0:type="simple">what does this mean?</ext-link>). If published, this will include your full peer review and any attached files.</p>
<p>If you choose &#8220;no&#8221;, your identity will remain anonymous but your review may still be made public.</p>
<p><bold>Do you want your identity to be public for this peer review?</bold> For information about this choice, including consent withdrawal, please see our <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://www.plos.org/privacy-policy" ns0:type="simple">Privacy Policy</ext-link>.</p>
<p>Reviewer #1: No</p>
<p>[NOTE: If reviewer comments were submitted as an attachment file, they will be attached to this email and accessible via the submission site. Please log into your account, locate the manuscript record, and check for the action link "View Attachments". If this link does not appear, there are no attachment files to be viewed.]</p>
<p>While revising your submission, please upload your figure files to the Preflight Analysis and Conversion Engine (PACE) digital diagnostic tool, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://pacev2.apexcovantage.com/" ns0:type="simple">https://pacev2.apexcovantage.com/</ext-link>. PACE helps ensure that figures meet PLOS requirements. To use PACE, you must first register as a user. Registration is free. Then, login and navigate to the UPLOAD tab, where you will find detailed instructions on how to use the tool. If you encounter any issues or have any questions when using PACE, please email us at <email ns0:type="simple">figures@plos.org</email>. Please note that Supporting Information files do not need this step.</p>
</body>
</sub-article>
