<sub-article xmlns:ns0="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="aggregated-review-documents" id="pone.0222756.r001" specific-use="decision-letter">
<front-stub>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0222756.r001</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title>Decision Letter 0</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Loor</surname>
<given-names>Juan J</given-names>
</name>
<role>Academic Editor</role>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<permissions>
<copyright-year>2019</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>Juan J Loor</copyright-holder>
<license ns0:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
<license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" ns0:type="simple">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<related-object document-id="10.1371/journal.pone.0222756" document-id-type="doi" document-type="article" id="rel-obj001" link-type="peer-reviewed-article" />
<custom-meta-group>
<custom-meta>
<meta-name>Submission Version</meta-name>
<meta-value>0</meta-value>
</custom-meta>
</custom-meta-group>
</front-stub>
<body>
<p>
<named-content content-type="letter-date">11 Jul 2019</named-content>
</p>
<p>PONE-D-19-14824</p>
<p>Confronting pastoralists&#8217; knowledge of cattle breeds raised in the extensive production systems of Benin with multivariate analyses of morphological traits</p>
<p>PLOS ONE</p>
<p>Dear Dr Dossa,</p>
<p>Thank you for submitting your manuscript to PLOS ONE. After careful consideration, we feel that it has merit but does not fully meet PLOS ONE&#8217;s publication criteria as it currently stands. Therefore, we invite you to submit a revised version of the manuscript that addresses the points raised during the review process.</p>
<p>We would appreciate receiving your revised manuscript by Aug 25 2019 11:59PM. When you are ready to submit your revision, log on to <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://www.editorialmanager.com/pone/" ns0:type="simple">https://www.editorialmanager.com/pone/</ext-link> and select the 'Submissions Needing Revision' folder to locate your manuscript file.</p>
<p>If you would like to make changes to your financial disclosure, please include your updated statement in your cover letter.</p>
<p>To enhance the reproducibility of your results, we recommend that if applicable you deposit your laboratory protocols in protocols.io, where a protocol can be assigned its own identifier (DOI) such that it can be cited independently in the future. For instructions see: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://journals.plos.org/plosone/s/submission-guidelines#loc-laboratory-protocols" ns0:type="simple">http://journals.plos.org/plosone/s/submission-guidelines#loc-laboratory-protocols</ext-link></p>
<p>Please include the following items when submitting your revised manuscript:</p>
<p><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>A rebuttal letter that responds to each point raised by the academic editor and reviewer(s). This letter should be uploaded as separate file and labeled 'Response to Reviewers'.</p></list-item><list-item><p>A marked-up copy of your manuscript that highlights changes made to the original version. This file should be uploaded as separate file and labeled 'Revised Manuscript with Track Changes'.</p></list-item><list-item><p>An unmarked version of your revised paper without tracked changes. This file should be uploaded as separate file and labeled 'Manuscript'.</p></list-item></list></p>
<p>Please note while forming your response, if your article is accepted, you may have the opportunity to make the peer review history publicly available. The record will include editor decision letters (with reviews) and your responses to reviewer comments. If eligible, we will contact you to opt in or out.</p>
<p>We look forward to receiving your revised manuscript.</p>
<p>Kind regards,</p>
<p>Juan J Loor</p>
<p>Academic Editor</p>
<p>PLOS ONE</p>
<p>Journal Requirements:</p>
<p>1. When submitting your revision, we need you to address these additional requirements.</p>
<p>Please ensure that your manuscript meets PLOS ONE's style requirements, including those for file naming. The PLOS ONE style templates can be found at</p>
<p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://www.journals.plos.org/plosone/s/file?id=wjVg/PLOSOne_formatting_sample_main_body.pdf" ns0:type="simple">http://www.journals.plos.org/plosone/s/file?id=wjVg/PLOSOne_formatting_sample_main_body.pdf</ext-link> and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://www.journals.plos.org/plosone/s/file?id=ba62/PLOSOne_formatting_sample_title_authors_affiliations.pdf" ns0:type="simple">http://www.journals.plos.org/plosone/s/file?id=ba62/PLOSOne_formatting_sample_title_authors_affiliations.pdf</ext-link></p>
<p>2. We noticed you have some minor occurrence of overlapping text with the following previous publication(s), which needs to be addressed:</p>
<p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://www.ccsenet.org/journal/index.php/sar/article/view/0/39141" ns0:type="simple">http://www.ccsenet.org/journal/index.php/sar/article/view/0/39141</ext-link></p>
<p>In your revision ensure you cite all your sources (including your own works), and quote or rephrase any duplicated text outside the methods section. Further consideration is dependent on these concerns being addressed.</p>
<p>[Note: HTML markup is below. Please do not edit.]</p>
<p>Reviewers' comments:</p>
<p>Reviewer's Responses to Questions</p>
<p><bold>Comments to the Author</bold></p>
<p>1. Is the manuscript technically sound, and do the data support the conclusions?</p>
<p>The manuscript must describe a technically sound piece of scientific research with data that supports the conclusions. Experiments must have been conducted rigorously, with appropriate controls, replication, and sample sizes. The conclusions must be drawn appropriately based on the data presented. </p>
<p>Reviewer #1: Yes</p>
<p>Reviewer #2: Yes</p>
<p>Reviewer #3: Yes</p>
<p>**********</p>
<p>2. Has the statistical analysis been performed appropriately and rigorously? </p>
<p>Reviewer #1: Yes</p>
<p>Reviewer #2: Yes</p>
<p>Reviewer #3: Yes</p>
<p>**********</p>
<p>3. Have the authors made all data underlying the findings in their manuscript fully available?</p>
<p>The <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://www.plosone.org/static/policies.action#sharing" ns0:type="simple">PLOS Data policy</ext-link> requires authors to make all data underlying the findings described in their manuscript fully available without restriction, with rare exception (please refer to the Data Availability Statement in the manuscript PDF file). The data should be provided as part of the manuscript or its supporting information, or deposited to a public repository. For example, in addition to summary statistics, the data points behind means, medians and variance measures should be available. If there are restrictions on publicly sharing data&#8212;e.g. participant privacy or use of data from a third party&#8212;those must be specified.</p>
<p>Reviewer #1: Yes</p>
<p>Reviewer #2: Yes</p>
<p>Reviewer #3: Yes</p>
<p>**********</p>
<p>4. Is the manuscript presented in an intelligible fashion and written in standard English?</p>
<p>PLOS ONE does not copyedit accepted manuscripts, so the language in submitted articles must be clear, correct, and unambiguous. Any typographical or grammatical errors should be corrected at revision, so please note any specific errors here.</p>
<p>Reviewer #1: Yes</p>
<p>Reviewer #2: Yes</p>
<p>Reviewer #3: Yes</p>
<p>**********</p>
<p>5. Review Comments to the Author</p>
<p>Please use the space provided to explain your answers to the questions above. You may also include additional comments for the author, including concerns about dual publication, research ethics, or publication ethics. (Please upload your review as an attachment if it exceeds 20,000 characters)</p>
<p>Reviewer #1: The paper Confronting pastoralists&#8217; knowledge of cattle breeds raised in the extensive production systems of Benin with multivariate analyses of morphological traits is a good paper.</p>
<p>In my opinion need:</p>
<p>1. In Table 1:) Suggest drop this information [Region; Agroecological zone (a); Soil type (a); Rainy season] on the table. Write in Material and Method (text body)</p>
<p>2. In Line 58: Version of SAS (2008) &#8211; is a paid program. Need use a actual version or use a SAS Student; (49. SAS (Statistical Analysis System Software), 2008. SAS Version 9.2, SAS Institute Inc, 512 Cary, NC, USA.)</p>
<p>3. The authors can insert an image et one cattle bread (Supporting information); Need insert the general names of each breed if had.</p>
<p>4. On the table 3: what&#8217;s means Trait expression ;;) coat color Variable?</p>
<p>Reviewer #2: This paper is valuable in that it helps to fill the large data-gap on African cattle. The paper is also well written and statistically sound.</p>
<p>My main comments are to (a) reduce the length of the introduction, (b) add a disccussion on the meaning of 'breed' which is subjective, and how you define it in this work.</p>
<p>If you do have tissue / blood / hair samples from the animals you measured, it would be extremely interesting to compare genomic results to those presented here.</p>
<p>Reviewer #3: Comments to the Author</p>
<p>Comments about the manuscript entitled &#8220;Confronting pastoralists&#8217; knowledge of cattle breeds raised in the extensive production systems of Benin with multivariate analyses of morphological traits&#8221;.</p>
<p>Authors investigated on the pastoralists&#8217; knowledge about of the cattle breeds raised in Benin. Methods used were clearly explained, but some precisions are necessary. Obtained results must be encouraged.</p>
<p>In general, this manuscript can be accepted for publication. Further remarks are given below.</p>
<p>Abstract</p>
<p>L21: change &#8220;characteristics-&#8221; to &#8220;characteristics.&#8221;</p>
<p>L34: Change &#8216;&#8216;keepers&#8217;&#8217; to &#8216;&#8216;herders&#8217;&#8217; and harmonize it in all the text</p>
<p>Introduction</p>
<p>L56-58: Add reference sources</p>
<p>L91-95: Change &#8216;&#8216;[42] further argues that in traditional livestock production systems, &#8230;. phenotypic traits.&#8217;&#8217; to &#8216;&#8216;Further, in traditional livestock production systems, &#8230;. phenotypic traits [42].&#8217;&#8217;</p>
<p>L97-98: Move &#8216;&#8216;[47,48]&#8217;&#8217; at the end of the sentence</p>
<p>L99: Change &#8216;&#8216;with the aim&#8217;&#8217; to &#8216;&#8216;in order to&#8217;&#8217;</p>
<p>L100-102: Rephrase to show clearly the study aim like that is in the abstract</p>
<p>Material and methods</p>
<p>How were interviewed herders sample population fixed? The study may justify that</p>
<p>Table 1: Change &#8216;&#8216;(a)&#8217;&#8217; to [70]; &#8216;&#8216;(b)&#8217;&#8217; to [72] and &#8216;&#8216;(c)&#8217;&#8217; to [71]</p>
<p>Table 1: Change &#8216;&#8216;Estimated total cattle population&#8217;&#8217; to &#8216;&#8216;Estimating of the total cattle population&#8217;&#8217;</p>
<p>L1: Harmonize expression &#8216;&#8216;cattle farmer&#8217;&#8217; or &#8216;&#8216;cattle herder&#8217;&#8217; in the all of the text</p>
<p>L6-7: CARDER was the departmental institution. So Communal Sector of the Agricultural Development (SCDA) was the local institution in the municipalities.</p>
<p>L11: Delete &#8216;&#8216;reported by&#8217;&#8217;</p>
<p>L17: Rephrase &#8216;&#8216;identify the villages&#8217;&#8217;</p>
<p>L59-60: Why this exclusion? Were these 6 animals included in the 1401 individual cattle?</p>
<p>Results</p>
<p>L88-89: What were the language of these breed names?</p>
<p>L97-99: What about of Keteeji Bargouji ? are they taurine or zebu breeds?</p>
<p>L105: Table 3: 8 breeds were described. What about of &#8216;&#8216;Keteeji&#8217;&#8217; ?</p>
<p>L105: Table 3: Goudali or Gudali? Harmonize it</p>
<p>Discussion</p>
<p>L207: Write &#8216;&#8216;Fongbe language&#8217;&#8217;</p>
<p>L219-221: Rephrase: &#8216;&#8216;For instance, a recent study conducted in ??? reported only five cattle breeds (Keteeji, Jaliji/Djelliji, Bodeeji, Tchiwali/Yakanaji and Gudali) [48] out of the total of ten recorded in the current study&#8217;&#8217;</p>
<p>L221: Change &#8216;&#8216;their study&#8217;&#8217; to &#8216;&#8216;the last authors study&#8217;&#8217;</p>
<p>L234: Rephrase &#8216;&#8216;by [16,60]&#8217;&#8217; to &#8216;&#8216;through others studies [16,60]&#8221;</p>
<p>L252: Rephrase &#8216;&#8216;as previously reported by [17,62]&#8217;&#8217; to &#8216;&#8216;as previously reported [17,62]&#8217;&#8217;</p>
<p>Ovoid &#8216;&#8216;by [&#8230;]&#8217;&#8217; and harmonize it in the all of the text.</p>
<p>**********</p>
<p>6. PLOS authors have the option to publish the peer review history of their article (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://journals.plos.org/plosone/s/editorial-and-peer-review-process#loc-peer-review-history" ns0:type="simple">what does this mean?</ext-link>). If published, this will include your full peer review and any attached files.</p>
<p>If you choose &#8220;no&#8221;, your identity will remain anonymous but your review may still be made public.</p>
<p><bold>Do you want your identity to be public for this peer review?</bold> For information about this choice, including consent withdrawal, please see our <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://www.plos.org/privacy-policy" ns0:type="simple">Privacy Policy</ext-link>.</p>
<p>Reviewer #1: No</p>
<p>Reviewer #2: No</p>
<p>Reviewer #3: Yes: S&#232;manou Robert DOGNON</p>
<p>[NOTE: If reviewer comments were submitted as an attachment file, they will be attached to this email and accessible via the submission site. Please log into your account, locate the manuscript record, and check for the action link "View Attachments". If this link does not appear, there are no attachment files to be viewed.]</p>
<p>While revising your submission, please upload your figure files to the Preflight Analysis and Conversion Engine (PACE) digital diagnostic tool, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://pacev2.apexcovantage.com/" ns0:type="simple">https://pacev2.apexcovantage.com/</ext-link>. PACE helps ensure that figures meet PLOS requirements. To use PACE, you must first register as a user. Registration is free. Then, login and navigate to the UPLOAD tab, where you will find detailed instructions on how to use the tool. If you encounter any issues or have any questions when using PACE, please email us at <email ns0:type="simple">figures@plos.org</email>. Please note that Supporting Information files do not need this step.</p>
<supplementary-material id="pone.0222756.s015" mimetype="application/pdf" position="float" ns0:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0222756.s015" ns0:type="simple">
<label>Attachment</label>
<caption>
<p>Submitted filename: <named-content content-type="submitted-filename">PONE-D-19-14824_reviewer.pdf</named-content></p>
</caption>
</supplementary-material>
</body>
</sub-article>
