<sub-article xmlns:ns0="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="aggregated-review-documents" id="pone.0222141.r001" specific-use="decision-letter">
<front-stub>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0222141.r001</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title>Decision Letter 0</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Meyre</surname>
<given-names>David</given-names>
</name>
<role>Academic Editor</role>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<permissions>
<copyright-year>2019</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>David Meyre</copyright-holder>
<license ns0:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
<license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" ns0:type="simple">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<related-object document-id="10.1371/journal.pone.0222141" document-id-type="doi" document-type="article" id="rel-obj001" link-type="peer-reviewed-article" />
<custom-meta-group>
<custom-meta>
<meta-name>Submission Version</meta-name>
<meta-value>0</meta-value>
</custom-meta>
</custom-meta-group>
</front-stub>
<body>
<p>
<named-content content-type="letter-date">21 Jul 2019</named-content>
</p>
<p>PONE-D-19-16847</p>
<p>The effect of birth weight on body composition: Evidence from a birth cohort and a Mendelian randomization study</p>
<p>PLOS ONE</p>
<p>Dear Dr Schooling,</p>
<p>Thank you for submitting your manuscript to PLOS ONE. After careful consideration, we feel that it has merit but does not fully meet PLOS ONE&#8217;s publication criteria as it currently stands. Therefore, we invite you to submit a revised version of the manuscript that addresses the points raised during the review process.</p>
<p>We would appreciate receiving your revised manuscript by Sep 04 2019 11:59PM. When you are ready to submit your revision, log on to <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://www.editorialmanager.com/pone/" ns0:type="simple">https://www.editorialmanager.com/pone/</ext-link> and select the 'Submissions Needing Revision' folder to locate your manuscript file.</p>
<p>If you would like to make changes to your financial disclosure, please include your updated statement in your cover letter.</p>
<p>To enhance the reproducibility of your results, we recommend that if applicable you deposit your laboratory protocols in protocols.io, where a protocol can be assigned its own identifier (DOI) such that it can be cited independently in the future. For instructions see: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://journals.plos.org/plosone/s/submission-guidelines#loc-laboratory-protocols" ns0:type="simple">http://journals.plos.org/plosone/s/submission-guidelines#loc-laboratory-protocols</ext-link></p>
<p>Please include the following items when submitting your revised manuscript:</p>
<p><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>A rebuttal letter that responds to each point raised by the academic editor and reviewer(s). This letter should be uploaded as separate file and labeled 'Response to Reviewers'.</p></list-item><list-item><p>A marked-up copy of your manuscript that highlights changes made to the original version. This file should be uploaded as separate file and labeled 'Revised Manuscript with Track Changes'.</p></list-item><list-item><p>An unmarked version of your revised paper without tracked changes. This file should be uploaded as separate file and labeled 'Manuscript'.</p></list-item></list></p>
<p>Please note while forming your response, if your article is accepted, you may have the opportunity to make the peer review history publicly available. The record will include editor decision letters (with reviews) and your responses to reviewer comments. If eligible, we will contact you to opt in or out.</p>
<p>We look forward to receiving your revised manuscript.</p>
<p>Kind regards,</p>
<p>David Meyre</p>
<p>Academic Editor</p>
<p>PLOS ONE</p>
<p>Journal Requirements:</p>
<p>When submitting your revision, we need you to address these additional requirements.</p>
<p>Please ensure that your manuscript meets PLOS ONE's style requirements, including those for file naming. The PLOS ONE style templates can be found at</p>
<p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://www.journals.plos.org/plosone/s/file?id=wjVg/PLOSOne_formatting_sample_main_body.pdf" ns0:type="simple">http://www.journals.plos.org/plosone/s/file?id=wjVg/PLOSOne_formatting_sample_main_body.pdf</ext-link> and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://www.journals.plos.org/plosone/s/file?id=ba62/PLOSOne_formatting_sample_title_authors_affiliations.pdf" ns0:type="simple">http://www.journals.plos.org/plosone/s/file?id=ba62/PLOSOne_formatting_sample_title_authors_affiliations.pdf</ext-link></p>
<p>[Note: HTML markup is below. Please do not edit.]</p>
<p>Reviewers' comments:</p>
<p>Reviewer's Responses to Questions</p>
<p><bold>Comments to the Author</bold></p>
<p>1. Is the manuscript technically sound, and do the data support the conclusions?</p>
<p>The manuscript must describe a technically sound piece of scientific research with data that supports the conclusions. Experiments must have been conducted rigorously, with appropriate controls, replication, and sample sizes. The conclusions must be drawn appropriately based on the data presented. </p>
<p>Reviewer #1: Yes</p>
<p>Reviewer #2: Partly</p>
<p>**********</p>
<p>2. Has the statistical analysis been performed appropriately and rigorously? </p>
<p>Reviewer #1: Yes</p>
<p>Reviewer #2: No</p>
<p>**********</p>
<p>3. Have the authors made all data underlying the findings in their manuscript fully available?</p>
<p>The <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://www.plosone.org/static/policies.action#sharing" ns0:type="simple">PLOS Data policy</ext-link> requires authors to make all data underlying the findings described in their manuscript fully available without restriction, with rare exception (please refer to the Data Availability Statement in the manuscript PDF file). The data should be provided as part of the manuscript or its supporting information, or deposited to a public repository. For example, in addition to summary statistics, the data points behind means, medians and variance measures should be available. If there are restrictions on publicly sharing data&#8212;e.g. participant privacy or use of data from a third party&#8212;those must be specified.</p>
<p>Reviewer #1: Yes</p>
<p>Reviewer #2: Yes</p>
<p>**********</p>
<p>4. Is the manuscript presented in an intelligible fashion and written in standard English?</p>
<p>PLOS ONE does not copyedit accepted manuscripts, so the language in submitted articles must be clear, correct, and unambiguous. Any typographical or grammatical errors should be corrected at revision, so please note any specific errors here.</p>
<p>Reviewer #1: Yes</p>
<p>Reviewer #2: Yes</p>
<p>**********</p>
<p>5. Review Comments to the Author</p>
<p>Please use the space provided to explain your answers to the questions above. You may also include additional comments for the author, including concerns about dual publication, research ethics, or publication ethics. (Please upload your review as an attachment if it exceeds 20,000 characters)</p>
<p>Reviewer #1: It was a pleasure to review this comprehensive study performed by Liu and colleagues, investigating the effect of birth weight on consequent body composition. The authors are experienced with the applied methods and have taken care in the performing appropriate analyses.</p>
<p>The work is already close to a standard suitable for publication. My main suggestion for improvement would be some clarification regarding the interpretation of causality. I think it is important that the authors discuss the potential implications of a shared (genetic) aetiology between birth weight and consequent body composition. Keeping this in mind, is it justified that the authors should imply in their conclusion that birth weight has a causal effect on consequent body composition?</p>
<p>In any case, I think that the authors should also be more clear about whether they are genuinely suggesting birth weight as a target for clinical intervention - although they do state this in the last line of the conclusion, I must admit that I'm struggling to take it seriously. The practicalities of modifying birth weight is another consideration. How might this be achieved? If the authors prefer not to answer this, then they should probably remove this suggestion.</p>
<p>Some discussion about the range of birth weights for which these findings might apply is also warranted. Can these estimates be extrapolated to the extremes of birth weight, for example?</p>
<p>Finally, I wonder whether the authors might also consider replacing (or supplementing) some of the existing results tables with figures (e.g. forest plots of the estimates and their confidence intervals). The current format used for presenting the data is a little overwhelming in places and therefore difficult to follow. Figures might make things easier to digest.</p>
<p>Reviewer #2: The authors examined the associations of birth weight (BW) with muscle and fat mass in an observational study. They also performed a Mendelian Randomisation (MR) of BW on these measures in the UK Biobank study. I have several major concerns relating to the MR section of the paper.</p>
<p>The authors do not clearly state the question that they are seeking to answer with the BW-fat/muscle MR analysis. It would be helpful if the authors could provide a diagram (eg. a DAG) explaining the causal question which they seek to answer. For example, are the authors using birth weight as a proxy for intrauterine exposures which might influence muscle and fat mass? If so, the maternal birth weight-associated alleles that are not passed to the child are the appropriate instrumental variables to use. The issue of MR in this context was discussed in the latest BW GWAS paper (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41588-019-0403-1" ns0:type="simple">https://doi.org/10.1038/s41588-019-0403-1</ext-link>). Further papers discussing this issue are <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://doi.org/10.12688/wellcomeopenres.10567.1" ns0:type="simple">https://doi.org/10.12688/wellcomeopenres.10567.1</ext-link> and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://doi.org/10.1093/ije/dyz019" ns0:type="simple">https://doi.org/10.1093/ije/dyz019</ext-link>. Alternatively, the authors might be asking about whether the genetic variation underlying birth weight is shared with the underlying muscle and fat mass, in which case, the fetal genotype is more important. Could the authors please clarify this.</p>
<p>A major problem in MR with birth weight using fetal genetic instruments as the exposure is the violation of MR assumptions by the association of maternal genotype with the outcome of interest. The latest BW GWAS paper discovered additional BW associated SNPs and also quantified the independent maternal and fetal associations with BW at each of the loci. Ideally this larger list and independent fetal effect sizes should be used for the exposure SNPs, the summary statistics from these analyses adjusted for maternal/fetal genotype associations are available to download from the EGG consortium website <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://egg-consortium.org/birth-weight-2019.html" ns0:type="simple">http://egg-consortium.org/birth-weight-2019.html</ext-link>. These adjusted association statistics correct the SNP-exposure associations for maternal genetic effects. This still would not get around the problem of the potential violation of the MR assumptions, indeed the large attenuation of the association results when potentially maternal SNPs are excluded from the analyses suggests that failing to account for maternal effects may be affecting the results. To properly perform these analyses the SNP-outcome associations should be corrected for maternal genetic associations. If this is not possible, this limitation should be clearly stated and fully discussed in the paper. The confounding introduced by maternal genotype is briefly mentioned at the end of the limitations section, but the potential impact of this on the results and the interpretation of them is not given sufficient attention and need to be carefully discussed and made more prominent.</p>
<p>It is also not clear to me why the authors reduced the original list of 60 BW SNPs to 47. The list of 60 loci already represents a list of independent association signals. A lot of the SNPs which were removed seem to be correlation artefacts rather than genuine LD, for example the SNP rs61830764 (DTL) is over 50mb from the nearest signal suggesting that the correlation here doesn&#8217;t reflect real LD. The signal rs1011939 (GPR139) also is the only SNP on chromosome 16 but seems to have been dropped as &#8220;not independent&#8221; although there can be no real LD with the other signals.</p>
<p>Other comments</p>
<p>In the limitations section, point 6 leaves me confused. They state &#8220;no age-specific genetic predictors of BW are available&#8221;, but birth weight is by definition the weight at birth, there is no age variation in BW. Point 8 also leaves me a little confused. It talks about lifetime exposure, but birth weight is again defined only at birth. I suggest the authors rephrase this point as I&#8217;m not entirely sure from what they have written what they are trying to say here.</p>
<p>**********</p>
<p>6. PLOS authors have the option to publish the peer review history of their article (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://journals.plos.org/plosone/s/editorial-and-peer-review-process#loc-peer-review-history" ns0:type="simple">what does this mean?</ext-link>). If published, this will include your full peer review and any attached files.</p>
<p>If you choose &#8220;no&#8221;, your identity will remain anonymous but your review may still be made public.</p>
<p><bold>Do you want your identity to be public for this peer review?</bold> For information about this choice, including consent withdrawal, please see our <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://www.plos.org/privacy-policy" ns0:type="simple">Privacy Policy</ext-link>.</p>
<p>Reviewer #1: Yes: Dipender Gill</p>
<p>Reviewer #2: No</p>
<p>[NOTE: If reviewer comments were submitted as an attachment file, they will be attached to this email and accessible via the submission site. Please log into your account, locate the manuscript record, and check for the action link "View Attachments". If this link does not appear, there are no attachment files to be viewed.]</p>
<p>While revising your submission, please upload your figure files to the Preflight Analysis and Conversion Engine (PACE) digital diagnostic tool, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://pacev2.apexcovantage.com/" ns0:type="simple">https://pacev2.apexcovantage.com/</ext-link>. PACE helps ensure that figures meet PLOS requirements. To use PACE, you must first register as a user. Registration is free. Then, login and navigate to the UPLOAD tab, where you will find detailed instructions on how to use the tool. If you encounter any issues or have any questions when using PACE, please email us at <email ns0:type="simple">figures@plos.org</email>. Please note that Supporting Information files do not need this step.</p>
</body>
</sub-article>
