<sub-article xmlns:ns0="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="aggregated-review-documents" id="pcbi.1007383.r005" specific-use="decision-letter">
<front-stub>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1007383.r005</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title>Decision Letter 2</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Ben-Tal</surname>
<given-names>Nir</given-names>
</name>
<role>Deputy Editor</role>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Wei</surname>
<given-names>Guanghong</given-names>
</name>
<role>Associate Editor</role>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<permissions>
<copyright-year>2019</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>Ben-Tal, Wei</copyright-holder>
<license ns0:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
<license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" ns0:type="simple">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<related-object document-id="10.1371/journal.pcbi.1007383" document-id-type="doi" document-type="article" id="rel-obj005" link-type="peer-reviewed-article" />
<custom-meta-group>
<custom-meta>
<meta-name>Submission Version</meta-name>
<meta-value>2</meta-value>
</custom-meta>
</custom-meta-group>
</front-stub>
<body>
<p>
<named-content content-type="letter-date">9 Sep 2019</named-content>
</p>
<p>Dear Dr Czub,</p>
<p>We are pleased to inform you that your manuscript 'Why do G-quadruplexes dimerize through the 5&#8217;-ends? Driving forces for G4 DNA dimerization examined in atomic detail.' has been provisionally accepted for publication in PLOS Computational Biology.</p>
<p>Before your manuscript can be formally accepted you will need to complete some formatting changes, which you will receive in a follow up email. Please be aware that it may take several days for you to receive this email; during this time no action is required by you. Once you have received these formatting requests, please note that your manuscript will not be scheduled for publication until you have made the required changes.</p>
<p>In the meantime, please log into Editorial Manager at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://www.editorialmanager.com/pcompbiol/" ns0:type="simple">https://www.editorialmanager.com/pcompbiol/</ext-link>, click the "Update My Information" link at the top of the page, and update your user information to ensure an efficient production and billing process.</p>
<p>One of the goals of PLOS is to make science accessible to educators and the public. PLOS staff issue occasional press releases and make early versions of PLOS Computational Biology articles available to science writers and journalists. PLOS staff also collaborate with Communication and Public Information Offices and would be happy to work with the relevant people at your institution or funding agency. If your institution or funding agency is interested in promoting your findings, please ask them to coordinate their releases with PLOS (contact <email ns0:type="simple">ploscompbiol@plos.org</email>).</p>
<p>Thank you again for supporting Open Access publishing. We look forward to publishing your paper in PLOS Computational Biology.</p>
<p>Sincerely,</p>
<p>Guanghong Wei</p>
<p>Associate Editor</p>
<p>PLOS Computational Biology</p>
<p>Nir Ben-Tal</p>
<p>Deputy Editor</p>
<p>PLOS Computational Biology</p>
<p>Reviewer's Responses to Questions</p>
<p><bold>Comments to the Authors:</bold></p>
<p><bold>Please note here if the review is uploaded as an attachment.</bold></p>
<p>Reviewer #3: The authors have addressed my concern and I think it should be published without further delay. One more correction, Page 3, line 99, "Table ??" should be "Table 1".</p>
<p>**********</p>
<p><bold>Have all data underlying the figures and results presented in the manuscript been provided?</bold></p>
<p>Large-scale datasets should be made available via a public repository as described in the <italic>PLOS Computational Biology</italic> <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://journals.plos.org/ploscompbiol/s/data-availability" ns0:type="simple">data availability policy</ext-link>, and numerical data that underlies graphs or summary statistics should be provided in spreadsheet form as supporting information.</p>
<p>Reviewer #3: Yes</p>
<p>**********</p>
<p>PLOS authors have the option to publish the peer review history of their article (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://journals.plos.org/ploscompbiol/s/editorial-and-peer-review-process#loc-peer-review-history" ns0:type="simple">what does this mean?</ext-link>). If published, this will include your full peer review and any attached files.</p>
<p>If you choose &#8220;no&#8221;, your identity will remain anonymous but your review may still be made public.</p>
<p><bold>Do you want your identity to be public for this peer review?</bold> For information about this choice, including consent withdrawal, please see our <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://www.plos.org/privacy-policy" ns0:type="simple">Privacy Policy</ext-link>.</p>
<p>Reviewer #3: No</p>
</body>
</sub-article>
