<sub-article xmlns:ns0="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="aggregated-review-documents" id="pone.0222943.r001" specific-use="decision-letter">
<front-stub>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0222943.r001</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title>Decision Letter 0</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Manicassamy</surname>
<given-names>Balaji</given-names>
</name>
<role>Academic Editor</role>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<permissions>
<copyright-year>2019</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>Balaji Manicassamy</copyright-holder>
<license ns0:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
<license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" ns0:type="simple">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<related-object document-id="10.1371/journal.pone.0222943" document-id-type="doi" document-type="article" id="rel-obj001" link-type="peer-reviewed-article" />
<custom-meta-group>
<custom-meta>
<meta-name>Submission Version</meta-name>
<meta-value>0</meta-value>
</custom-meta>
</custom-meta-group>
</front-stub>
<body>
<p>
<named-content content-type="letter-date">16 Jul 2019</named-content>
</p>
<p>PONE-D-19-15088</p>
<p>Experimental H1N1pdm09 infection in pigs mimics human seasonal influenza infections</p>
<p>PLOS ONE</p>
<p>Dear Dr. Blohm,</p>
<p>Thank you for submitting your manuscript to PLOS ONE. After careful consideration, we feel that it has merit but does not fully meet PLOS ONE&#8217;s publication criteria as it currently stands. Therefore, we invite you to submit a revised version of the manuscript that addresses the points raised during the review process.</p>
<p>We would appreciate receiving your revised manuscript by September 15, 2019. When you are ready to submit your revision, log on to <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://www.editorialmanager.com/pone/" ns0:type="simple">https://www.editorialmanager.com/pone/</ext-link> and select the 'Submissions Needing Revision' folder to locate your manuscript file.</p>
<p>If you would like to make changes to your financial disclosure, please include your updated statement in your cover letter.</p>
<p>To enhance the reproducibility of your results, we recommend that if applicable you deposit your laboratory protocols in protocols.io, where a protocol can be assigned its own identifier (DOI) such that it can be cited independently in the future. For instructions see: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://journals.plos.org/plosone/s/submission-guidelines#loc-laboratory-protocols" ns0:type="simple">http://journals.plos.org/plosone/s/submission-guidelines#loc-laboratory-protocols</ext-link></p>
<p>Please include the following items when submitting your revised manuscript:</p>
<p><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>A rebuttal letter that responds to each point raised by the academic editor and reviewer(s). This letter should be uploaded as separate file and labeled 'Response to Reviewers'.</p></list-item><list-item><p>A marked-up copy of your manuscript that highlights changes made to the original version. This file should be uploaded as separate file and labeled 'Revised Manuscript with Track Changes'.</p></list-item><list-item><p>An unmarked version of your revised paper without tracked changes. This file should be uploaded as separate file and labeled 'Manuscript'.</p></list-item></list></p>
<p>Please note while forming your response, if your article is accepted, you may have the opportunity to make the peer review history publicly available. The record will include editor decision letters (with reviews) and your responses to reviewer comments. If eligible, we will contact you to opt in or out.</p>
<p>We look forward to receiving your revised manuscript.</p>
<p>Kind regards,</p>
<p>Balaji Manicassamy, Ph.D.</p>
<p>Academic Editor</p>
<p>PLOS ONE</p>
<p>Journal Requirements:</p>
<p>1. When submitting your revision, we need you to address these additional requirements.</p>
<p>Please ensure that your manuscript meets PLOS ONE's style requirements, including those for file naming. The PLOS ONE style templates can be found at</p>
<p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://www.journals.plos.org/plosone/s/file?id=wjVg/PLOSOne_formatting_sample_main_body.pdf" ns0:type="simple">http://www.journals.plos.org/plosone/s/file?id=wjVg/PLOSOne_formatting_sample_main_body.pdf</ext-link> and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://www.journals.plos.org/plosone/s/file?id=ba62/PLOSOne_formatting_sample_title_authors_affiliations.pdf" ns0:type="simple">http://www.journals.plos.org/plosone/s/file?id=ba62/PLOSOne_formatting_sample_title_authors_affiliations.pdf</ext-link></p>
<p>2. We note that you have included the phrase &#8220;data not shown&#8221; in your manuscript. Unfortunately, this does not meet our data sharing requirements. PLOS does not permit references to inaccessible data. We require that authors provide all relevant data within the paper, Supporting Information files, or in an acceptable, public repository. Please add a citation to support this phrase or upload the data that corresponds with these findings to a stable repository (such as Figshare or Dryad) and provide and URLs, DOIs, or accession numbers that may be used to access these data. Or, if the data are not a core part of the research being presented in your study, we ask that you remove the phrase that refers to these data.</p>
<p>[Note: HTML markup is below. Please do not edit.]</p>
<p>Reviewers' comments:</p>
<p>Reviewer's Responses to Questions</p>
<p><bold>Comments to the Author</bold></p>
<p>1. Is the manuscript technically sound, and do the data support the conclusions?</p>
<p>The manuscript must describe a technically sound piece of scientific research with data that supports the conclusions. Experiments must have been conducted rigorously, with appropriate controls, replication, and sample sizes. The conclusions must be drawn appropriately based on the data presented. </p>
<p>Reviewer #1: Partly</p>
<p>Reviewer #2: Yes</p>
<p>Reviewer #3: Yes</p>
<p>**********</p>
<p>2. Has the statistical analysis been performed appropriately and rigorously? </p>
<p>Reviewer #1: N/A</p>
<p>Reviewer #2: Yes</p>
<p>Reviewer #3: Yes</p>
<p>**********</p>
<p>3. Have the authors made all data underlying the findings in their manuscript fully available?</p>
<p>The <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://www.plosone.org/static/policies.action#sharing" ns0:type="simple">PLOS Data policy</ext-link> requires authors to make all data underlying the findings described in their manuscript fully available without restriction, with rare exception (please refer to the Data Availability Statement in the manuscript PDF file). The data should be provided as part of the manuscript or its supporting information, or deposited to a public repository. For example, in addition to summary statistics, the data points behind means, medians and variance measures should be available. If there are restrictions on publicly sharing data&#8212;e.g. participant privacy or use of data from a third party&#8212;those must be specified.</p>
<p>Reviewer #1: Yes</p>
<p>Reviewer #2: Yes</p>
<p>Reviewer #3: Yes</p>
<p>**********</p>
<p>4. Is the manuscript presented in an intelligible fashion and written in standard English?</p>
<p>PLOS ONE does not copyedit accepted manuscripts, so the language in submitted articles must be clear, correct, and unambiguous. Any typographical or grammatical errors should be corrected at revision, so please note any specific errors here.</p>
<p>Reviewer #1: Yes</p>
<p>Reviewer #2: Yes</p>
<p>Reviewer #3: Yes</p>
<p>**********</p>
<p>5. Review Comments to the Author</p>
<p>Please use the space provided to explain your answers to the questions above. You may also include additional comments for the author, including concerns about dual publication, research ethics, or publication ethics. (Please upload your review as an attachment if it exceeds 20,000 characters)</p>
<p>Reviewer #1: 1. Please furnish information on the pre-screen done on the pigs. This should include both qPCR and serology (ELISA) for IAV, PRRSV, PPV, PCV 2, TTV. if animals were negative prior to D0, what was their status at the end of the study?</p>
<p>2. How were the mock and challenge groups housed? could comparative counts and FACS data for mocks also be clearly identified and shown along with challenge groups?</p>
<p>Reviewer #2: The manuscript by Schwaiger and colleagues describes the characterization of swine immune cell population changes following an experimental infection with a human H1N1 influenza virus. The results are of interest because swine are a natural host of influenza viruses and can also play a role in the zoonotic transmission of non-human influenza strains into the human population. In addition, (as stated by the authors), because of comparable sizes, immunity and physiology, pigs are a valuable animal model for evaluating immune responses, vaccines, antivirals, etc. In general, the manuscript is well written and provides detailed methods and results that can serve as a guide to other groups. To be fair, the authors should also point out some important differences between pigs and humans such as the much shorter &#8220;childhood&#8221; and general lifespan of pigs; important differences in immune cell populations such as the double positive CD4+CD8+ lymphocytes and strikingly different proportions of gamma-delta+ T cells in blood, or the lack of reagents and general knowledge of the pig&#8217;s immunity in comparison to other animal models (mice).</p>
<p>The authors should also consider the following specific comments:</p>
<p>Line 68. The animals were obtained from a commercial herd. If known, it would be important to state the serological status (from natural infection and from vaccination) of the mothers, since the presence of maternal antibodies against H1N1 influenza would have a strong impact in the evolution of the infection.</p>
<p>Line 73. Animals were re-infected with the same influenza strain 21 days after the first infection. In the context of modelling influenza in humans, it is not clear what was the purpose of this infection. In humans, re-infection occurs in the following influenza seasons (at least 1 year later) and by an antigenically drifted strain.</p>
<p>Line 122. &#8220;&#8230;antibody against the anti-matrixprotein&#8230;&#8221; this sentence is incorrect. It should be either &#8220;&#8230;antibody against the matrixprotein&#8230;&#8221; or &#8220;&#8230;anti-matrixprotein monoclonal antibody&#8230;&#8221;. Please correct.</p>
<p>Line 128. It might be useful to describe what TBS stands for.</p>
<p>Line 149. In this paragraph there is a sentence repeated &#8220;Antibodies used in this study are listed in Supplementary table 1&#8221;. Please correct.</p>
<p>Line 175 and beyond. Please consider using the term &#8220;necropsy&#8221; instead of &#8220;autopsy&#8221;.</p>
<p>Line 197. I believe the panels from figure 2 are cited wrongly: panel 2I shows H&amp;E staining (infiltrating inflammatory cells) and panel 2J shows immunohistochemistry (viral antigen).</p>
<p>Line 334. &#8220;&#8230;as well as in infectious conditions&#8221; I believe it should say &#8220;&#8230;as well as in infection conditions&#8221;.</p>
<p>Line 404. This is probably a typo, &#8220;deceased&#8221; should say &#8220;decreased&#8221;</p>
<p>Line 423. &#8220;&#8230;reported those CD4+ T cells to have cytolytic&#8230;&#8221; please double check. Did you mean CD8+?</p>
<p>Reviewer #3: The manuscript by Schwaiger and colleagues described experimental H1N1pdm09 infection in pigs in order to mimic human seasonal influenza infections. The authors used 2009 pandemic H1N1 virus to intranasally infect a group of 4-week-old pigs for 21 days, then re-infected them with the same virus again to investigate systemic and local immune responses by testing blood, mucosa of nasal cavity and lung tissues bronchoalveolar lavage fluid samples. Result showed that decreasing numbers of peripheral blood lymphocytes were detected after the first infection, the simultaneous increase in the frequencies of proliferating cells correlated with an increase in infiltrating leukocytes in the lung. Furthermore, a cytotoxic T cell response was detected but restricted to the respiratory route of virus entry such as the nose, the lung and the bronchoalveolar lavage according to detected enhanced perforin expression in &#945;&#946; and &#947;&#948; T cells in the respiratory tract. Increasing frequencies of CD8&#945;&#945; expressing &#945;&#946; T cells were also observed rapidly after the first infection, which could play a role in inhibition of uncontrolled inflammation in the respiratory tract. Authors conclude that the results from this study demonstrate that experimental influenza A virus infection in pigs mimics major characteristics of human seasonal influenza A virus infections. The manuscript is well written and provides interesting information which complements findings of former studies.</p>
<p>Comments:</p>
<p>The pigs used in the study were purchased from a commercial high health status herd. The detailed information on these pigs should be provided such as which pathogens (influenza A, D virus, PRRSV, PCV2 and mycoplasma etc) were tested prior to infection as any prior infection will impact the obtained results and further interpret.</p>
<p>In the figures 5, 6, 9 and 10, the data from only infected pigs were presented despite of the data at d0 as controls. If the pigs were infected other pathogens before, these data could not reflect the reality of only infection of 2009 pandemic H1N1 virus. Therefore, it is necessary to provide more detailed information on pigs</p>
<p>**********</p>
<p>6. PLOS authors have the option to publish the peer review history of their article (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://journals.plos.org/plosone/s/editorial-and-peer-review-process#loc-peer-review-history" ns0:type="simple">what does this mean?</ext-link>). If published, this will include your full peer review and any attached files.</p>
<p>If you choose &#8220;no&#8221;, your identity will remain anonymous but your review may still be made public.</p>
<p><bold>Do you want your identity to be public for this peer review?</bold> For information about this choice, including consent withdrawal, please see our <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://www.plos.org/privacy-policy" ns0:type="simple">Privacy Policy</ext-link>.</p>
<p>Reviewer #1: No</p>
<p>Reviewer #2: No</p>
<p>Reviewer #3: No</p>
<p>[NOTE: If reviewer comments were submitted as an attachment file, they will be attached to this email and accessible via the submission site. Please log into your account, locate the manuscript record, and check for the action link "View Attachments". If this link does not appear, there are no attachment files to be viewed.]</p>
<p>While revising your submission, please upload your figure files to the Preflight Analysis and Conversion Engine (PACE) digital diagnostic tool, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://pacev2.apexcovantage.com/" ns0:type="simple">https://pacev2.apexcovantage.com/</ext-link>. PACE helps ensure that figures meet PLOS requirements. To use PACE, you must first register as a user. Registration is free. Then, login and navigate to the UPLOAD tab, where you will find detailed instructions on how to use the tool. If you encounter any issues or have any questions when using PACE, please email us at <email ns0:type="simple">figures@plos.org</email>. Please note that Supporting Information files do not need this step.</p>
</body>
</sub-article>
