<sub-article xmlns:ns0="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="author-comment" id="pone.0221918.r002">
<front-stub>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0221918.r002</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title>Author response to Decision Letter 0</article-title>
</title-group>
<related-object document-id="10.1371/journal.pone.0221918" document-id-type="doi" document-type="peer-reviewed-article" id="rel-obj002" link-type="rebutted-decision-letter" object-id="10.1371/journal.pone.0221918.r001" object-id-type="doi" object-type="decision-letter" />
<custom-meta-group>
<custom-meta>
<meta-name>Submission Version</meta-name>
<meta-value>1</meta-value>
</custom-meta>
</custom-meta-group>
</front-stub>
<body>
<p>
<named-content content-type="author-response-date">3 Aug 2019</named-content>
</p>
<p>Reviewer #1: </p>
<p>Major comments</p>
<p>- The authors should give detailed information about the clinical findings of CSF patients and control patients. In particular, the symptomatic burden, including duration of the angina pattern, as well as frequency and severity of angina attacks should be reported and compared.</p>
<p>Response: </p>
<p>I added a definition to the methodology explaining what we meant by objective evidence of ischemia. Duration and frequency of angina information (for all patients) are not available in the database of this study, only the results of the non-invasive tests for coronary artery disease.</p>
<p>- The use of beta-blockers, vasodilators or other anti-ischemic drugs might have affected the detection of CSF. The authors should at least comment this point as a limitation of the study.</p>
<p>Response:</p>
<p>I added this comment to the limitation.</p>
<p>- If possible, the authors should report the educational and socioeconomic status of patients of the 2 groups, as possible factors influencing depression or anxiety status.</p>
<p>Response:</p>
<p>Unfortunately, data on educational and socioeconomic status of patients are not available in our database, and this is mentioned in the limitations section. However, our institution mainly serves patients of low-intermediate socio-economic class.</p>
<p>Minor comments</p>
<p>- The analysis of this study doesn&#8217;t account for the use of psychiatric drugs or other medication. Although none of the antidepressant drugs is known to cause CSF, as the authors say in the text, the answers of patients to the interviews might have been influenced by their use.</p>
<p>Response:</p>
<p>One of the exclusion criteria is the presence of psychiatric illness or the regular use of psychiatric drugs. So, this issue is unlikely to cause any bias. However, we mentioned it in the limitation section.</p>
<p>- Have the authors tried to exclude patients with possible &#8220;secondary form&#8221; of CSF (i.e. coronary artery ectasia, coronary artery spasm, pulmonary arterial hypertension, etc...)?</p>
<p>Response:</p>
<p>Yes, we excluded all patients with ectasia or spasm or known gross heart or vascular disease.</p>
<p>- The depression and anxiety rating scales (BAI and BDI), used to assess the severity of the psychiatric disorder, are two self-report scales. Thus, they depend on patients&#8217; reliability, time and context of interview administration.</p>
<p>Response: </p>
<p>This is an absolutely valid point, which we mentioned in the limitation section. For a better assessment of psychiatric status, this should have been correlated with clinical symptoms.</p>
<p>Reviewer #2: </p>
<p>Major comments</p>
<p>1. The study population is composed by consecutive patients who underwent coronary angiography due to &#8216;objective evidence of ischemia&#8217;. What do the Authors mean with that sentence? It is necessary to provide a clear definition of ischemia and a standardized diagnosis.</p>
<p>Response: </p>
<p>A statement was added to the paragraph defining the objective evidence of ischemia as positive exercise stress test or radionuclide study. </p>
<p>2. Diabetes, one of the most important cardiovascular risk factors and strongly related to endothelial dysfunction, seems not to be associated with CSF. The authors should be discussing this point</p>
<p>Response:</p>
<p>I added this point to the discussion.</p>
<p>3. Another point is the definition of the ex-smoker status. The Authors have provided an arbitrary definition of former smoker (only the patients who have stopped &gt; 2 years), not shared by the principal National Health Systems. This gross classification of patients probably leads to some bias in defining the relationship between smoking and CSF because the toxic substances contained in cigarettes act in a short/medium period of time in causing endothelial dysfunction and inflammation.</p>
<p>Response:</p>
<p>Some studies demonstrated that 1-year of smoking cessation was associated with improved endothelial function (Johnson, JACC 2010 May 4;55(18):1988-95). Our database defines former smoking as those who stopped &gt;2 years. We found that this was not a major issue (based on the above-mentioned study); so during patient enrollment, we opted not to change the current definition in our institution&#8217;s database. However, this is a valid point to be seriously considered before carrying on future research.</p>
<p>4. It is well established that depression and anxiety are twice as high in females than in males, in this study the mean BDI and BAI scores are lower in women. Maybe these scores should be integrated with a clinical evaluation of symptoms by a psychiatrist to avoid the subjective influence of the patients and on the physician in interpreting the answers. It would also be useful to provide the complete data of the prevalence and of the degree of anxiety and depression adjusted for gender.</p>
<p>Response:   </p>
<p>I added the total scores of BDI and BAI in males and females in both groups to the results section, the difference was not significant. This was different from the well-established fact referred to by the reviewer. I added this to the discussion section stating that this issue may be related to the different cohort used in the study. I also found another study showing similar data, and it was attributed to the difference in the instruments used in analysis of psychiatric illness. Integrating the scores with the clinical evaluation is a very good idea and would give a better assessment of the psychiatric state. Unfortunately, it was not done because it was not part of the study design and methodology. I added this to the limitations section.</p>
<p>5. One major problem of this work is that it does not evaluate the role of psychoactive drugs. For example, it is not well established if the antidepressants play a role in unmasking endothelial dysfunction or platelet adhesion and it is still a matter of debate the role of these drugs in improving symptoms and prognosis in patients with cardiovascular diseases. It would be interesting to have some data regarding this issue in the study population.</p>
<p>Response: None of the patients were on regular psychoactive drugs. This is indeed a major limitation that I mentioned in the limitation section. However, none of the patients were previously diagnosed with psychiatric illnesses or were on regular long-term psychoactive drugs (it was an exclusion criterion).</p>
<p>Minor comments</p>
<p>1. Please check the references. For example, references 10-15 refer to articles that do not match with the text.</p>
<p>Response:</p>
<p>I rechecked and updated all the references after correction of any error.</p>
<p>2. Try to make the &#8216;Result Section&#8217; more uniform. There are many tables that can be merged into one single table. This solution will help in improving paper&#8217;s structure: more logical and fluid to read and understand.</p>
<p>Response:</p>
<p>I revised the results section and merged some of the tables. I hope it looks better now.</p>
<supplementary-material id="pone.0221918.s001" mimetype="application/vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.wordprocessingml.document" position="float" ns0:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0221918.s001" ns0:type="simple">
<label>Attachment</label>
<caption>
<p>Submitted filename: <named-content content-type="submitted-filename">Response to Reviewers.docx</named-content></p>
</caption>
</supplementary-material>
</body>
</sub-article>
