<sub-article xmlns:ns0="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="aggregated-review-documents" id="pone.0222937.r001" specific-use="decision-letter">
<front-stub>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0222937.r001</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title>Decision Letter 0</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Tizzoni</surname>
<given-names>Michele</given-names>
</name>
<role>Academic Editor</role>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<permissions>
<copyright-year>2019</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>Michele Tizzoni</copyright-holder>
<license ns0:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
<license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" ns0:type="simple">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<related-object document-id="10.1371/journal.pone.0222937" document-id-type="doi" document-type="article" id="rel-obj001" link-type="peer-reviewed-article" />
<custom-meta-group>
<custom-meta>
<meta-name>Submission Version</meta-name>
<meta-value>0</meta-value>
</custom-meta>
</custom-meta-group>
</front-stub>
<body>
<p>
<named-content content-type="letter-date">24 Jul 2019</named-content>
</p>
<p>PONE-D-19-18299</p>
<p>Forecasting the impact of population ageing on tuberculosis incidence</p>
<p>PLOS ONE</p>
<p>Dear Mr. Ku,</p>
<p>Thank you for submitting your manuscript to PLOS ONE. After careful consideration, we feel that it has merit but does not fully meet PLOS ONE&#8217;s publication criteria as it currently stands. Therefore, we invite you to submit a revised version of the manuscript that addresses the points raised during the review process.</p>
<p>We would appreciate receiving your revised manuscript by Sep 07 2019 11:59PM. When you are ready to submit your revision, log on to <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://www.editorialmanager.com/pone/" ns0:type="simple">https://www.editorialmanager.com/pone/</ext-link> and select the 'Submissions Needing Revision' folder to locate your manuscript file.</p>
<p>If you would like to make changes to your financial disclosure, please include your updated statement in your cover letter.</p>
<p>To enhance the reproducibility of your results, we recommend that if applicable you deposit your laboratory protocols in protocols.io, where a protocol can be assigned its own identifier (DOI) such that it can be cited independently in the future. For instructions see: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://journals.plos.org/plosone/s/submission-guidelines#loc-laboratory-protocols" ns0:type="simple">http://journals.plos.org/plosone/s/submission-guidelines#loc-laboratory-protocols</ext-link></p>
<p>Please include the following items when submitting your revised manuscript:</p>
<p><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>A rebuttal letter that responds to each point raised by the academic editor and reviewer(s). This letter should be uploaded as separate file and labeled 'Response to Reviewers'.</p></list-item><list-item><p>A marked-up copy of your manuscript that highlights changes made to the original version. This file should be uploaded as separate file and labeled 'Revised Manuscript with Track Changes'.</p></list-item><list-item><p>An unmarked version of your revised paper without tracked changes. This file should be uploaded as separate file and labeled 'Manuscript'.</p></list-item></list></p>
<p>Please note while forming your response, if your article is accepted, you may have the opportunity to make the peer review history publicly available. The record will include editor decision letters (with reviews) and your responses to reviewer comments. If eligible, we will contact you to opt in or out.</p>
<p>We look forward to receiving your revised manuscript.</p>
<p>Kind regards,</p>
<p>Michele Tizzoni</p>
<p>Academic Editor</p>
<p>PLOS ONE</p>
<p>Journal Requirements:</p>
<p>When submitting your revision, we need you to address these additional requirements.</p>
<p>1) Please ensure that your manuscript meets PLOS ONE's style requirements, including those for file naming. The PLOS ONE style templates can be found at</p>
<p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://www.journals.plos.org/plosone/s/file?id=wjVg/PLOSOne_formatting_sample_main_body.pdf" ns0:type="simple">http://www.journals.plos.org/plosone/s/file?id=wjVg/PLOSOne_formatting_sample_main_body.pdf</ext-link> and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://www.journals.plos.org/plosone/s/file?id=ba62/PLOSOne_formatting_sample_title_authors_affiliations.pdf" ns0:type="simple">http://www.journals.plos.org/plosone/s/file?id=ba62/PLOSOne_formatting_sample_title_authors_affiliations.pdf</ext-link></p>
<p>2) Please add the following to your COI statement: "Peter J. Dodd is also a PLOS ONE handling editor for this collection."</p>
<p>Please confirm that this does not alter your adherence to all PLOS ONE policies on sharing data and materials, by including the following statement: "This does not alter our adherence to&#160; PLOS ONE policies on sharing data and materials.&#8221; (as detailed online in our guide for authors <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://journals.plos.org/plosone/s/competing-interests" ns0:type="simple">http://journals.plos.org/plosone/s/competing-interests</ext-link>). &#160;</p>
<p>If there are restrictions on sharing of data and/or materials, please state these. Please note that we cannot proceed with consideration of your article until this information has been declared.</p>
<p>Please include your updated Competing Interests statement in your cover letter; we will change the online submission form on your behalf.</p>
<p>[Note: HTML markup is below. Please do not edit.]</p>
<p>Reviewers' comments:</p>
<p>Reviewer's Responses to Questions</p>
<p><bold>Comments to the Author</bold></p>
<p>1. Is the manuscript technically sound, and do the data support the conclusions?</p>
<p>The manuscript must describe a technically sound piece of scientific research with data that supports the conclusions. Experiments must have been conducted rigorously, with appropriate controls, replication, and sample sizes. The conclusions must be drawn appropriately based on the data presented. </p>
<p>Reviewer #1: Yes</p>
<p>Reviewer #2: Yes</p>
<p>**********</p>
<p>2. Has the statistical analysis been performed appropriately and rigorously? </p>
<p>Reviewer #1: Yes</p>
<p>Reviewer #2: Yes</p>
<p>**********</p>
<p>3. Have the authors made all data underlying the findings in their manuscript fully available?</p>
<p>The <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://www.plosone.org/static/policies.action#sharing" ns0:type="simple">PLOS Data policy</ext-link> requires authors to make all data underlying the findings described in their manuscript fully available without restriction, with rare exception (please refer to the Data Availability Statement in the manuscript PDF file). The data should be provided as part of the manuscript or its supporting information, or deposited to a public repository. For example, in addition to summary statistics, the data points behind means, medians and variance measures should be available. If there are restrictions on publicly sharing data&#8212;e.g. participant privacy or use of data from a third party&#8212;those must be specified.</p>
<p>Reviewer #1: Yes</p>
<p>Reviewer #2: Yes</p>
<p>**********</p>
<p>4. Is the manuscript presented in an intelligible fashion and written in standard English?</p>
<p>PLOS ONE does not copyedit accepted manuscripts, so the language in submitted articles must be clear, correct, and unambiguous. Any typographical or grammatical errors should be corrected at revision, so please note any specific errors here.</p>
<p>Reviewer #1: Yes</p>
<p>Reviewer #2: Yes</p>
<p>**********</p>
<p>5. Review Comments to the Author</p>
<p>Please use the space provided to explain your answers to the questions above. You may also include additional comments for the author, including concerns about dual publication, research ethics, or publication ethics. (Please upload your review as an attachment if it exceeds 20,000 characters)</p>
<p>Reviewer #1: The authors estimate future trends in the age-specific tuberculosis (TB) incidence in Taiwan until 2035, by applying statistical models (called Lee-Carter models) to time series of incidence data from 2007-2017 and accounting for sex, age, and year-specific effects. The estimated age-specific incidences are then applied to the projected demographic age structure to derive total incidence trends. Overall, the idea is simple and the considerations on demographic changes are important for projections of TB incidence in countries with declining transmission and undergoing a demographic transition, therefore the paper deserves consideration.</p>
<p>My main criticism is that Lee-Carter models were, according to the authors, previously applied in demography and non-communicable diseases epidemiology. However, because the incidence of infectious diseases is critically dependent on the current prevalence of infections, highly non-linear effects in temporal trends take an important role (e.g. threshold effects in the reproductive number) which may make these models highly inaccurate for projecting disease incidence. If transmission dynamics are very far from the epidemic threshold and therefore the large majority of TB cases are due to reactivations, these effects can likely be neglected. Previous studies from US (a low incidence country) showed that only 30% of cases are recently transmitted (Guzzetta et al., JTB 2011), and the large burden of reactivated disease results in a poor performance of TB control strategies applied in the state (Guzzetta et al., JTB 2013). Considering that the average incidence of TB in the US is around 5 per 100k, one might expect a larger contribution of recently transmitted cases in Taiwan, given the average current incidence of about 8 times the US one.</p>
<p>Thus, the authors should:</p>
<p>- provide a demonstration that the method works when parametrizing the model with a subset of data, e.g. the first 5 years of the time series, and projecting the final 5 years against actual observations (this would not be final proof, because short term projections are highly correlated to the current status, but would at least show that the model works in a very easy case);</p>
<p>- discuss the proportion of reactivated vs. recently transmitted TB in Taiwan or countries with similar epidemiology/geographic settings, in light of the above criticism;</p>
<p>- acknowledge the overall limitation of using Lee-Carter models in a context of highly non-linear time trends.</p>
<p>Other comments:</p>
<p>- a minimum description of how Lee-Carter models work mathematically should be provided, at least in the Supplementary Materials; a Coale-Kisker method is mentioned at l. 147, but no specification of why a different method is used for the age class above 85 years old, nor a description of how the method differs from the Lee-Carter one;</p>
<p>- the definition of the likelihood formula used to calculate AIC and BIC should be made explicit;</p>
<p>- do the authors have specific reasons for considering sex-specific incidence separately? Are differences in results significant? Fig. 1 could show estimates for the two sexes in the same graph, in order to allow an easier comparability;</p>
<p>- l. 59: the burden of TB in the mentioned countries cannot be considered "high" from a global point of view. They are perhaps higher than most industrialized countries, but certainly very low compared to the 22 high-burden countries representing 83% of the overall TB burden. Also, "Korean" should be South Korea;</p>
<p>- l. 189: "excepting the reference group aged 0-4": what is the exception? Uncertainties seem large for this age group as well;</p>
<p>- l. 190: "constant trends with calendar years": the trend is linear, perhaps the authors mean that the effect (slope) is constant;</p>
<p>- l. 219, "which is 37% short of the 90%": using percentages as differences may be very confusing, I recommend dropping the 37% figure;</p>
<p>- sentence at lines 246-247 is not clear;</p>
<p>- when mentioning co-morbidities in the discussion (l.328 and 329), HIV should also be mentioned and average prevalences/trends in Taiwan of the two main comorbidities should be provided, to give a general idea on how much neglecting them can impact results;</p>
<p>- I suggest to move the final paragraph of the discussion to somewhere in the beginning: as it is, it has a very anticlimactic effect.</p>
<p>Reviewer #2: This work presents a series of analyses based on statistical modelling to describe the interplay between population's ageing and TB incidence rates -both aggregated and age-specific- in Taiwan. Based on Lee-Carter models, authors analyse age-specific time series between 2005 and 2018 regarding both TB incidence and population structures, and extrapolate to produce forecasts of both aggregated and age-specific TB incidence rates that run until 2035.</p>
<p>The paper is written in a clear and concise manner, and the general research question -what can be expected from the effects of populations' aging on global TB burden levels- is timely and of utmost importance. Statistical modelling methods are sound and described in a (perhaps too much) succinct way. Results -the main observation that contemplating populations' ageing translate into more pessimistic forecasts for TB incidence in Taiwan for the next years- are robust, and in line with previous literature, which is, however, scarce, as authors point out. Conclusions are backed up by the analyses done, and the limitations of the statistical approach are framed in a way that is essentially adequate.</p>
<p>I have therefore no major objections for the publication of this manuscript, and congratulate the authors for their important work. I have, though, the following minor comments/questions, which should be successfully addressed before I can finally recommend the article for publication in this journal:</p>
<p>1. I think that the description of the methods should probably be more exhaustive and explicit, given the specialised character of the statistical modelling framework used in this study, which the interdisciplinary audience of PLoS One might not be necessarily familiar with. Other aspects that might better be explained to a higher level of detail are how the age-specific and aggregated TB incidence rates are built, and rescaled from the demographic and migration forecasts, how does the bootstrap work and how (explicitly) does the uncertainty to TB rates propagates from the different sub-models.</p>
<p>2. At several points of the manuscript, we read the following statements:</p>
<p>line 74: "time series analysis producing age-specific forecasts of the TB incidence has not been published to our knowledge."</p>
<p>line 83: "However, age-specific forecasting and the impact of demographic change have yet to be analysed."</p>
<p>line 281: "Some transmission modelling studies [16,18] have explored issues related to age-structure, but without forecasts or formal assessment of fit."</p>
<p>line 335: "Our result that population ageing will act to slow declines in TB incidence does not seem to have been previously noted."</p>
<p>Which are not totally true. As a matter of fact, reference [18] is a study where authors report the impact of populations' ageing on TB incidence forecasts using transmission modelling. In [18], incidence rate forecasts, both aggregated and age-specific, are indeed reported for different countries, as well as fit evaluations of incidence and mortality rates between 2000 and 2015, upon model calibration. Importantly, the main conclusion of that work -that populations' ageing appears to be directly proportional to an increase in model-based TB burden forecasts with respect to simpler estimations that neglect demographic evolution- is exactly the same of the work here presented for the case of Taiwan, despite the type of models used in that work being radically different from what is presented here. Therefore, the aforementioned statements should be modified, and the findings presented in this work should be put in context to the conceptually similar results reported for other countries in [18].</p>
<p>3. In their analyses, authors assume, as they explicitly acknowledge, the equivalence between TB cases notifications and incidence for the sake of the results they reports. Is not there available data about case notification rates that could be integrated into the models? If not, this possibility should at least be discussed. Even if working with just notification data might be reasonable in the case of contemporary Taiwan; the changes in the population structure that authors forecast in the years to come, along with the eventual added difficulties to detect and register active TB cases in the oldest population strata (which authors also discuss in the introduction) might translate into the growth of a reservoir of undetected/unregistered active TB among eldest age-groups. This plausible scenario might bias the quantitative conclusions of this work, and it should probably be discussed when exposing the limitations of working on notification data alone.</p>
<p>-3. In line 224, we read: "age groups below 65 will be gradually decreasing whereas the above 65 will nearly stay constant from 2018 to 2035"</p>
<p>It took me some time to understand that the age-specific incidence is proportional to the area under the curves, but not to the lines (i.e. that the histograms are stacked), this probably should be stated more clearly. Also, and more important, in figures 3C-3D, four shades are included in the legend, but only three can be appreciated in the figures.</p>
<p>4. The text is very well written, I only found the following couple of typos:</p>
<p>Line 195: "although it cost a higher degree of freedom" should read "it costs"</p>
<p>Line 262: "Table 2. Summary of reductions in TB incidence reductions with and without</p>
<p>263 demographic change" (remove the second "reductions"?)</p>
<p>**********</p>
<p>6. PLOS authors have the option to publish the peer review history of their article (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://journals.plos.org/plosone/s/editorial-and-peer-review-process#loc-peer-review-history" ns0:type="simple">what does this mean?</ext-link>). If published, this will include your full peer review and any attached files.</p>
<p>If you choose &#8220;no&#8221;, your identity will remain anonymous but your review may still be made public.</p>
<p><bold>Do you want your identity to be public for this peer review?</bold> For information about this choice, including consent withdrawal, please see our <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://www.plos.org/privacy-policy" ns0:type="simple">Privacy Policy</ext-link>.</p>
<p>Reviewer #1: No</p>
<p>Reviewer #2: No</p>
<p>[NOTE: If reviewer comments were submitted as an attachment file, they will be attached to this email and accessible via the submission site. Please log into your account, locate the manuscript record, and check for the action link "View Attachments". If this link does not appear, there are no attachment files to be viewed.]</p>
<p>While revising your submission, please upload your figure files to the Preflight Analysis and Conversion Engine (PACE) digital diagnostic tool, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://pacev2.apexcovantage.com/" ns0:type="simple">https://pacev2.apexcovantage.com/</ext-link>. PACE helps ensure that figures meet PLOS requirements. To use PACE, you must first register as a user. Registration is free. Then, login and navigate to the UPLOAD tab, where you will find detailed instructions on how to use the tool. If you encounter any issues or have any questions when using PACE, please email us at <email ns0:type="simple">figures@plos.org</email>. Please note that Supporting Information files do not need this step.</p>
</body>
</sub-article>
