<sub-article xmlns:ns0="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="aggregated-review-documents" id="pone.0221918.r001" specific-use="decision-letter">
<front-stub>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0221918.r001</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title>Decision Letter 0</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Pizzi</surname>
<given-names>Carmine</given-names>
</name>
<role>Academic Editor</role>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<permissions>
<copyright-year>2019</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>Carmine Pizzi</copyright-holder>
<license ns0:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
<license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" ns0:type="simple">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<related-object document-id="10.1371/journal.pone.0221918" document-id-type="doi" document-type="article" id="rel-obj001" link-type="peer-reviewed-article" />
<custom-meta-group>
<custom-meta>
<meta-name>Submission Version</meta-name>
<meta-value>0</meta-value>
</custom-meta>
</custom-meta-group>
</front-stub>
<body>
<p>
<named-content content-type="letter-date">28 Jun 2019</named-content>
</p>
<p>PONE-D-19-14921</p>
<p>Anxiety and Depression Relationship with Coronary Slow Flow</p>
<p>PLOS ONE</p>
<p>Dear Dr. Elamragy,</p>
<p>Thank you for submitting your manuscript to PLOS ONE. After careful consideration, we feel that it has merit but does not fully meet PLOS ONE&#8217;s publication criteria as it currently stands. Therefore, we invite you to submit a revised version of the manuscript that addresses the points raised during the review process.</p>
<p>We would appreciate receiving your revised manuscript by Aug 12 2019 11:59PM. When you are ready to submit your revision, log on to <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://www.editorialmanager.com/pone/" ns0:type="simple">https://www.editorialmanager.com/pone/</ext-link> and select the 'Submissions Needing Revision' folder to locate your manuscript file.</p>
<p>If you would like to make changes to your financial disclosure, please include your updated statement in your cover letter.</p>
<p>To enhance the reproducibility of your results, we recommend that if applicable you deposit your laboratory protocols in protocols.io, where a protocol can be assigned its own identifier (DOI) such that it can be cited independently in the future. For instructions see: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://journals.plos.org/plosone/s/submission-guidelines#loc-laboratory-protocols" ns0:type="simple">http://journals.plos.org/plosone/s/submission-guidelines#loc-laboratory-protocols</ext-link></p>
<p>Please include the following items when submitting your revised manuscript:</p>
<p><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>A rebuttal letter that responds to each point raised by the academic editor and reviewer(s). This letter should be uploaded as separate file and labeled 'Response to Reviewers'.</p></list-item><list-item><p>A marked-up copy of your manuscript that highlights changes made to the original version. This file should be uploaded as separate file and labeled 'Revised Manuscript with Track Changes'.</p></list-item><list-item><p>An unmarked version of your revised paper without tracked changes. This file should be uploaded as separate file and labeled 'Manuscript'.</p></list-item></list></p>
<p>Please note while forming your response, if your article is accepted, you may have the opportunity to make the peer review history publicly available. The record will include editor decision letters (with reviews) and your responses to reviewer comments. If eligible, we will contact you to opt in or out.</p>
<p>We look forward to receiving your revised manuscript.</p>
<p>Kind regards,</p>
<p>Carmine Pizzi</p>
<p>Academic Editor</p>
<p>PLOS ONE</p>
<p>Journal Requirements:</p>
<p>1. When submitting your revision, we need you to address these additional requirements.</p>
<p>Please ensure that your manuscript meets PLOS ONE's style requirements, including those for file naming. The PLOS ONE style templates can be found at</p>
<p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://www.journals.plos.org/plosone/s/file?id=wjVg/PLOSOne_formatting_sample_main_body.pdf" ns0:type="simple">http://www.journals.plos.org/plosone/s/file?id=wjVg/PLOSOne_formatting_sample_main_body.pdf</ext-link> and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://www.journals.plos.org/plosone/s/file?id=ba62/PLOSOne_formatting_sample_title_authors_affiliations.pdf" ns0:type="simple">http://www.journals.plos.org/plosone/s/file?id=ba62/PLOSOne_formatting_sample_title_authors_affiliations.pdf</ext-link></p>
<p>2. Thank you for including your ethics statement; "All the procedures were in accordance with the standards of the Institute&#8217;s ethical committee and with the Helsinki Declaration of 1975, as revised in 2000. Oral consent was taken from the subjects participated in the psychiatric questionnaires."</p>
<p>We note that you include the full name of your Institutional Review Board on the online submission form; "Cairo University Ethics committee approved the study.</p>
<p>Oral consent was obtained."</p>
<p>Please amend your current ethics statement to include the full name of the ethics committee/institutional review board(s) that approved your specific study and also ensure that you have specified the committee approved the study.</p>
<p>Also, please provide additional details regarding participant consent and ensure that you have specified how the verbal or oral consent was documented and witnessed. If the verbal consent was approved by the ethics committee, please include this information.</p>
<p>Once you have amended this/these statement(s) in the Methods section of the manuscript, please add the same text to the &#8220;Ethics Statement&#8221; field of the submission form (via &#8220;Edit Submission&#8221;).</p>
<p>For additional information about PLOS ONE ethical requirements for human subjects research, please refer to <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://journals.plos.org/plosone/s/submission-guidelines#loc-human-subjects-research" ns0:type="simple">http://journals.plos.org/plosone/s/submission-guidelines#loc-human-subjects-research</ext-link>.</p>
<p>Reviewer #1: In this study, the authors aimed to assess the possible relation of psychiatric disorders, such as depression and anxiety status, with the coronary flow pattern in patients with angiographically normal coronary arteries. The TIMI frame count (TFC) has been used for definition of coronary slow flow (CSF) phenomenon and psychiatric interviews were performed to assess severity of anxiety and depression using the BAI and BDI scales. The results show that patients with CSF had significantly higher anxiety and depression scores, irrespective of gender. The authors also found a strong correlation between the BAI score and CSF severity.</p>
<p>We thank the authors for this interesting study. The pathophysiologic hypothesis is intriguing and the study design is fitting. However, this reviewer has several concerns:</p>
<p>Major comments</p>
<p>- The authors should give detailed information about the clinical findings of CSF patients and control patients. In particular, the symptomatic burden, including duration of the angina pattern, as well as frequency and severity of angina attacks should be reported and compared.</p>
<p>- The use of beta-blockers, vasodilators or other anti-ischemic drugs might have affected the detection of CSF. The authors should at least comment this point as a limitation of the study.</p>
<p>- If possible, the authors should report the educational and socioeconomic status of patients of the 2 groups, as possible factors influencing depression or anxiety status.</p>
<p>Minor comments</p>
<p>- The analysis of this study doesn&#8217;t account for the use of psychiatric drugs or other medication. Although none of the antidepressant drugs is known to cause CSF, as the authors say in the text, the answers of patients to the interviews might have been influenced by their use.</p>
<p>- Have the authors tried to exclude patients with possible &#8220;secondary form&#8221; of CSF (i.e. coronary artery ectasia, coronary artery spasm, pulmonary arterial hypertension, etc...)?</p>
<p>- The depression and anxiety rating scales (BAI and BDI), used to assess the severity of the psychiatric disorder, are two self-report scales. Thus, they depend on patients&#8217; reliability, time and context of interview administration.</p>
<p>Reviewer #2: The study is focused on a large-scale problem that is the increasing prevalence of patients with both coronary artery disease (CAD) and depression or anxiety, that, to date, are probably not well diagnosed and treated for the underlying psychological conditions despite growing evidences that these conditions play an important role in provoking and modifying the prognosis in cardiovascular diseases. The study, taking into account the intrinsic limitations of a cross sectional study, shows significant and independent association between depression and coronary slow flow (CSF) as well as with male gender or triglyceride serum levels (association already demonstrated by other authors) and significant but dependent association with anxiety and other classical cardiovascular risk factors. The paper, sustaining the role of psychological conditions together with classical cardiovascular risk factors in determining CSF, wants to stress the importance of an accurate global (physical and psychological) assessment of the patient. An interesting point of the paper is the exclusion of patients with a coronary artery stenosis &gt; 20%, in fact even mild-to-moderate stenosis could affect CSF and could have represented a selection bias.</p>
<p>However, this manuscript had some issues that deserve clarifications.</p>
<p>Major comments</p>
<p>1. The study population is composed by consecutive patients who underwent coronary angiography due to &#8216;objective evidence of ischemia&#8217;. What do the Authors mean with that sentence? It is necessary to provide a clear definition of ischemia and a standardized diagnosis.</p>
<p>2. Diabetes, one of the most important cardiovascular risk factors and strongly related to endothelial dysfunction, seems not to be associated with CSF. The authors should be discussing this point</p>
<p>3. Another point is the definition of the ex-smoker status. The Authors have provided an arbitrary definition of former smoker (only the patients who have stopped &gt; 2 years), not shared by the principal National Health Systems. This gross classification of patients probably leads to some bias in defining the relationship between smoking and CSF because the toxic substances contained in cigarettes act in a short/medium period of time in causing endothelial dysfunction and inflammation.</p>
<p>4. It is well established that depression and anxiety are twice as high in females than in males, in this study the mean BDI and BAI scores are lower in women. Maybe these scores should be integrated with a clinical evaluation of symptoms by a psychiatrist to avoid the subjective influence of the patients and on the physician in interpreting the answers. It would also be useful to provide the complete data of the prevalence and of the degree of anxiety and depression adjusted for gender.</p>
<p>5. One major problem of this work is that it does not evaluate the role of psychoactive drugs. For example, it is not well established if the antidepressants play a role in unmasking endothelial dysfunction or platelet adhesion and it is still a matter of debate the role of these drugs in improving symptoms and prognosis in patients with cardiovascular diseases. It would be interesting to have some data regarding this issue in the study population.</p>
<p>Minor comments</p>
<p>1. Please check the references. For example, references 10-15 refer to articles that do not match with the text.</p>
<p>2. Try to make the &#8216;Result Section&#8217; more uniform. There are many tables that can be merged into one single table. This solution will help in improving paper&#8217;s structure: more logical and fluid to read and understand.</p>
</body>
</sub-article>
