<sub-article article-type="author-comment" id="pone.0221778.r006">
<front-stub>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0221778.r006</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title>Author response to Decision Letter 2</article-title>
</title-group>
<related-object document-id="10.1371/journal.pone.0221778" document-id-type="doi" document-type="peer-reviewed-article" id="rel-obj006" link-type="rebutted-decision-letter" object-id="10.1371/journal.pone.0221778.r005" object-id-type="doi" object-type="decision-letter" />
<custom-meta-group>
<custom-meta>
<meta-name>Submission Version</meta-name>
<meta-value>3</meta-value>
</custom-meta>
</custom-meta-group>
</front-stub>
<body>
<p>
<named-content content-type="author-response-date">13 Aug 2019</named-content>
</p>
<p>Dear Editor,</p>
<p>We want to thank you and the reviewers for the constructive criticism and suggestions that have helped us to improve our manuscript. We have now addressed the comments raised, and we trust you will find our manuscript acceptable for publication. </p>
<p>Below we provide a point-by-point response to the comments.</p>
<p>Best Regards</p>
<p>Anthony</p>
<p>On behalf of all authors. </p>
<p>Additional Editor Comments (if provided): Thanks for making significant improvements to this manuscript. There are minor comments to address before it can be accepted for publication. Thanks</p>
<p>Response: We thank the Editor for providing us with constructive feedback that has helped us to improve our manuscript.</p>
<p>Reviewer #1: Many thanks to the authors for the revisions made. However, this topic which is based on the old data set (Nigeria DHS 2013) has been covered extensively in some recently published articles, therefore, adds no new information to what is already known on this topic.</p>
<p>Response: We believe our paper addresses an important topic, and our work is unique by focusing on inequality in access to caesarean section in Nigeria, a country that contributes 19% of global maternal deaths. While the 2013 NDHS may appear to the old in the context of the 2018 NDHS data, the fact is that the 2013 data is still the most recent publicly available. As indicated in our earlier response, when the 2018 data set becomes available, we hope to build on this work to undertake trend analysis on the caesarean section utilization. </p>
<p>Reviewer #2: This paper has been greatly improved. My only additional comment is that I feel the paragraph in the discussion starting "anecdotal evidence suggests..." where the authors go on to discuss longer hospital stays following caesarean section should have some reference for the assertions made regarding hospital stay. Otherwise, the discussion is much richer and of wider interest as a result.</p>
<p>Response: We appreciate the reviewer&#8217;s comments that have enabled us to revise our discussion section significantly. We have now referenced the paragraph as suggested.</p>
</body>
</sub-article>
