<sub-article xmlns:ns0="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="aggregated-review-documents" id="pcbi.1007383.r003" specific-use="decision-letter">
<front-stub>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1007383.r003</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title>Decision Letter 1</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Ben-Tal</surname>
<given-names>Nir</given-names>
</name>
<role>Deputy Editor</role>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Wei</surname>
<given-names>Guanghong</given-names>
</name>
<role>Associate Editor</role>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<permissions>
<copyright-year>2019</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>Ben-Tal, Wei</copyright-holder>
<license ns0:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
<license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" ns0:type="simple">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<related-object document-id="10.1371/journal.pcbi.1007383" document-id-type="doi" document-type="article" id="rel-obj003" link-type="peer-reviewed-article" />
<custom-meta-group>
<custom-meta>
<meta-name>Submission Version</meta-name>
<meta-value>1</meta-value>
</custom-meta>
</custom-meta-group>
</front-stub>
<body>
<p>
<named-content content-type="letter-date">29 Aug 2019</named-content>
</p>
<p>[EXSCINDED]</p>
<p>Dear Dr Czub,</p>
<p>Thank you very much for submitting your manuscript, 'Why do G-quadruplexes dimerize through the 5&#8217;-ends? Driving forces for G4 DNA dimerization examined in atomic detail.', to PLOS Computational Biology. As with all papers submitted to the journal, yours was fully evaluated by the PLOS Computational Biology editorial team, and in this case, by independent peer reviewers. The reviewers appreciated the attention to an important topic but identified some aspects of the manuscript that should be improved.</p>
<p>We would therefore like to ask you to modify the manuscript according to the review recommendations before we can consider your manuscript for acceptance. Your revisions should address the specific points made by each reviewer and we encourage you to respond to particular issues Please note while forming your response, if your article is accepted, you may have the opportunity to make the peer review history publicly available. The record will include editor decision letters (with reviews) and your responses to reviewer comments. If eligible, we will contact you to opt in or out.raised.</p>
<p>In addition, when you are ready to resubmit, please be prepared to provide the following:</p>
<p>(1) A detailed list of your responses to the review comments and the changes you have made in the manuscript. We require a file of this nature before your manuscript is passed back to the editors.</p>
<p>(2) A copy of your manuscript with the changes highlighted (encouraged). We encourage authors, if possible to show clearly where changes have been made to their manuscript e.g. by highlighting text.</p>
<p>(3) A striking still image to accompany your article (optional). If the image is judged to be suitable by the editors, it may be featured on our website and might be chosen as the issue image for that month. These square, high-quality images should be accompanied by a short caption. Please note as well that there should be no copyright restrictions on the use of the image, so that it can be published under the Open-Access license and be subject only to appropriate attribution.</p>
<p>Before you resubmit your manuscript, please consult our Submission Checklist to ensure your manuscript is formatted correctly for PLOS Computational Biology: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://www.ploscompbiol.org/static/checklist.action" ns0:type="simple">http://www.ploscompbiol.org/static/checklist.action</ext-link>. Some key points to remember are:</p>
<p>- Figures uploaded separately as TIFF or EPS files (if you wish, your figures may remain in your main manuscript file in addition).</p>
<p>- Supporting Information uploaded as separate files, titled 'Dataset', 'Figure', 'Table', 'Text', 'Protocol', 'Audio', or 'Video'.</p>
<p>- Funding information in the 'Financial Disclosure' box in the online system.</p>
<p>While revising your submission, please upload your figure files to the Preflight Analysis and Conversion Engine (PACE) digital diagnostic tool, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://pacev2.apexcovantage.com" ns0:type="simple">https://pacev2.apexcovantage.com</ext-link> &#160;PACE helps ensure that figures meet PLOS requirements. To use PACE, you must first register as a user. Then, login and navigate to the UPLOAD tab, where you will find detailed instructions on how to use the tool. If you encounter any issues or have any questions when using PACE, please email us at <email ns0:type="simple">figures@plos.org</email>.</p>
<p>We hope to receive your revised manuscript within the next 30 days. If you anticipate any delay in its return, we ask that you let us know the expected resubmission date by email at <email ns0:type="simple">ploscompbiol@plos.org</email>.</p>
<p>If you have any questions or concerns while you make these revisions, please let us know.</p>
<p>Sincerely,</p>
<p>Guanghong Wei</p>
<p>Associate Editor</p>
<p>PLOS Computational Biology</p>
<p>Nir Ben-Tal</p>
<p>Deputy Editor</p>
<p>PLOS Computational Biology</p>
<p>A link appears below if there are any accompanying review attachments. If you believe any reviews to be missing, please contact <email ns0:type="simple">ploscompbiol@plos.org</email> immediately:</p>
<p>[LINK]</p>
<p>Reviewer's Responses to Questions</p>
<p><bold>Comments to the Authors:</bold></p>
<p><bold>Please note here if the review is uploaded as an attachment.</bold></p>
<p>Reviewer #1: The authors have answered all my questions, I suggest the acceptance of the manuscript for publication.</p>
<p>Reviewer #2: none</p>
<p>Reviewer #3: Please see the attached review.</p>
<p>**********</p>
<p><bold>Have all data underlying the figures and results presented in the manuscript been provided?</bold></p>
<p>Large-scale datasets should be made available via a public repository as described in the <italic>PLOS Computational Biology</italic> <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://journals.plos.org/ploscompbiol/s/data-availability" ns0:type="simple">data availability policy</ext-link>, and numerical data that underlies graphs or summary statistics should be provided in spreadsheet form as supporting information.</p>
<p>Reviewer #1: Yes</p>
<p>Reviewer #2: Yes</p>
<p>Reviewer #3: Yes</p>
<p>**********</p>
<p>PLOS authors have the option to publish the peer review history of their article (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://journals.plos.org/ploscompbiol/s/editorial-and-peer-review-process#loc-peer-review-history" ns0:type="simple">what does this mean?</ext-link>). If published, this will include your full peer review and any attached files.</p>
<p>If you choose &#8220;no&#8221;, your identity will remain anonymous but your review may still be made public.</p>
<p><bold>Do you want your identity to be public for this peer review?</bold> For information about this choice, including consent withdrawal, please see our <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://www.plos.org/privacy-policy" ns0:type="simple">Privacy Policy</ext-link>.</p>
<p>Reviewer #1: No</p>
<p>Reviewer #2: No</p>
<p>Reviewer #3: Yes: Nanjie Deng</p>
<supplementary-material id="pcbi.1007383.s024" mimetype="application/pdf" position="float" ns0:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1007383.s024" ns0:type="simple">
<label>Attachment</label>
<caption>
<p>Submitted filename: <named-content content-type="submitted-filename">Review-G4-dimerization-PLOS-COMPBIOL-08-2019-revised.pdf</named-content></p>
</caption>
</supplementary-material>
</body>
</sub-article>
