<sub-article xmlns:ns0="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="aggregated-review-documents" id="pone.0218300.r001" specific-use="decision-letter">
<front-stub>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0218300.r001</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title>Decision Letter 0</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Pereira</surname>
<given-names>In&#234;s A. Cardoso</given-names>
</name>
<role>Academic Editor</role>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<permissions>
<copyright-year>2019</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>In&#234;s A. Cardoso Pereira</copyright-holder>
<license ns0:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
<license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" ns0:type="simple">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<related-object document-id="10.1371/journal.pone.0218300" document-id-type="doi" document-type="article" id="rel-obj001" link-type="peer-reviewed-article" />
<custom-meta-group>
<custom-meta>
<meta-name>Submission Version</meta-name>
<meta-value>0</meta-value>
</custom-meta>
</custom-meta-group>
</front-stub>
<body>
<p>
<named-content content-type="letter-date">26 Jun 2019</named-content>
</p>
<p>PONE-D-19-15019</p>
<p>The Dps4 from Nostoc punctiforme ATCC 29133 is a member of His-type FOC containing Dps protein class that can be broadly found among cyanobacteria</p>
<p>PLOS ONE</p>
<p>Dear Dr. Stensj&#246;,</p>
<p>Thank you for submitting your manuscript to PLOS ONE. After careful consideration, we feel that it has merit but does not fully meet PLOS ONE&#8217;s publication criteria as it currently stands. Therefore, we invite you to submit a revised version of the manuscript that addresses the points raised during the review process.</p>
<p>Both reviewers raise a number of points regarding the interpretation of the kinetic and structural data, which need to be fully addressed. If you feel that you can change the manuscript in order to address these points, we would be happy to receive a revised version.</p>
<p>We would appreciate receiving your revised manuscript by Aug 10 2019 11:59PM. When you are ready to submit your revision, log on to <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://www.editorialmanager.com/pone/" ns0:type="simple">https://www.editorialmanager.com/pone/</ext-link> and select the 'Submissions Needing Revision' folder to locate your manuscript file.</p>
<p>If you would like to make changes to your financial disclosure, please include your updated statement in your cover letter.</p>
<p>To enhance the reproducibility of your results, we recommend that if applicable you deposit your laboratory protocols in protocols.io, where a protocol can be assigned its own identifier (DOI) such that it can be cited independently in the future. For instructions see: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://journals.plos.org/plosone/s/submission-guidelines#loc-laboratory-protocols" ns0:type="simple">http://journals.plos.org/plosone/s/submission-guidelines#loc-laboratory-protocols</ext-link></p>
<p>Please include the following items when submitting your revised manuscript:</p>
<p><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>A rebuttal letter that responds to each point raised by the academic editor and reviewer(s). This letter should be uploaded as separate file and labeled 'Response to Reviewers'.</p></list-item><list-item><p>A marked-up copy of your manuscript that highlights changes made to the original version. This file should be uploaded as separate file and labeled 'Revised Manuscript with Track Changes'.</p></list-item><list-item><p>An unmarked version of your revised paper without tracked changes. This file should be uploaded as separate file and labeled 'Manuscript'.</p></list-item></list></p>
<p>Please note while forming your response, if your article is accepted, you may have the opportunity to make the peer review history publicly available. The record will include editor decision letters (with reviews) and your responses to reviewer comments. If eligible, we will contact you to opt in or out.</p>
<p>We look forward to receiving your revised manuscript.</p>
<p>Kind regards,</p>
<p>In&#234;s A. Cardoso Pereira, Ph.D.</p>
<p>Academic Editor</p>
<p>PLOS ONE</p>
<p>Journal Requirements:</p>
<p>1. When submitting your revision, we need you to address these additional requirements.</p>
<p>Please ensure that your manuscript meets PLOS ONE's style requirements, including those for file naming. The PLOS ONE style templates can be found at</p>
<p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://www.journals.plos.org/plosone/s/file?id=wjVg/PLOSOne_formatting_sample_main_body.pdf" ns0:type="simple">http://www.journals.plos.org/plosone/s/file?id=wjVg/PLOSOne_formatting_sample_main_body.pdf</ext-link> and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://www.journals.plos.org/plosone/s/file?id=ba62/PLOSOne_formatting_sample_title_authors_affiliations.pdf" ns0:type="simple">http://www.journals.plos.org/plosone/s/file?id=ba62/PLOSOne_formatting_sample_title_authors_affiliations.pdf</ext-link></p>
<p>[Note: HTML markup is below. Please do not edit.]</p>
<p>Reviewers' comments:</p>
<p>Reviewer's Responses to Questions</p>
<p><bold>Comments to the Author</bold></p>
<p>1. Is the manuscript technically sound, and do the data support the conclusions?</p>
<p>The manuscript must describe a technically sound piece of scientific research with data that supports the conclusions. Experiments must have been conducted rigorously, with appropriate controls, replication, and sample sizes. The conclusions must be drawn appropriately based on the data presented. </p>
<p>Reviewer #1: Partly</p>
<p>Reviewer #2: Yes</p>
<p>**********</p>
<p>2. Has the statistical analysis been performed appropriately and rigorously? </p>
<p>Reviewer #1: No</p>
<p>Reviewer #2: N/A</p>
<p>**********</p>
<p>3. Have the authors made all data underlying the findings in their manuscript fully available?</p>
<p>The <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://www.plosone.org/static/policies.action#sharing" ns0:type="simple">PLOS Data policy</ext-link> requires authors to make all data underlying the findings described in their manuscript fully available without restriction, with rare exception (please refer to the Data Availability Statement in the manuscript PDF file). The data should be provided as part of the manuscript or its supporting information, or deposited to a public repository. For example, in addition to summary statistics, the data points behind means, medians and variance measures should be available. If there are restrictions on publicly sharing data&#8212;e.g. participant privacy or use of data from a third party&#8212;those must be specified.</p>
<p>Reviewer #1: Yes</p>
<p>Reviewer #2: Yes</p>
<p>**********</p>
<p>4. Is the manuscript presented in an intelligible fashion and written in standard English?</p>
<p>PLOS ONE does not copyedit accepted manuscripts, so the language in submitted articles must be clear, correct, and unambiguous. Any typographical or grammatical errors should be corrected at revision, so please note any specific errors here.</p>
<p>Reviewer #1: Yes</p>
<p>Reviewer #2: Yes</p>
<p>**********</p>
<p>5. Review Comments to the Author</p>
<p>Please use the space provided to explain your answers to the questions above. You may also include additional comments for the author, including concerns about dual publication, research ethics, or publication ethics. (Please upload your review as an attachment if it exceeds 20,000 characters)</p>
<p>Reviewer #1: The current manuscript focused on the structural and kinetic studies of Dps4 from a cyanobacteria. Interestingly Nostoc punctiforme, the phototrophic and filamentous cyanobacterium encodes for five different Dps, but the specific function of each Dps it is not fully yet stablished. Thus, the work present in the current manuscript, contribute to elucidate the function of the NpDps4. Nevertheless, there are a several modifications that have to be included in the manuscript, mainly regarding the kinetic analysis of the data, which was not properly performed; and a more detailed crystal structure analysis.</p>
<p>The authors should be more carefully with the scientific language, please rephrase the following sentences.</p>
<p>Page 6, line 147 - &#8220;meet thus creating a pore.&#8221; - The pore is not created, it is formed, and word &#8220;meet&#8221; should be avoided. Please rephrase.</p>
<p>Page 7, line 158 - &#8220;of three monomers meet&#8221;. Again the word &#8220;meet&#8221; should be avoided.</p>
<p>Comments:</p>
<p>Page 5-9, line 123-204 &#8211;Although the overall fold is the same in the three structures presented (5HJF, 5HJH, 5I4J), the authors should present the rmsd between the different structures.</p>
<p>Besides the difference in the ferroxidase center that the authors comment, is there any structural difference in the crystal structures induced by the presence of the different metals, for instance in the 3-fold pores, or in other part of the structure.</p>
<p>Page 6 and 7, line 147-153- The authors described the ferritin-like pore of the NpDps4, but they do not mentioned if there is any water or metal located in this pore.</p>
<p>Page 7, line 158-164 &#8211; The authors describe the Dps-like pore in the NpDps4, and they mention that it contains a &#8220;small cap-like structure on the outside of the protein&#8221;. However it is not clear if the pore is blocked by any residue from the C-terminal tails that are at the top of the pore, and if the nature of these residues is negative or positive. A more detailed description should be included.</p>
<p>Page 8, line 188, 195- The authors mentioned that the distance between Fe in site A and Fe in site B is 3.5 &#197;, and that there is one water molecule coordinating both irons. Is this a bridging molecule, if so it is not clear how can be at a distance of 2.2 and 2.3 &#197; from site A and B respectively, since the distance between the two irons is 3.5 &#197;. This part should be clarified.</p>
<p>Page 7-9, lines 173-205 &#8211; In order to understand if the Fe in site B is more loosely coordinated, and if the distances between the metals and the coordinating residues are similar in the structure with Fe or Zn, a Table with the coordination distances between the different coordinating residues and the metal ions for the different structures should be included. The authors should compare the distances between the coordinating residues and Fe in site A, and those for Fe in site B.</p>
<p>Page 8, lines 198-204; Page 10, lines 252-269 &#8211; The authors have determined the crystal structure of NpDps4 in which the crystals were independently soaked with a solution of FeSO4 or ZnSO4. The structures showed that the iron was bound in two position, site A and B, while in the case of the structure with zinc, the metal was bound to a similar structural position as the Fe in site A. Moreover, by kinetic studies the authors showed that the zinc inhibits the iron oxidation rates. In order to understand if the &#8220;di-iron&#8221; center formed upon iron addition is not maintained in the presence of zinc, or if it is form a mixed di-center with Zn and Fe, it would be interesting to determine the crystal structure, in which the crystals were first soaked with an iron solution followed by a zinc solution.</p>
<p>Page 10, 226-240 &#8211; Iron oxidation assays. The authors mentioned the increase of absorbance at 310 nm which is related with the oxidation of iron by the protein. Nevertheless, the authors should present a proper analysis of the data, the initial rate should be determined for each assay, with the corresponding error bar.</p>
<p>Moreover, the authors only present one condition tested, in which they have used 0.5 uM with 24uM Fe, corresponding to a ratio of 48 Fe/dodecamer and 4Fe/monomer. A proper kinetic study should be included, using different Fe/dodecamer from 12 to the maximum capacity per dodecamer. In addition, for each assay the iron oxidation rates have to be determined, which is not presented in the current version of the manuscript. As an example &#8220;Abs310nm 0.014 after 2 min&#8221; (page 10, line 230) is not a rate.</p>
<p>Page 10, lines 241-251 &#8211; The authors also address the iron oxidation by using hydrogen peroxide. Although they do not see any difference with and without the protein, in order to account only for the contribution of hydrogen peroxide, have the authors performed the assays for iron oxidation by hydrogen peroxide under anaerobic conditions. As mentioned before, the data should be presented with the error bars, and they have to present iron oxidation rates.</p>
<p>Page 11, lines 258-260; Fig 6A- From Fig 6A and from the corresponding legend it is clear that the protein is able to oxidize the iron (black line) but if zinc was added before, the iron oxidation is inhibited. Nevertheless, the corresponding phrase, in the text (page 11, lines 258-260) is not clear, please rephrase it.</p>
<p>Page 15-17, lines 368-415- The authors present an analysis of different amino acid sequences of Dps, and they proposed a His-type FOC. The others NpDps instead of His63 present an aspartate residues, moreover as it states in the Introduction part (page 4, lines 91-92) the NpDps1-3 catalyzes the iron oxidation with hydrogen peroxide and not with oxygen, while NpDps4 is the other way around. So, it would be interesting if the authors could comment on the oxidation rates for the other NpDps or even for &#8220;canonical&#8221; Dps that contain a aspartate residue and their specificity of hydrogen peroxide vs oxygen and histidine vs aspartate.</p>
<p>Page 19, line 481 &#8211; Please define DrDps1, since it is the first time it is mentioned in the text.</p>
<p>Page 20, lines 514-515 &#8211; The authors have wrote that &#8220;ferritins have be found to act as zinc detoxification agents delivering a certain stress resistance&#8221;- do the authors have any evidence that the NpDps4 stores Zn or was only tested for the inhibition of the iron oxidation.</p>
<p>Figure 2 &#8211; The different subunits should be in different colours, similar to the one presented in Figure 4. In addition, the corresponding residues should use the same colour as the subunit, maintaining the red for the oxygen and blue for nitrogen.</p>
<p>Figure 3 &#8211; For clarity, figure 3A should be zoom-in and the residues should be in the same colour as the corresponding subunit, maintaining the red for the oxygen and blue for nitrogen.</p>
<p>Figure 7 &#8211; From the figure it was not clear the representation of &#8220;lengths of &#945;-helices refer to the crystal structure of NpDps4 and are indicated by black bars and red letters.&#8221; In the figure legend the explanation for the different His-type FOC should be induced, namely the definition of Nx, SynPro, LPP-B, AcTh, Osc, SPM.</p>
<p>Figure 7 &#8211; Since N. punctiforme contains five different Dps, is there any reason why NpDps5 was not included in the Multiple sequence alignment presented in Fig. 7. Moreover, for clarity for the reader, the figure should include the name of the organism instead of the protein code. The figure legend should have the information for each protein code and the corresponding name of the organism, as it is currently.</p>
<p>Table 1 &#8211; The authors should comment on why they did not process the data of Metal-free NpDps4 structure to a higher resolution based on their values of I/&#963;(I).</p>
<p>To be consistent the authors should present the values for highest resolution shell for the Rwork and Rfree.</p>
<p>Reviewer #2: The authors Howe et al., in their work about the fourth Dps from Nostoc punctiforme has tried to unravel its role in the organism and propose a new class of Dps, having His-type Ferroxidation centres unique to cyanobacteria. They also claim the NpDps4 uses O2 over H2O2 to oxidise iron. Also, crystal structures of apo, iron bound and zinc bound Dps has been analysed and they conclude by spectroscopic assays that binding of Zinc to the FOC inhibits ferroxidation.</p>
<p>While it&#8217;s interesting to note the presence of a new type of ferroxidation site in cyanobacterial Dps, the authors could not make convincing theories about its possible biological significance. There are also some major points that the authors need to address regarding their other findings to make their claims credible.</p>
<p>The following points are raised in the order they occur in the text:</p>
<p>Line 142</p>
<p>The residues Phe95, Leu98 and Ala99 are mentioned in the text but not marked in the figure.</p>
<p>Line 157</p>
<p>&#8230; acid of the trio &#8230;</p>
<p>Lines 168-169</p>
<p>&#8220;each symmetrical amino acid of the trio is indicated only once&#8221;, but Figure 3B shows amino acids from all three monomers related by three-fold.</p>
<p>Line 174</p>
<p>How does the authors know SOKALAN66 is a metal chelating agent?</p>
<p>Line 176</p>
<p>Is there any experimental evidence whether it is really Zinc or Iron bound in the crystal structure like anomalous X-ray scattering or even a simple detection of Zinc ions on a gel?</p>
<p>Line 177</p>
<p>It would be more desirable to show electron density maps to show the fitting of ion atoms in Figure 4</p>
<p>Line 189</p>
<p>Since the FOC is formed not only of residues from two monomers related by two-fold, but also from a third monomer it is also unusual for Dps proteins.</p>
<p>Lines 213-214</p>
<p>The sentence can be phrased better</p>
<p>Line 220</p>
<p>What is the rationale of using 24 mM Fe2+ and 0.5 mM NpDps?</p>
<p>Lines 241-250</p>
<p>If the ferroxidation experiments using H2O2 were done under aerobic conditions, how does the authors discount for the effect of O2 on oxidation and especially as they&#8217;re comparing the ferroxidation properties between O2 and H2O2. It is strange that the graph doesn&#8217;t show any increase in ferroxidation under aerobic conditions, as in the above paragraph they show that oxygen can be used for ferroxidation by NpDps4.</p>
<p>Lines 262-263</p>
<p>Does the inhibition of ferroxidation by Zinc related to it causing protein aggregation as it is mentioned in line 263 that Zinc negatively impacts protein solubility?</p>
<p>Lines 282-288</p>
<p>Addition of Zinc indicated by arrow is misleading in Figure 6B as the black graph shows the reaction without Zn addition. In line 287 the authors mean figure 6B and not 6A?</p>
<p>Line 302</p>
<p>Figure 7 is illegible, and nothing can be inferred from it. So, the authors most important claim that the his-type FOC is conserved across cyanobacteria cannot be ascertained at all from the figure.</p>
<p>Line 392</p>
<p>It&#8217;s not clear to the reader what is &#8216;the specific function&#8217; in cyanobacteria.</p>
<p>Line 470</p>
<p>Recent developments on the dps-like interface and its role as an evolutionary switch between dps and ferritins has to be mentioned when discussing the role of this interface.</p>
<p>Lines 620-621</p>
<p>During the ferroxidation experiment the authors talk of mixing the reaction by resuspension. How do they account for the reaction time that has elapsed during this process? Wherever possible cuvettes with stirrers should be used as these reaction rates can be pretty fast, especially the rates with H2O2.</p>
<p>Line 626</p>
<p>Ideally kinetic data should be evaluated from 3-4 experiments and at least two different protein preparations.</p>
<p>**********</p>
<p>6. PLOS authors have the option to publish the peer review history of their article (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://journals.plos.org/plosone/s/editorial-and-peer-review-process#loc-peer-review-history" ns0:type="simple">what does this mean?</ext-link>). If published, this will include your full peer review and any attached files.</p>
<p>If you choose &#8220;no&#8221;, your identity will remain anonymous but your review may still be made public.</p>
<p><bold>Do you want your identity to be public for this peer review?</bold> For information about this choice, including consent withdrawal, please see our <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://www.plos.org/privacy-policy" ns0:type="simple">Privacy Policy</ext-link>.</p>
<p>Reviewer #1: No</p>
<p>Reviewer #2: No</p>
<p>[NOTE: If reviewer comments were submitted as an attachment file, they will be attached to this email and accessible via the submission site. Please log into your account, locate the manuscript record, and check for the action link "View Attachments". If this link does not appear, there are no attachment files to be viewed.]</p>
<p>While revising your submission, please upload your figure files to the Preflight Analysis and Conversion Engine (PACE) digital diagnostic tool, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://pacev2.apexcovantage.com/" ns0:type="simple">https://pacev2.apexcovantage.com/</ext-link>. PACE helps ensure that figures meet PLOS requirements. To use PACE, you must first register as a user. Registration is free. Then, login and navigate to the UPLOAD tab, where you will find detailed instructions on how to use the tool. If you encounter any issues or have any questions when using PACE, please email us at <email ns0:type="simple">figures@plos.org</email>. Please note that Supporting Information files do not need this step.</p>
</body>
</sub-article>
