<sub-article xmlns:ns0="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="aggregated-review-documents" id="pone.0222979.r001" specific-use="decision-letter">
<front-stub>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0222979.r001</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title>Decision Letter 0</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Oury</surname>
<given-names>C&#233;cile</given-names>
</name>
<role>Academic Editor</role>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<permissions>
<copyright-year>2019</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>C&#233;cile Oury</copyright-holder>
<license ns0:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
<license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" ns0:type="simple">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<related-object document-id="10.1371/journal.pone.0222979" document-id-type="doi" document-type="article" id="rel-obj001" link-type="peer-reviewed-article" />
<custom-meta-group>
<custom-meta>
<meta-name>Submission Version</meta-name>
<meta-value>0</meta-value>
</custom-meta>
</custom-meta-group>
</front-stub>
<body>
<p>
<named-content content-type="letter-date">1 Aug 2019</named-content>
</p>
<p>PONE-D-19-17543</p>
<p>Transcatheter Aortic Valve Implantation Versus Conservative Management for Severe Aortic Stenosis in Real Clinical Practice</p>
<p>PLOS ONE</p>
<p>Dear Dr Naritatsu Saito,</p>
<p>Thank you for submitting your manuscript to PLOS ONE. After careful consideration, we feel that it has merit but does not fully meet PLOS ONE&#8217;s publication criteria as it currently stands. Therefore, we invite you to submit a revised version of the manuscript that addresses the points raised during the review process.</p>
<p>In the revised version of the manuscript, you should provide some lacking informations on patients, including inclusion/exclusion criteria. Some re-analyses should be performed in line with updated thresholds from recent studies. Satistics methods need to be adapted according to reviewer's comments.</p>
<p>We would appreciate receiving your revised manuscript by 31st October. When you are ready to submit your revision, log on to <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://www.editorialmanager.com/pone/" ns0:type="simple">https://www.editorialmanager.com/pone/</ext-link> and select the 'Submissions Needing Revision' folder to locate your manuscript file.</p>
<p>If you would like to make changes to your financial disclosure, please include your updated statement in your cover letter.</p>
<p>To enhance the reproducibility of your results, we recommend that if applicable you deposit your laboratory protocols in protocols.io, where a protocol can be assigned its own identifier (DOI) such that it can be cited independently in the future. For instructions see: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://journals.plos.org/plosone/s/submission-guidelines#loc-laboratory-protocols" ns0:type="simple">http://journals.plos.org/plosone/s/submission-guidelines#loc-laboratory-protocols</ext-link></p>
<p>Please include the following items when submitting your revised manuscript:</p>
<p><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>A rebuttal letter that responds to each point raised by the academic editor and reviewer(s). This letter should be uploaded as separate file and labeled 'Response to Reviewers'.</p></list-item><list-item><p>A marked-up copy of your manuscript that highlights changes made to the original version. This file should be uploaded as separate file and labeled 'Revised Manuscript with Track Changes'.</p></list-item><list-item><p>An unmarked version of your revised paper without tracked changes. This file should be uploaded as separate file and labeled 'Manuscript'.</p></list-item></list></p>
<p>Please note while forming your response, if your article is accepted, you may have the opportunity to make the peer review history publicly available. The record will include editor decision letters (with reviews) and your responses to reviewer comments. If eligible, we will contact you to opt in or out.</p>
<p>We look forward to receiving your revised manuscript.</p>
<p>Kind regards,</p>
<p>C&#233;cile Oury</p>
<p>Academic Editor</p>
<p>PLOS ONE</p>
<p>Journal Requirements:</p>
<p>1. When submitting your revision, we need you to address these additional requirements.</p>
<p>Please ensure that your manuscript meets PLOS ONE's style requirements, including those for file naming. The PLOS ONE style templates can be found at</p>
<p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://www.journals.plos.org/plosone/s/file?id=wjVg/PLOSOne_formatting_sample_main_body.pdf" ns0:type="simple">http://www.journals.plos.org/plosone/s/file?id=wjVg/PLOSOne_formatting_sample_main_body.pdf</ext-link> and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://www.journals.plos.org/plosone/s/file?id=ba62/PLOSOne_formatting_sample_title_authors_affiliations.pdf" ns0:type="simple">http://www.journals.plos.org/plosone/s/file?id=ba62/PLOSOne_formatting_sample_title_authors_affiliations.pdf</ext-link></p>
<p>2. Please provide details of the author contributions in accordance with CRediT standards <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://journals.plos.org/plosone/s/authorship" ns0:type="simple">https://journals.plos.org/plosone/s/authorship</ext-link></p>
<p>*In your financial disclosure, please clearly specify whether the funders played any role in the study.</p>
<p>3. Please provide the names of all the ethics committees which approved this study.</p>
<p>*Please include the information on ethics approval and consent, given in the methods section of your manuscript, in the ethics statement on the online submission form.</p>
<p>4. Thank you for stating in your Funding Statement:</p>
<p>&#160;[Yes</p>
<p>&#160;CURRENT AS registry was supported by an educational grant from the Research Institute for Production Development (Kyoto, Japan).].&#160;</p>
<p>* Please provide an amended statement that declares *all* the funding or sources of support (whether external or internal to your organization) received during this study, as detailed online in our guide for authors at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://journals.plos.org/plosone/s/submit-now" ns0:type="simple">http://journals.plos.org/plosone/s/submit-now</ext-link>. &#160;Please also include the statement &#8220;There was no additional external funding received for this study.&#8221; in your updated Funding Statement.</p>
<p>* Please include your amended Funding Statement within your cover letter. We will change the online submission form on your behalf.</p>
<p>[Note: HTML markup is below. Please do not edit.]</p>
<p>Reviewers' comments:</p>
<p>Reviewer's Responses to Questions</p>
<p><bold>Comments to the Author</bold></p>
<p>1. Is the manuscript technically sound, and do the data support the conclusions?</p>
<p>The manuscript must describe a technically sound piece of scientific research with data that supports the conclusions. Experiments must have been conducted rigorously, with appropriate controls, replication, and sample sizes. The conclusions must be drawn appropriately based on the data presented. </p>
<p>Reviewer #1: Yes</p>
<p>Reviewer #2: No</p>
<p>**********</p>
<p>2. Has the statistical analysis been performed appropriately and rigorously? </p>
<p>Reviewer #1: Yes</p>
<p>Reviewer #2: No</p>
<p>**********</p>
<p>3. Have the authors made all data underlying the findings in their manuscript fully available?</p>
<p>The <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://www.plosone.org/static/policies.action#sharing" ns0:type="simple">PLOS Data policy</ext-link> requires authors to make all data underlying the findings described in their manuscript fully available without restriction, with rare exception (please refer to the Data Availability Statement in the manuscript PDF file). The data should be provided as part of the manuscript or its supporting information, or deposited to a public repository. For example, in addition to summary statistics, the data points behind means, medians and variance measures should be available. If there are restrictions on publicly sharing data&#8212;e.g. participant privacy or use of data from a third party&#8212;those must be specified.</p>
<p>Reviewer #1: Yes</p>
<p>Reviewer #2: Yes</p>
<p>**********</p>
<p>4. Is the manuscript presented in an intelligible fashion and written in standard English?</p>
<p>PLOS ONE does not copyedit accepted manuscripts, so the language in submitted articles must be clear, correct, and unambiguous. Any typographical or grammatical errors should be corrected at revision, so please note any specific errors here.</p>
<p>Reviewer #1: Yes</p>
<p>Reviewer #2: Yes</p>
<p>**********</p>
<p>5. Review Comments to the Author</p>
<p>Please use the space provided to explain your answers to the questions above. You may also include additional comments for the author, including concerns about dual publication, research ethics, or publication ethics. (Please upload your review as an attachment if it exceeds 20,000 characters)</p>
<p>Reviewer #1: This is a nice study combining two prospective registries. The study is providing new and valuable data.</p>
<p>The references are perhaps missing European registries&#8217;data.</p>
<p>The paper is nicely written and very informative, the discussion is really nice and the figures are clean.</p>
<p>Perhaps the text is a bit too long? It could be shorten to provide more data on subgroups with figures.</p>
<p>It appears that the study is not including patients with any low gradient, low flow AS? That is a pity and adding a specific analysis on this group of patients could be even more original and valuable as no strong data are available yet.</p>
<p>The EF is looked according to cut-off of 40 and 50% but the recent literature is underscoring the difference between 60 or 55% versus below: could the authors provide these data and the Kaplan Meier curves according to EF above of below 55% when the patients are treated or not?</p>
<p>The COPD is strikingly different between groups: comments.</p>
<p>The ischemic heart disease: comments?</p>
<p>Is it expected to have such a low rate of AF in such elderly patients? This is strikingly different for USA and Europe.</p>
<p>Reviewer #2: General comments:</p>
<p>In this observational retrospective study authors aimed at comparing TAVI to medical treatment using historical cohort data. The study is not timely since the question asked has been previously answered in much more robust studies. However, it could still be interesting regarding the long-term differences between the two groups. But authors should provide a more robust methodological and statistical approach and would benefit from simplification (the sensitivity and subgroup analyses provide little new insight).</p>
<p>Specific comments:</p>
<p>&#8226; Not a timely study, as attested by the use of Sapien XT valves, 37% of alternative access, with probably transapical as first alternative (Results page 22 &#8220;trans-femoral approach was selected only in 63% of patients&#8221;) with a comparator based on a historical pre-TAVI era cohort. Must be clearly stated that comparison is not applicable to current clinical practice</p>
<p>&#8226; Method page 15 &#8220;We also excluded those patients &#8230; might also be contraindicated for TAVI&#8221; Authors should clarify what patients were excluded here and reformulate this statement because TAVI is a clear indication for a large proportion of patients which are contraindicated to SAVR. Please also clarify the flow chart figure 1 with regard to the box &#8220;conservative group with formal indication of AVR &#8230;&#8221;</p>
<p>&#8226; Statistical analysis page 17 &#8220;Because some variables were not well balanced &#8230; further adjustment by using the Cox proportional hazard models&#8221; In case of PS matching failure please consider removing PS matching step and apply multivariable Cox upfront.</p>
<p>&#8226; Statistical analysis &#8220;We also performed subgroup analyses in terms of age, sex, STS score, LVEF, and high/low gradient AS in the propensity-score matched cohort&#8221; As reported by authors, the PS matching failed, therefore building subgroups for this cohort is likely to provide biased results.</p>
<p>&#8226; Please consider separating all-cause mortality and HR rehospitalization all over the manuscript. Those 2 outcomes have little in common and the database is likely able to provide these data.</p>
<p>&#8226; Please provide information regarding TAVI procedural characteristics in a Table: valves used, labels/generations, pathways, TEE use, general versus local anaesthesia, complications, etc</p>
<p>**********</p>
<p>6. PLOS authors have the option to publish the peer review history of their article (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://journals.plos.org/plosone/s/editorial-and-peer-review-process#loc-peer-review-history" ns0:type="simple">what does this mean?</ext-link>). If published, this will include your full peer review and any attached files.</p>
<p>If you choose &#8220;no&#8221;, your identity will remain anonymous but your review may still be made public.</p>
<p><bold>Do you want your identity to be public for this peer review?</bold> For information about this choice, including consent withdrawal, please see our <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://www.plos.org/privacy-policy" ns0:type="simple">Privacy Policy</ext-link>.</p>
<p>Reviewer #1: No</p>
<p>Reviewer #2: Yes: Thomas Modine, Pavel Overtchouk</p>
<p>[NOTE: If reviewer comments were submitted as an attachment file, they will be attached to this email and accessible via the submission site. Please log into your account, locate the manuscript record, and check for the action link "View Attachments". If this link does not appear, there are no attachment files to be viewed.]</p>
<p>While revising your submission, please upload your figure files to the Preflight Analysis and Conversion Engine (PACE) digital diagnostic tool, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://pacev2.apexcovantage.com/" ns0:type="simple">https://pacev2.apexcovantage.com/</ext-link>. PACE helps ensure that figures meet PLOS requirements. To use PACE, you must first register as a user. Registration is free. Then, login and navigate to the UPLOAD tab, where you will find detailed instructions on how to use the tool. If you encounter any issues or have any questions when using PACE, please email us at <email ns0:type="simple">figures@plos.org</email>. Please note that Supporting Information files do not need this step.</p>
</body>
</sub-article>
