<sub-article xmlns:ns0="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="author-comment" id="pone.0222544.r004">
<front-stub>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0222544.r004</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title>Author response to Decision Letter 1</article-title>
</title-group>
<related-object document-id="10.1371/journal.pone.0222544" document-id-type="doi" document-type="peer-reviewed-article" id="rel-obj004" link-type="rebutted-decision-letter" object-id="10.1371/journal.pone.0222544.r003" object-id-type="doi" object-type="decision-letter" />
<custom-meta-group>
<custom-meta>
<meta-name>Submission Version</meta-name>
<meta-value>2</meta-value>
</custom-meta>
</custom-meta-group>
</front-stub>
<body>
<p>
<named-content content-type="author-response-date">29 Aug 2019</named-content>
</p>
<p>Dear Editor,</p>
<p>We thank the reviewers for their work and their interesting remarks.</p>
<p>Please consider the revised version of our manuscript.</p>
<p>Please find below the answers to the reviewers&#8217; comments.</p>
<p>In the revised manuscript, all substantial modifications appear in red and bold whereas previous modifications remain in black and bold.</p>
<p>Sincerely yours.</p>
<p>Romain Jouffroy</p>
<p>Responses to Reviewers' comments:</p>
<p>Comments to the Author</p>
<p>1. If the authors have adequately addressed your comments raised in a previous round of review and you feel that this manuscript is now acceptable for publication, you may indicate that here to bypass the &#8220;Comments to the Author&#8221; section, enter your conflict of interest statement in the &#8220;Confidential to Editor&#8221; section, and submit your "Accept" recommendation.</p>
<p>Reviewer #1: (No Response)</p>
<p>Reviewer #2: All comments have been addressed</p>
<p>2. Is the manuscript technically sound, and do the data support the conclusions?</p>
<p>The manuscript must describe a technically sound piece of scientific research with data that supports the conclusions. Experiments must have been conducted rigorously, with appropriate controls, replication, and sample sizes. The conclusions must be drawn appropriately based on the data presented. </p>
<p>Reviewer #1: Yes</p>
<p>Reviewer #2: Yes</p>
<p>3. Has the statistical analysis been performed appropriately and rigorously? </p>
<p>Reviewer #1: I Don't Know</p>
<p>Reviewer #2: Yes</p>
<p>4. Have the authors made all data underlying the findings in their manuscript fully available?</p>
<p>The PLOS Data policy requires authors to make all data underlying the findings described in their manuscript fully available without restriction, with rare exception (please refer to the Data Availability Statement in the manuscript PDF file). The data should be provided as part of the manuscript or its supporting information, or deposited to a public repository. For example, in addition to summary statistics, the data points behind means, medians and variance measures should be available. If there are restrictions on publicly sharing data&#8212;e.g. participant privacy or use of data from a third party&#8212;those must be specified.</p>
<p>Reviewer #1: Yes</p>
<p>Reviewer #2: Yes</p>
<p>5. Is the manuscript presented in an intelligible fashion and written in standard English?</p>
<p>PLOS ONE does not copyedit accepted manuscripts, so the language in submitted articles must be clear, correct, and unambiguous. Any typographical or grammatical errors should be corrected at revision, so please note any specific errors here.</p>
<p>Reviewer #1: No</p>
<p>Reviewer #2: Yes </p>
<p>6. Review Comments to the Author</p>
<p>Reviewer #1: I thank the authors for their revisions that adequately addressed my major concerns. I have several additional comments/suggestions to further improve the manuscript for publication.</p>
<p>Answer: We thank the reviewer for his work and new comments/suggestions to further improve our manuscript. </p>
<p>I appreciate the authors&#8217; clarification regarding the novelty of their study in comparison to prior studies. The authors should add a sentence or two introducing what trail running is as explained in their response to my first comment. They can include aspects such as terrain, running surface, flat vs. hills, carry extra weight, and make a comparison with marathons to help clarify and explain differences in the races.</p>
<p>Answer: We thank you for this suggestion. In the revised manuscript, three sentences have been added to better explain to the readers what trail running is in comparison with marathons.</p>
<p>Throughout the manuscript, the authors should emphasize &#8220;ultra-distance&#8221; when referring to the race rather than &#8220;long-distance&#8221; to distinguish from marathons.</p>
<p>Answer: We thank the reviewer for this suggestion. In the revised manuscript, the term &#8220;long-distance&#8221; was replaced by &#8220;ultra-distance&#8221;. </p>
<p>Authors use the words running where in some sentences, race would be the more appropriate word. The sentences can be reworded so that running also fits if the authors prefer to use that word. Page 3 lines 4 and 5 &#8211; &#8220;biomarker injury while running&#8221; or &#8220;biomarker injury during the race&#8221;.</p>
<p>Answer: We thank the reviewer for this suggestion. In the revised manuscript, the term running was replaced by race.</p>
<p>Temporal seems to be a more appropriate word than kinetic when describing changes in biomarkers over time. Kinetic refers more to the changes in the rate of something. </p>
<p>Answer: We thank the reviewer for this interesting remark. In the revised manuscript, the word &#8220;kinetic&#8221; running was replaced by &#8220;temporal&#8221;.</p>
<p>The authors can consider calculating rates of change at each time point but I don&#8217;t think that would be of any clinical significance.</p>
<p>Answer: We fully agree with the reviewer. As underlined, the rate of change does not provide more clinical information in this study. </p>
<p>As some of the authors have previously published on changes in cardiac function during ultradistance racing, do the authors think the reduction in eGFR can be partially explained by cardiac strain? </p>
<p>Also, the authors state in the discussion on page 18 line 22 that AKI may be prerenal. Besides extracellular volume depletion, it may be worth mentioning other potential mechanisms such effects on renal blood flow by the sympathetic nervous system, and antidiuresis from vasopressin release in response to stress/pain. May be worth commenting on to build the discussion but not critical.</p>
<p>Answer: We fully agree with this very interesting remark. A sentence has been inserted in the discussion in order to take into account the remark. </p>
<p>Page 5 line 3 - As the authors discuss recent trends in increasing race distance in several parts of the manuscript, they should consider using a more recent reference than the one used from 2001.</p>
<p>Answer: We thank the reviewer for this suggestion. In the revised manuscript, a more recent reference replaced the one of 2001. Consequently, the sentence was modified. </p>
<p>Page 5 line 2 and line 10 &#8211; fix the use of two vs. 2</p>
<p>Answer: We thank the reviewer. The modification appears in the revised version of the manuscript. </p>
<p>Page 5 line 24 &#8211; clarify that &#8220;before and after&#8221; is referring to the race</p>
<p>Answer: We thank the reviewer. The modification appears in the revised version of the manuscript.</p>
<p>Page 6 line 3 &#8211; blood and urine samples were also collected before the race.</p>
<p>Answer: We fully agree with the reviewer. The term &#8220;before&#8221; was added in the sentence.</p>
<p>Did participants exclusively drink water or could some have consumed sports drinks? Might be worth discussing the association with kidney injury and rehydration with sugar sweetened beverages if participants did in fact have access to it.</p>
<p>Answer: We thank the reviewer for this suggestion. The participants drink only water during the race. A sentence was inserted in the revised version of the manuscript to clarify this point.</p>
<p>It is more appropriate to use the word &#8220;chloride&#8221; rather than &#8220;chlorine&#8221; in the text and tables.</p>
<p>Answer: We thank the reviewer. The modification appears in the revised version of the manuscript.</p>
<p>Page 12 lines 9-10 &#8211; Myoglobin increased from 34 to 2761, if not statistically significant, this increase may possibly be of some clinical significance. Although not massively elevated, do the authors believe this elevation could have contributed to any reduction in eGFR?</p>
<p>Answer: We fully agree with the author that the myoglobin elevation at the end of the race vs start could partly explain the reduction in eGFR. </p>
<p>Page 14 lines 12-16 &#8211; Awkward sentence structure. These sentences would benefit from English editing.</p>
<p>Answer: We thank the reviewer. The sentences were edited in the new version of the manuscript. </p>
<p>Page 18 line 23 - If the hypothesis is that free access to food and water limited the kidney injury, it is safe to say on page 18 lines 12-13 that suggesting dehydration and antidiuresis?</p>
<p>Answer: We fully agree with the reviewer for this very interesting suggestion. During the race, free access to food and water was limited to the refreshment points allowed by the race organisation. Thus, we cannot exclude that some participants experienced dehydration and antidiuresis during the race (all samples were collected before the participant refreshed). A sentence was inserted in the revised version of the manuscript to clarify this point.</p>
<p>Page 19 line 21 &#8211; ultra endurance races do in fact have considerable effects to kidney function such as, as the authors state, antidiuresis. However, it would be more accurate to state that ultra-endurance races specifically have no impact on acute kidney injury.</p>
<p>Answer: We fully agree with this remark and thank the reviewer. The sentence was modified in order to take into account the remark.</p>
<p>Reviewer #2: (No Response)</p>
<supplementary-material id="pone.0222544.s002" mimetype="application/vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.wordprocessingml.document" position="float" ns0:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0222544.s002" ns0:type="simple">
<label>Attachment</label>
<caption>
<p>Submitted filename: <named-content content-type="submitted-filename">Response to Reviewers.docx</named-content></p>
</caption>
</supplementary-material>
</body>
</sub-article>
