<sub-article xmlns:ns0="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="aggregated-review-documents" id="pone.0222335.r001" specific-use="decision-letter">
<front-stub>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0222335.r001</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title>Decision Letter 0</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Harhaus</surname>
<given-names>Leila</given-names>
</name>
<role>Academic Editor</role>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<permissions>
<copyright-year>2019</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>Leila Harhaus</copyright-holder>
<license ns0:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
<license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" ns0:type="simple">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<related-object document-id="10.1371/journal.pone.0222335" document-id-type="doi" document-type="article" id="rel-obj001" link-type="peer-reviewed-article" />
<custom-meta-group>
<custom-meta>
<meta-name>Submission Version</meta-name>
<meta-value>0</meta-value>
</custom-meta>
</custom-meta-group>
</front-stub>
<body>
<p>
<named-content content-type="letter-date">10 Jul 2019</named-content>
</p>
<p>PONE-D-19-16142</p>
<p>Anatomical Analysis of Antebrachial Cutaneous Nerve Distribution Pattern and Its Clinical Implications for Sensory Reconstruction</p>
<p>PLOS ONE</p>
<p>Dear Dr Yang,</p>
<p>Thank you for submitting your manuscript to PLOS ONE. After careful consideration, we feel that it has merit but does not fully meet PLOS ONE&#8217;s publication criteria as it currently stands. Therefore, we invite you to submit a revised version of the manuscript that addresses the points raised during the review process.</p>
<p>We would appreciate receiving your revised manuscript by Aug 24 2019 11:59PM. When you are ready to submit your revision, log on to <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://www.editorialmanager.com/pone/" ns0:type="simple">https://www.editorialmanager.com/pone/</ext-link> and select the 'Submissions Needing Revision' folder to locate your manuscript file.</p>
<p>If you would like to make changes to your financial disclosure, please include your updated statement in your cover letter.</p>
<p>To enhance the reproducibility of your results, we recommend that if applicable you deposit your laboratory protocols in protocols.io, where a protocol can be assigned its own identifier (DOI) such that it can be cited independently in the future. For instructions see: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://journals.plos.org/plosone/s/submission-guidelines#loc-laboratory-protocols" ns0:type="simple">http://journals.plos.org/plosone/s/submission-guidelines#loc-laboratory-protocols</ext-link></p>
<p>Please include the following items when submitting your revised manuscript:</p>
<p><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>A rebuttal letter that responds to each point raised by the academic editor and reviewer(s). This letter should be uploaded as separate file and labeled 'Response to Reviewers'.</p></list-item><list-item><p>A marked-up copy of your manuscript that highlights changes made to the original version. This file should be uploaded as separate file and labeled 'Revised Manuscript with Track Changes'.</p></list-item><list-item><p>An unmarked version of your revised paper without tracked changes. This file should be uploaded as separate file and labeled 'Manuscript'.</p></list-item></list></p>
<p>Please note while forming your response, if your article is accepted, you may have the opportunity to make the peer review history publicly available. The record will include editor decision letters (with reviews) and your responses to reviewer comments. If eligible, we will contact you to opt in or out.</p>
<p>We look forward to receiving your revised manuscript.</p>
<p>Kind regards,</p>
<p>Leila Harhaus</p>
<p>Academic Editor</p>
<p>PLOS ONE</p>
<p><bold>Journal Requirements</bold></p>
<p>1. When submitting your revision, we need you to address these additional requirements.</p>
<p>Please ensure that your manuscript meets PLOS ONE's style requirements, including those for file naming. The PLOS ONE style templates can be found at</p>
<p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://www.journals.plos.org/plosone/s/file?id=wjVg/PLOSOne_formatting_sample_main_body.pdf" ns0:type="simple">http://www.journals.plos.org/plosone/s/file?id=wjVg/PLOSOne_formatting_sample_main_body.pdf</ext-link> and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://www.journals.plos.org/plosone/s/file?id=ba62/PLOSOne_formatting_sample_title_authors_affiliations.pdf" ns0:type="simple">http://www.journals.plos.org/plosone/s/file?id=ba62/PLOSOne_formatting_sample_title_authors_affiliations.pdf</ext-link></p>
<p>2. Thank you for including your ethics statement:&#160; "Twelve adult cadavers, 8 men and 4 women.The use of these specimens was authorized by the ethics committee of our school.".&#160; &#160;</p>
<p>a.Please amend your current ethics statement to include the full name of the ethics committee/institutional review board(s) that approved your specific study.</p>
<p>b.Please amend your current ethics statement to confirm that your named institutional review board or ethics committee specifically approved this study.</p>
<p>c.Once you have amended this/these statement(s) in the Methods section of the manuscript, please add the same text to the &#8220;Ethics Statement&#8221; field of the submission form (via &#8220;Edit Submission&#8221;).</p>
<p>For additional information about PLOS ONE ethical requirements for human subjects research, please refer to <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://journals.plos.org/plosone/s/submission-guidelines#loc-human-subjects-research" ns0:type="simple">http://journals.plos.org/plosone/s/submission-guidelines#loc-human-subjects-research</ext-link>.</p>
<p>3. Thank you for stating that &#8220;The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript&#8221; in your financial disclosure.</p>
<p>Please also provide the name of the funders of this study (as well as grant numbers if available) in your financial disclosure statement.</p>
<p>Please include your amended statements within your cover letter; we will change the online submission form on your behalf.</p>
<p>4. Please include captions for your Supporting Information files at the end of your manuscript, and update any in-text citations to match accordingly. Please see our Supporting Information guidelines for more information: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://journals.plos.org/plosone/s/supporting-information" ns0:type="simple">http://journals.plos.org/plosone/s/supporting-information</ext-link>.</p>
<p><bold>Comments to the Author</bold></p>
<p>1. Is the manuscript technically sound, and do the data support the conclusions?</p>
<p>The manuscript must describe a technically sound piece of scientific research with data that supports the conclusions. Experiments must have been conducted rigorously, with appropriate controls, replication, and sample sizes. The conclusions must be drawn appropriately based on the data presented. </p>
<p>Reviewer #1: Yes</p>
<p>Reviewer #2: Yes</p>
<p>Reviewer #3: Yes</p>
<p>**********</p>
<p>2. Has the statistical analysis been performed appropriately and rigorously? </p>
<p>Reviewer #1: N/A</p>
<p>Reviewer #2: Yes</p>
<p>Reviewer #3: I Don't Know</p>
<p>**********</p>
<p>3. Have the authors made all data underlying the findings in their manuscript fully available?</p>
<p>The <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://www.plosone.org/static/policies.action#sharing" ns0:type="simple">PLOS Data policy</ext-link> requires authors to make all data underlying the findings described in their manuscript fully available without restriction, with rare exception (please refer to the Data Availability Statement in the manuscript PDF file). The data should be provided as part of the manuscript or its supporting information, or deposited to a public repository. For example, in addition to summary statistics, the data points behind means, medians and variance measures should be available. If there are restrictions on publicly sharing data&#8212;e.g. participant privacy or use of data from a third party&#8212;those must be specified.</p>
<p>Reviewer #1: Yes</p>
<p>Reviewer #2: Yes</p>
<p>Reviewer #3: Yes</p>
<p>**********</p>
<p>4. Is the manuscript presented in an intelligible fashion and written in standard English?</p>
<p>PLOS ONE does not copyedit accepted manuscripts, so the language in submitted articles must be clear, correct, and unambiguous. Any typographical or grammatical errors should be corrected at revision, so please note any specific errors here.</p>
<p>Reviewer #1: Yes</p>
<p>Reviewer #2: Yes</p>
<p>Reviewer #3: Yes</p>
<p>**********</p>
<p>5. Review Comments to the Author</p>
<p>Please use the space provided to explain your answers to the questions above. You may also include additional comments for the author, including concerns about dual publication, research ethics, or publication ethics. (Please upload your review as an attachment if it exceeds 20,000 characters)</p>
<p>Reviewer #1: The paper is original and adds to the knowledge base in this area using a novel approach to staining and defining the branching anatomy. The paper is well written and no substantial revisions are required. In line 73 the &#8220;A&#8221; should be non capital and in line 173 there should be a space between &#8220;Fig&#8221; and &#8220;3&#8221;.</p>
<p>Reviewer #2: DEAR AUTHOR,</p>
<p>THIS STUDY IS A VERY GOOD CADAVERIC WORK, DISPLAYING FOREARM SENSITIVE DISTRUBUTION WITH SOME LIMITATIONS CONCERNING RACE DIFFERENCES. HOWEVER CLINICAL USE OF THIS KNOWLEDGE ( YOUR FINDINGS ) IS DEBATABLE SINCE, FLAP ELEVATION STILL DEPENDS ON VASCULAR (PERFORATOR VESSEL) DISTRIBUTION.</p>
<p>I HAVE SOME DOUBTS REGARDING DONOR AREA SENSITIVE NERVE THICKNESS IS DIRECTLY CORRELATED WITH BETTER SENSITIVE OUTCOME, YOU WOULD RATHER SMOOTHEN YOUR IDEAS OR SUPPORT WTH MORE DATA.</p>
<p>Reviewer #3: This study describes distribution of forearm cutaneous nerves including gross anatomy, main and minor branches, interconnections and density. One of the aims is to give clinical suggestions to improve flap design in a matter or sensory reconstruction at recipient site and possible sensory loss at donor site.</p>
<p>The study is well designed and appropriate methods were used including application of modified Sihler's staining to reveal and analyze cutaneous distribution.</p>
<p>Advantages:</p>
<p>- novel data about branches distribution, density and interconnections between major antebrachial nerves</p>
<p>Disadvantages:</p>
<p>- the process of pictures conversion and further image processing is not well described</p>
<p>- although authors describe the results thickness, area and nerve branch density of each region (p.10) they provide only general ANOVA result (p. 11) without post-hoc analysis</p>
<p>- clinical implications are hard to drawn due to big amount of data in multiple regions - most suitable donor sites could be marked on separate figure</p>
<p>In the summary the study gives relevant and precise anatomical information but clinical implications are not so clear to me at this moment.</p>
<p>**********</p>
<p>6. PLOS authors have the option to publish the peer review history of their article (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://journals.plos.org/plosone/s/editorial-and-peer-review-process#loc-peer-review-history" ns0:type="simple">what does this mean?</ext-link>). If published, this will include your full peer review and any attached files.</p>
<p>If you choose &#8220;no&#8221;, your identity will remain anonymous but your review may still be made public.</p>
<p><bold>Do you want your identity to be public for this peer review?</bold> For information about this choice, including consent withdrawal, please see our <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://www.plos.org/privacy-policy" ns0:type="simple">Privacy Policy</ext-link>.</p>
<p>Reviewer #1: No</p>
<p>Reviewer #2: No</p>
<p>Reviewer #3: Yes: Piotr Czarnecki</p>
<p>[NOTE: If reviewer comments were submitted as an attachment file, they will be attached to this email and accessible via the submission site. Please log into your account, locate the manuscript record, and check for the action link "View Attachments". If this link does not appear, there are no attachment files to be viewed.]</p>
<p>While revising your submission, please upload your figure files to the Preflight Analysis and Conversion Engine (PACE) digital diagnostic tool, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://pacev2.apexcovantage.com/" ns0:type="simple">https://pacev2.apexcovantage.com/</ext-link>. PACE helps ensure that figures meet PLOS requirements. To use PACE, you must first register as a user. Registration is free. Then, login and navigate to the UPLOAD tab, where you will find detailed instructions on how to use the tool. If you encounter any issues or have any questions when using PACE, please email us at <email ns0:type="simple">figures@plos.org</email>. Please note that Supporting Information files do not need this step.</p>
</body>
</sub-article>
