<sub-article article-type="author-comment" id="pone.0222393.r002">
<front-stub>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0222393.r002</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title>Author response to Decision Letter 0</article-title>
</title-group>
<related-object document-id="10.1371/journal.pone.0222393" document-id-type="doi" document-type="peer-reviewed-article" id="rel-obj002" link-type="rebutted-decision-letter" object-id="10.1371/journal.pone.0222393.r001" object-id-type="doi" object-type="decision-letter" />
<custom-meta-group>
<custom-meta>
<meta-name>Submission Version</meta-name>
<meta-value>1</meta-value>
</custom-meta>
</custom-meta-group>
</front-stub>
<body>
<p>
<named-content content-type="author-response-date">22 Aug 2019</named-content>
</p>
<p>Reviewer 1:</p>
<p>Comment:</p>
<p>Comment #1: The authors should better clarify the storage times, were the bacterial lysates stored at -80 &#176; C for how long before the analysis?</p>
<p>Thank you for your feedback. The lysates were only stored for a brief time (approximately 1 month) before extraction, a time which was consistent across all samples. In our experience, lysates of this nature suspended in KH2PO4-based lysis buffer are stable for metabolomics analyses for several years, so we are confident that this short storage period is inconsequential to the experiment. We have adjusted the text (highlighted below) as follows to make this more clear to the reader.</p>
<p>&#8220;Cell lysates were immediately frozen at -80 &#176;C to ensure their stability and were briefly held frozen (approximately 1 month) until needed for extraction, all samples being stored for an equal period of time. In our experience, lysates of this nature suspended in KH2PO4-based lysis buffer are stable for metabolomics analyses for several years.&#8221;</p>
<p>Comment #2: Was the storage time the same for all the samples analyzed in this work?</p>
<p>Thank you for your feedback. Yes, the storage time was the sample for all samples analyzed in this work. Please see our response to Comment #1 in which we clarify this point in the adjusted text.</p>
<p>Comment #3: The authors compare the metabolic profiles between the two bacterial strains grown in a medium supplemented with oxalate (20 mM), they believe that it is not necessary to carry out controls on cultures not supplemented with oxalate? Or have they already performed these experiments in the past?</p>
<p>Thank you for your feedback. The purpose of this experiment was to profile and compare the metabolomes of L. acidophilus and L. gasseri, not necessarily to compare the metabolomes in an oxalate versus non-oxalate environment. Oxalate was included in the media simply because that is how we have historically cultured Lactobacillus, but it will grow in many different types of media so it is difficult to assign one media as its native environment. Therefore, we did not perform an analysis on Lactobacillus grown without oxalate since such a control was outside of the focus of this experiment. </p>
<p>It would be interesting for future studies to compare how the metabolome of Lactobacillus changes in different types of media, but being that it grows in many different matrices, it would be difficult to establish what is the &#8220;native&#8221; media since there is no designated media that puts it into its native state. </p>
<p>Comment #4: The description of lipid extraction should be improved.</p>
<p>Thank you for your feedback. We believe there may be some confusion that the lipid extraction was not explained given the placement of references to the Folch method and our previous work at the beginning of the Lipid Extraction section. Immediately following this first sentence, the lipid extraction is explained in significant detail. To make this more clear to the reader, we have inserted text (highlighted below) that indicates the beginning of the description of the lipid extraction.</p>
<p>&#8220;Lipids were extracted using a modified version of the Folch method (41) similarly to our previous work (38) using the following process which we describe in detail here. From each normalized cell lysate sample, 150 &#181;L was transferred to a 12 mL glass vial. Extraction blanks were included for downstream data filtering using 150 &#181;L lysis buffer and were treated identically to biological samples. To each sample, 20 &#956;L of internal standard mix (Avanti Polar Lipids, Alabaster, AL, USA) was added followed by brief vortexing &#8211; LPC(17:0), PC(17:0/17:0), PG(14:0/14:0), PE(15:0/15:0), PS(14:0/14:0), TG(15:0/15:0/15:0), PI(8:0), SM(d18:1/17:0), CER(d18:1/17:0), DG(14:0/14:0), CL(15:0(3)-16:1), SO(d17:1), PAzePC, CER(Glycosyl(&#946;) C12), BMP(14:0 (S,R)), LSM(d17:1), 5 &#956;g/mL each in 2:1 chloroform:methanol. Next, 400 &#956;L methanol was added to each sample followed by vortexing, then 800 &#956;L chloroform was added. Samples were vortexed and incubated on ice for 20 min, with vortexing at 10 and 20 min, followed by addition of 200 &#956;L water. Samples were briefly vortexed and incubated on ice for 10 min with vortexing at 5 and 10 min. Separation of the organic and aqueous layers was achieved by centrifugation at 3260&#215;g, 4&#176;C for 10 min. The organic (bottom) layer containing lipid content was transferred to a new 12 mL glass vial in two steps: first with removal of 800 &#956;L of the original organic layer, followed by another removal of 400 &#956;L after re-extracting the remaining aqueous layer with 400 &#956;L 2:1 chloroform:methanol by incubating on ice for 10 min and centrifugation at 3260&#215;g, 4&#176;C for 10 min. Lipid extracts were dried under nitrogen at 30&#176;C and reconstituted in 300 &#956;L isopropanol. Samples were centrifuged at 3260&#215;g, 4&#176;C for 10 min to pellet any residual protein, and 250 &#956;L supernatants were transferred to glass LC vials for UHPLC-HRMS analysis.&#8221;</p>
<p>Reviewer 2: </p>
<p>Comment #1: The authors should explain for how long the bacterial lysates were stored at -80 &#176; C before analysis?</p>
<p>Thank you for your feedback. Please see our response to Reviewer 1 Comments #1 and #2, which addresses these same questions.</p>
<p>Comment #2: Have the authors performed the metabolic profiles also on cultures not supplemented with oxalate?</p>
<p>Thank you for your feedback. Please see our response to Reviewer 1 Comment #3, which addresses this same question.</p>
</body>
</sub-article>
