<sub-article xmlns:ns0="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="aggregated-review-documents" id="pgen.1008389.r001" specific-use="decision-letter">
<front-stub>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1008389.r001</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title>Decision Letter 0</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Payseur</surname>
<given-names>Bret</given-names>
</name>
<role>Section Editor: Evolution</role>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Bai</surname>
<given-names>Lu</given-names>
</name>
<role>Guest Editor</role>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<permissions>
<copyright-year>2019</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>Payseur, Bai</copyright-holder>
<license ns0:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
<license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" ns0:type="simple">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<related-object document-id="10.1371/journal.pgen.1008389" document-id-type="doi" document-type="article" id="rel-obj001" link-type="peer-reviewed-article" />
<custom-meta-group>
<custom-meta>
<meta-name>Submission Version</meta-name>
<meta-value>0</meta-value>
</custom-meta>
</custom-meta-group>
</front-stub>
<body>
<p>
<named-content content-type="letter-date">10 Jul 2019</named-content>
</p>
<p>* Please note while forming your response, if your article is accepted, you may have the opportunity to make the peer review history publicly available. The record will include editor decision letters (with reviews) and your responses to reviewer comments. If eligible, we will contact you to opt in or out. *</p>
<p>Dear Dr Zhang:</p>
<p>Thank you very much for submitting your Research Article entitled 'Chromosome-wide co-fluctuation of stochastic gene expression in mammalian cells' to PLOS Genetics. Your manuscript was fully evaluated at the editorial level and by three independent peer reviewers. The reviewers appreciated the attention to an important topic but identified some aspects of the manuscript that should be improved.</p>
<p>We therefore ask you to modify the manuscript according to the review recommendations before we can consider your manuscript for acceptance. Your revisions should address the specific points made by each reviewer.</p>
<p>In addition we ask that you:</p>
<p>1) Provide a detailed list of your responses to the review comments and a description of the changes you have made in the manuscript.</p>
<p>2) Upload a Striking Image with a corresponding caption to accompany your manuscript if one is available (either a new image or an existing one from within your manuscript). If this image is judged to be suitable, it may be featured on our website. Images should ideally be high resolution, eye-catching, single panel square images. For examples, please browse our <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://www.plosgenetics.org/article/browse/volume" ns0:type="simple">archive</ext-link>. If your image is from someone other than yourself, please ensure that the artist has read and agreed to the terms and conditions of the Creative Commons Attribution License. Note: we cannot publish copyrighted images.</p>
<p>We hope to receive your revised manuscript within the next 30 days. If you anticipate any delay in its return, we would ask you to let us know the expected resubmission date by email to <email ns0:type="simple">plosgenetics@plos.org</email>.</p>
<p>If present, accompanying reviewer attachments should be included with this email; please notify the journal office if any appear to be missing. They will also be available for download from the link below. You can use this link to log into the system when you are ready to submit a revised version, having first consulted our <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://journals.plos.org/plosgenetics/s/submit-now#loc-submission-checklist" ns0:type="simple">Submission Checklist</ext-link>.</p>
<p>While revising your submission, please upload your figure files to the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://pace.apexcovantage.com/" ns0:type="simple">Preflight Analysis and Conversion Engine</ext-link>&#160;(PACE) digital diagnostic tool. PACE helps ensure that figures meet PLOS requirements. To use PACE, you must first register as a user. Then, login and navigate to the UPLOAD tab, where you will find detailed instructions on how to use the tool. If you encounter any issues or have any questions when using PACE, please email us at <email ns0:type="simple">figures@plos.org</email>.</p>
<p>Please be aware that our&#160;<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://journals.plos.org/plosgenetics/s/data-availability" ns0:type="simple">data availability policy</ext-link>&#160;requires that all numerical data underlying graphs or summary statistics are included with the submission, and you will need to provide this upon resubmission if not already present. In addition, we do not permit the inclusion of phrases such as "data not shown" or "unpublished results" in manuscripts. All points should be backed up by data provided with the submission.</p>
<p>PLOS has incorporated <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://www.crossref.org/crosscheck.html" ns0:type="simple">Similarity Check</ext-link>, powered by iThenticate, into its journal-wide submission system in order to screen submitted content for originality before publication. Each PLOS journal undertakes screening on a proportion of submitted articles. You will be contacted if needed following the screening process.</p>
<p>To resubmit, you will need to go to the link below and 'Revise Submission' in the 'Submissions Needing Revision' folder.</p>
<p>[LINK]</p>
<p>Please let us know if you have any questions while making these revisions.</p>
<p>Yours sincerely,</p>
<p>Lu Bai</p>
<p>Guest Editor</p>
<p>PLOS Genetics</p>
<p>Bret Payseur</p>
<p>Section Editor: Evolution</p>
<p>PLOS Genetics</p>
<p>Reviewer's Responses to Questions</p>
<p><bold>Comments to the Authors:</bold></p>
<p><bold>Please note here if the review is uploaded as an attachment.</bold></p>
<p>Reviewer #1: The study of Sun &amp; Zhang reveals an interesting coupling between gene positioning along a chromosome and fluctuations, indicating that cis-correlations are higher than trans-correlations in the context of homologous chromosomes. The majority of tests are convincing, in particular the one showing that the effect becomes more prominent when they focus on highly expressed genes. The fact that the authors study the differential behavior of linked genes in comparison to their homologous counterparts (within a certain cell type) is clear in some but not in other contexts. Therefore, I suggest addressing the points below before the publication of the manuscript.</p>
<p>Major remarks</p>
<p>1) The comparison of expression fluctuations with chromosomal looping and chromatin accessibility clearly follows physical models of gene expression. However, the hypothesized link between expression fluctuations and protein complexes &#8220; the expression co-fluctuation of genes encoding components of the same protein complex is likely advantageous.&#8221; should be examined in more detail. The authors implicitly assume the formation of protein complexes is enhanced when the subunits expressed in a coordinated fashion, irrespective of the basis of comparison. However, it is possible that there is no difference in the correlation with homologous and heterologous interchromosomal fluctuations. This is important since each subunit of the dimer is expressed from a maternal and paternal chromosome even if they are positioned on homologous and heterologous chromosomes. Therefore, either the simulations should include different scenarios of chromosomal fluctuations or the above conclusion should be explained statistically more rigorously.</p>
<p>Minor remarks:</p>
<p>2) A. The authors compare stochastic intra-chromosomal and inter-chromosomal correlations. This is important because most studies (as mentioned in the discussion) do not distinguish intra-chromosomal effect. This is mentioned at several places, notably in the abstract, in the last paragraph of the introduction , first section of the results,&#8230;. However, the authors should not assume that the general audience understands the term &#8220;linked&#8221; and should explain that in more general terms in the author summary. For example, the authors could explain in the author summary that each individual receives a maternal and paternal copy of the same chromosome.</p>
<p>B. Figure 1 or Figure 2A should include the full depiction of pair(s) of homologous chromosomes so that it becomes clear what the authors mean.</p>
<p>3) The interchromosomal fluctuations may have a substantially stronger effect on gene choice than on protein complexes. Therefore, I suggest the authors discussing stochastic gene choice in the context of their results. The Protocadhering gene array is prototypical example where stochastic gene expression is very strongly depends on intrachromosomal looping controlled by the binding of the looping factor CTCF in neuronal progenitors (PMID: 15640798, 30257211). Therefore, the intrachromosomal fluctuations and conformational changes may have a strong impact on the choice and number of expressed protein isoforms of this membrane protein, which can underscore the biological relevance of the fluctuations studied by the authors.</p>
<p>Reviewer #2: RE: PGENETICS-D-19-00916</p>
<p>In this study, the authors investigated co-fluctuation of chromosomally-linked genes. This phenomenon was first discovered experimentally by a previous study using fluorescent reporters (Raj et al, 2006). Here the authors analyzed the existing single-cell RNA seq data and showed that this could be a genome-wide phenomenon. To this end, they showed statistically the expression correlations between linked alleles (on the same chromosome) of two genes are greater than those between unlinked alleles. With the support of additional analysis, they further demonstrated that the 3D proximity and chromatin co-accessibility could be the underlying mechanism of this effect. Finally, they proposed that, through natural selection, genes encoding components of the same complexes might be organized onto the same chromosomes to correlate their expression.</p>
<p>I find this paper well-written and scientifically interesting. Gene expression coordination in single cells has been an important topic of research. The authors performed a careful analysis of existing data and raised an intriguing model. I would recommend the acceptance of this manuscript for publication shall the concerns below be addressed.</p>
<p>1. I would think that the most direct way to coordinate gene expression of functionally-related genes in individual cells is through sharing the same trans or cis-regulatory factors. Is there a way to quantitively compare the contribution of this mechanism with the contribution of chromosomal linkage? I suspect that the former one might play a major role. The paper is interesting either way, but a careful discussion and comparison will be helpful.</p>
<p>2. Related to point 1, for natural selection, would sharing regulatory elements provide more plasticity than reorganizing the genome? Again, a careful discussion would be needed. Genome re-organization does not seem like the more intuitive way to ensure gene expression coordination.</p>
<p>3. In addition to genes encoding components of the same complexes, I wonder whether the same organization rule can be applied to the genes encoding components of the same signaling or metabolic pathways? If not, why?</p>
<p>Reviewer #3: The manuscript from Mengyi Sun and Jianzhi Zhang lays out the novel and provocative idea that coordinated fluctuations in gene expression stem from fluctuations in local histone H1 concentrations.</p>
<p>In support of this idea, they show that expression of "linked" (immediate nearest neighbors along the same chromosome) genes is more correlated than expression of the same pair of genes across homologous chromosomes. Suprisingly, this is true even when the two genes are seperated by over 100Mb, suggesting a 3D, not 1D, cause. Consistent with this, but unsuprisingly, alleles on the same chrommosome are more frequently in physical contact with each other than alleles on homologous chromosomes.</p>
<p>As a mechanism they propose local diffusion of H1, and in support of this mechanism they find that protein complex members whose expression is negativly correlated with H1 mRNA levels are more likely to be linked.</p>
<p>The ideas are provocative and, while, as the authors point out, the effect sizes are weak, some of this may be due to imperfect matches between experimental data and experimental error. In addition, evolution can act on weak effect sizes.</p>
<p>However, their model makes a major prediction that I'm suprised they didn't test, and I would like to see tested before the paper is published. The authors propose that 1D distance doesn't matter; only 3D distance. This predicts that the correlation shown in Fig1D should be even stronger if 3D distance is plotted on the X axis. Furthremore, being nearest neighbors (linked) shouldn't be the most predictive feature. HiC contact frequency should be.</p>
<p>If you recalculate something like Figure 1B but bin into multiple groups, binning genes by contact frequency and/or distance in 3D space, instead of only into linked vs unlinked, does the effect still hold?</p>
<p>In other words, genes that are unlinked, but still close in 3D space, should exhibit equally strong co-expression.</p>
<p>Minor Point:</p>
<p>"While each of the four correlations could be positive or negative, in the large data analyzed below, they are mostly positive and show approximately normal distributions across gene pairs examined."</p>
<p>I'd like to see the histograms of these four correlations (re(A1,B1), re(A2,B2), etc)</p>
<p>"All statistical analyses were performed using custom R and python scripts that are available upon request."</p>
<p>It's 2019; this should no longer be acceptable. Please put all code and intermediate (processed) data on github or some other repository.</p>
<p>The PLoS Genetics data availibility guidelines state that, if the data are not made publically availible, "The reasons for restrictions on public data deposition must also be specified. "</p>
<p>**********</p>
<p><bold>Have all data underlying the figures and results presented in the manuscript been provided?</bold></p>
<p>Large-scale datasets should be made available via a public repository as described in the <italic>PLOS Genetics</italic> <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://journals.plos.org/plosgenetics/s/data-availability" ns0:type="simple">data availability policy</ext-link>, and numerical data that underlies graphs or summary statistics should be provided in spreadsheet form as supporting information.</p>
<p>Reviewer #1: Yes</p>
<p>Reviewer #2: None</p>
<p>Reviewer #3: No: "All statistical analyses were performed using custom R and python scripts that are available upon request."</p>
<p>It's 2019; this should no longer be acceptable. Please put all code and intermediate (processed) data on github or some other repository.</p>
<p>The PLoS Genetics data availibility guidelines state that, if the data are not made publically availible, "The reasons for restrictions on public data deposition must also be specified. "</p>
<p>**********</p>
<p>PLOS authors have the option to publish the peer review history of their article (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://journals.plos.org/plosgenetics/s/editorial-and-peer-review-process#loc-peer-review-history" ns0:type="simple">what does this mean?</ext-link>). If published, this will include your full peer review and any attached files.</p>
<p>If you choose &#8220;no&#8221;, your identity will remain anonymous but your review may still be made public.</p>
<p><bold>Do you want your identity to be public for this peer review?</bold> For information about this choice, including consent withdrawal, please see our <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://www.plos.org/privacy-policy" ns0:type="simple">Privacy Policy</ext-link>.</p>
<p>Reviewer #1: No</p>
<p>Reviewer #2: No</p>
<p>Reviewer #3: Yes: Lucas Carey</p>
</body>
</sub-article>
