<sub-article xmlns:ns0="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="editor-report" id="pbio.3000460.r001" specific-use="decision-letter">
<front-stub>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pbio.3000460.r001</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title>Decision Letter 0</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Richardson</surname>
<given-names>Lauren A</given-names>
</name>
<role>Senior Editor</role>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<permissions>
<copyright-year>2019</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>Lauren A Richardson</copyright-holder>
<license ns0:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
<license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" ns0:type="simple">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<related-object document-id="10.1371/journal.pbio.3000460" document-id-type="doi" document-type="article" id="rel-obj001" link-type="peer-reviewed-article" />
<custom-meta-group>
<custom-meta>
<meta-name>Submission Version</meta-name>
<meta-value>0</meta-value>
</custom-meta>
</custom-meta-group>
</front-stub>
<body>
<p>
<named-content content-type="letter-date">5 Jun 2019</named-content>
</p>
<p>Dear Dr Ettensohn, </p>
<p>Thank you for submitting your manuscript entitled "The evolution of a new cell type was associated with competition for a signaling ligand" for consideration as a Research Article by PLOS Biology.</p>
<p>Your manuscript has now been evaluated by the PLOS Biology editorial staff as well as by an academic editor with relevant expertise and I am writing to let you know that we would like to send your submission out for external peer review.</p>
<p>However, before we can send your manuscript to reviewers, we need you to complete your submission by providing the metadata that is required for full assessment. To this end, please login to Editorial Manager where you will find the paper in the 'Submissions Needing Revisions' folder on your homepage. Please click 'Revise Submission' from the Action Links and complete all additional questions in the submission questionnaire.</p>
<p>Please re-submit your manuscript within two working days, ie. by Jun 07 2019 11:59PM.</p>
<p>Login to Editorial Manager here: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://www.editorialmanager.com/pbiology" ns0:type="simple">https://www.editorialmanager.com/pbiology</ext-link> </p>
<p>During resubmission, you will be invited to opt-in to posting your pre-review manuscript as a bioRxiv preprint. Visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://journals.plos.org/plosbiology/s/preprints" ns0:type="simple">http://journals.plos.org/plosbiology/s/preprints</ext-link> for full details. If you consent to posting your current manuscript as a preprint, please upload a single Preprint PDF when you re-submit. </p>
<p>Once your full submission is complete, your paper will undergo a series of checks in preparation for peer review. Once your manuscript has passed all checks it will be sent out for review. </p>
<p>Feel free to email us at <email ns0:type="simple">plosbiology@plos.org</email> if you have any queries relating to your submission.</p>
<p>Kind regards,</p>
<p>Lauren A Richardson, Ph.D</p>
<p>Senior Editor</p>
<p>PLOS Biology</p>
</body>
</sub-article>
