<sub-article xmlns:ns0="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="aggregated-review-documents" id="pone.0223257.r001" specific-use="decision-letter">
<front-stub>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0223257.r001</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title>Decision Letter 0</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Sato</surname>
<given-names>Marcello Otake</given-names>
</name>
<role>Academic Editor</role>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<permissions>
<copyright-year>2019</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>Marcello Otake Sato</copyright-holder>
<license ns0:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
<license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" ns0:type="simple">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<related-object document-id="10.1371/journal.pone.0223257" document-id-type="doi" document-type="article" id="rel-obj001" link-type="peer-reviewed-article" />
<custom-meta-group>
<custom-meta>
<meta-name>Submission Version</meta-name>
<meta-value>0</meta-value>
</custom-meta>
</custom-meta-group>
</front-stub>
<body>
<p>
<named-content content-type="letter-date">22 Jul 2019</named-content>
</p>
<p>PONE-D-19-18473</p>
<p>Genetic characterization of Angiostrongylus larvae and their natural intermediate host, Achatina fulica, in Thailand</p>
<p>PLOS ONE</p>
<p>Dear Dr. Vitta,</p>
<p>Thank you for submitting your manuscript to PLOS ONE. After careful consideration, we feel that it has merit but does not fully meet PLOS ONE&#8217;s publication criteria as it currently stands. Therefore, we invite you to submit a revised version of the manuscript that addresses the points raised during the review process.</p>
<p>==============================</p>
<p>The MS brings informative results of the distribution of Angiostrongylus and the snail intermediate host in Thailand.</p>
<p>The comments and suggestions of the reviewers were complementary and&#160;the authors should address all the items suggested if possible.&#160;&#160;&#160; &#160;</p>
<p>Improvement on the text&#160;is necessary. Organizing&#160;better the&#160;ideas, specially in the discussion.&#160;The methodology should be written in a more concise manner. The map presented as a supplementary material could be a figure in the article,&#160;with data of snails/haplotypes and Angiostrongylus/haplotypes. Also in the discussion, the correlation of haplotype and final hosts (human infection if possible) would be an interesting and informative point in this MS.</p>
<p>We would appreciate receiving your revised manuscript by Sep 05 2019 11:59PM. When you are ready to submit your revision, log on to <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://www.editorialmanager.com/pone/" ns0:type="simple">https://www.editorialmanager.com/pone/</ext-link> and select the 'Submissions Needing Revision' folder to locate your manuscript file.</p>
<p>If you would like to make changes to your financial disclosure, please include your updated statement in your cover letter.</p>
<p>To enhance the reproducibility of your results, we recommend that if applicable you deposit your laboratory protocols in protocols.io, where a protocol can be assigned its own identifier (DOI) such that it can be cited independently in the future. For instructions see: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://journals.plos.org/plosone/s/submission-guidelines#loc-laboratory-protocols" ns0:type="simple">http://journals.plos.org/plosone/s/submission-guidelines#loc-laboratory-protocols</ext-link></p>
<p>Please include the following items when submitting your revised manuscript:</p>
<p><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>A rebuttal letter that responds to each point raised by the academic editor and reviewer(s). This letter should be uploaded as separate file and labeled 'Response to Reviewers'.</p></list-item><list-item><p>A marked-up copy of your manuscript that highlights changes made to the original version. This file should be uploaded as separate file and labeled 'Revised Manuscript with Track Changes'.</p></list-item><list-item><p>An unmarked version of your revised paper without tracked changes. This file should be uploaded as separate file and labeled 'Manuscript'.</p></list-item></list></p>
<p>Please note while forming your response, if your article is accepted, you may have the opportunity to make the peer review history publicly available. The record will include editor decision letters (with reviews) and your responses to reviewer comments. If eligible, we will contact you to opt in or out.</p>
<p>We look forward to receiving your revised manuscript.</p>
<p>Kind regards,</p>
<p>Marcello Otake Sato, Ph.D., D.V.M.</p>
<p>Academic Editor</p>
<p>PLOS ONE</p>
<p>Journal Requirements:</p>
<p>1. When submitting your revision, we need you to address these additional requirements.</p>
<p>Please ensure that your manuscript meets PLOS ONE's style requirements, including those for file naming. The PLOS ONE style templates can be found at</p>
<p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://www.journals.plos.org/plosone/s/file?id=wjVg/PLOSOne_formatting_sample_main_body.pdf" ns0:type="simple">http://www.journals.plos.org/plosone/s/file?id=wjVg/PLOSOne_formatting_sample_main_body.pdf</ext-link> and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://www.journals.plos.org/plosone/s/file?id=ba62/PLOSOne_formatting_sample_title_authors_affiliations.pdf" ns0:type="simple">http://www.journals.plos.org/plosone/s/file?id=ba62/PLOSOne_formatting_sample_title_authors_affiliations.pdf</ext-link></p>
<p>2. In your Methods section, please provide additional information regarding the permits you obtained for the work. Please ensure you have included the full name of the authority that approved the field site access and, if no permits were required, a brief statement explaining why.</p>
<p>Additional Editor Comments:</p>
<p>The MS brings informative results of the distribution of Angiostrongylus and the snail intermediate host in Thailand. However, improvement on the text is necessary. The methodology should be written in a more concise manner. The map presented as a supplementary material could be a figure with data of snails/haplotypes and Angiostrongylus/haplotypes. Also in the discussion, the correlation of haplotype and human infection (if possible) would be an interesting and informative point in this MS.</p>
<p>[Note: HTML markup is below. Please do not edit.]</p>
<p>Reviewers' comments:</p>
<p>Reviewer's Responses to Questions</p>
<p><bold>Comments to the Author</bold></p>
<p>1. Is the manuscript technically sound, and do the data support the conclusions?</p>
<p>The manuscript must describe a technically sound piece of scientific research with data that supports the conclusions. Experiments must have been conducted rigorously, with appropriate controls, replication, and sample sizes. The conclusions must be drawn appropriately based on the data presented. </p>
<p>Reviewer #1: Yes</p>
<p>Reviewer #2: Yes</p>
<p>**********</p>
<p>2. Has the statistical analysis been performed appropriately and rigorously? </p>
<p>Reviewer #1: I Don't Know</p>
<p>Reviewer #2: N/A</p>
<p>**********</p>
<p>3. Have the authors made all data underlying the findings in their manuscript fully available?</p>
<p>The <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://www.plosone.org/static/policies.action#sharing" ns0:type="simple">PLOS Data policy</ext-link> requires authors to make all data underlying the findings described in their manuscript fully available without restriction, with rare exception (please refer to the Data Availability Statement in the manuscript PDF file). The data should be provided as part of the manuscript or its supporting information, or deposited to a public repository. For example, in addition to summary statistics, the data points behind means, medians and variance measures should be available. If there are restrictions on publicly sharing data&#8212;e.g. participant privacy or use of data from a third party&#8212;those must be specified.</p>
<p>Reviewer #1: No</p>
<p>Reviewer #2: Yes</p>
<p>**********</p>
<p>4. Is the manuscript presented in an intelligible fashion and written in standard English?</p>
<p>PLOS ONE does not copyedit accepted manuscripts, so the language in submitted articles must be clear, correct, and unambiguous. Any typographical or grammatical errors should be corrected at revision, so please note any specific errors here.</p>
<p>Reviewer #1: Yes</p>
<p>Reviewer #2: Yes</p>
<p>**********</p>
<p>5. Review Comments to the Author</p>
<p>Please use the space provided to explain your answers to the questions above. You may also include additional comments for the author, including concerns about dual publication, research ethics, or publication ethics. (Please upload your review as an attachment if it exceeds 20,000 characters)</p>
<p>Reviewer #1: PONE-D-19-18473</p>
<p>This is a very nice set of data, with genetic studies of Angiostrongylus and its intermediate host in a wide an important endemic area.</p>
<p>The title: what do authors mean by &#8220;natural&#8221;? I can think of two meanings: &#8220;that can be found naturally infected&#8221; and &#8220;well-adapted&#8221;. I suggest to remove this word from the title since it does not add any fundamental information besides the main objective.</p>
<p>Line 73: As commented above, I see no reason to include &#8220;in nature&#8221;.</p>
<p>Line 84- Sure that genetic studies are fundamental, but the linkage between this study and &#8220;disease control&#8221; or specifically angiostrongyliasis control is not clear. Perhaps authors may re-write or clarify.</p>
<p>Line 100- &#8220;&#8230;an invasive land snail..&#8221; is not needed here as this was just addressed in the previous section.</p>
<p>Tables- formatting shall be revised according to PLoS One instructions.</p>
<p>Figures- They also need improvement for better quality.</p>
<p>Figure 1- the map of Thailand showing places where collection was performed. A much nicer presentation would be the indication of collection places with dots corresponding to exact geographic coordinates (geo-referencing). This shall be the informative mode of presenting geographic occurrence data, since just painting the geographic area of province is less informative.</p>
<p>Results- one very important information is the distribution of individual larvae counts. I strongly suggest authors to provide this information ina suppplementary file or to add it in manuscript and explore it. It gives a very nice opportunity to discuss the degree of parasite-host adaptation. It also enriches the contribution of this nice work.</p>
<p>Reviewer #2: Comment to MS: MS. No. PONE-D-19-18473 Genetic characterization of Angiostrongylus larvae and their natural intermediate host, Achatina fulica, in Thailand</p>
<p>This study revealed genetic diversity of Angiostrongylus larvae and Achatina fulica, natural intermediate host. New findings of A. fulica haplotypes were found (AF1 and AF2) based on sequencing of the COI gene. Two new additional cytb haplotypes of A. cantonensis (AC19 and AC20) were also identified in this study. Scientific sound is good. Manuscript is well written. This is useful for more understanding of system study to explore the epidemiology of Angiostrongylus spp. and Achatina fulica intermediate host.</p>
<p>Specific comment:</p>
<p>For ensure phylogenetic analysis, in addition to using the maximum-likelihood (ML) method in Phylogenetic analysis of Figures 1, 2 and 3, the authors should also use other methods such as (Bayesian analyses (BI) maximum-parsimony (MP) and neighbour-joining (NJ) analyses implemented as reported by as Ref 9: Rodpai R, Intapan PM, Thanchomnang T, Sanpool O, Sadaow L, Laymanivong S, et al. Angiostrongylus cantonensis and A. malaysiensis Broadly Overlap in Thailand, Lao PDR, Cambodia and Myanmar: A Molecular Survey of Larvae in Land Snails. PLoS One. 2016;11(8): e0161128. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.016112" ns0:type="simple">https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.016112</ext-link>.</p>
<p>**********</p>
<p>6. PLOS authors have the option to publish the peer review history of their article (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://journals.plos.org/plosone/s/editorial-and-peer-review-process#loc-peer-review-history" ns0:type="simple">what does this mean?</ext-link>). If published, this will include your full peer review and any attached files.</p>
<p>If you choose &#8220;no&#8221;, your identity will remain anonymous but your review may still be made public.</p>
<p><bold>Do you want your identity to be public for this peer review?</bold> For information about this choice, including consent withdrawal, please see our <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://www.plos.org/privacy-policy" ns0:type="simple">Privacy Policy</ext-link>.</p>
<p>Reviewer #1: Yes: Carlos Graeff-Teixeira</p>
<p>Reviewer #2: No</p>
<p>[NOTE: If reviewer comments were submitted as an attachment file, they will be attached to this email and accessible via the submission site. Please log into your account, locate the manuscript record, and check for the action link "View Attachments". If this link does not appear, there are no attachment files to be viewed.]</p>
<p>While revising your submission, please upload your figure files to the Preflight Analysis and Conversion Engine (PACE) digital diagnostic tool, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://pacev2.apexcovantage.com/" ns0:type="simple">https://pacev2.apexcovantage.com/</ext-link>. PACE helps ensure that figures meet PLOS requirements. To use PACE, you must first register as a user. Registration is free. Then, login and navigate to the UPLOAD tab, where you will find detailed instructions on how to use the tool. If you encounter any issues or have any questions when using PACE, please email us at <email ns0:type="simple">figures@plos.org</email>. Please note that Supporting Information files do not need this step.</p>
</body>
</sub-article>
