<sub-article xmlns:ns0="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="aggregated-review-documents" id="pone.0220839.r001" specific-use="decision-letter">
<front-stub>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0220839.r001</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title>Decision Letter 0</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Lebarbenchon</surname>
<given-names>Camille</given-names>
</name>
<role>Academic Editor</role>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<permissions>
<copyright-year>2019</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>Camille Lebarbenchon</copyright-holder>
<license ns0:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
<license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" ns0:type="simple">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<related-object document-id="10.1371/journal.pone.0220839" document-id-type="doi" document-type="article" id="rel-obj001" link-type="peer-reviewed-article" />
<custom-meta-group>
<custom-meta>
<meta-name>Submission Version</meta-name>
<meta-value>0</meta-value>
</custom-meta>
</custom-meta-group>
</front-stub>
<body>
<p>
<named-content content-type="letter-date">11 Jul 2019</named-content>
</p>
<p>PONE-D-19-16454</p>
<p>Winter habitats of bats in Texas</p>
<p>PLOS ONE</p>
<p>Dear Ms. Meierhofer,</p>
<p>Thank you for submitting your manuscript to PLOS ONE. After careful consideration, we feel that it has merit but does not fully meet PLOS ONE&#8217;s publication criteria as it currently stands. Therefore, we invite you to submit a revised version of the manuscript that addresses the points raised during the review process.</p>
<p>We would appreciate receiving your revised manuscript by Aug 25 2019 11:59PM. When you are ready to submit your revision, log on to <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://www.editorialmanager.com/pone/" ns0:type="simple">https://www.editorialmanager.com/pone/</ext-link> and select the 'Submissions Needing Revision' folder to locate your manuscript file.</p>
<p>If you would like to make changes to your financial disclosure, please include your updated statement in your cover letter.</p>
<p>To enhance the reproducibility of your results, we recommend that if applicable you deposit your laboratory protocols in protocols.io, where a protocol can be assigned its own identifier (DOI) such that it can be cited independently in the future. For instructions see: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://journals.plos.org/plosone/s/submission-guidelines#loc-laboratory-protocols" ns0:type="simple">http://journals.plos.org/plosone/s/submission-guidelines#loc-laboratory-protocols</ext-link></p>
<p>Please include the following items when submitting your revised manuscript:</p>
<p><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>A rebuttal letter that responds to each point raised by the academic editor and reviewer(s). This letter should be uploaded as separate file and labeled 'Response to Reviewers'.</p></list-item><list-item><p>A marked-up copy of your manuscript that highlights changes made to the original version. This file should be uploaded as separate file and labeled 'Revised Manuscript with Track Changes'.</p></list-item><list-item><p>An unmarked version of your revised paper without tracked changes. This file should be uploaded as separate file and labeled 'Manuscript'.</p></list-item></list></p>
<p>Please note while forming your response, if your article is accepted, you may have the opportunity to make the peer review history publicly available. The record will include editor decision letters (with reviews) and your responses to reviewer comments. If eligible, we will contact you to opt in or out.</p>
<p>We look forward to receiving your revised manuscript.</p>
<p>Kind regards,</p>
<p>Camille Lebarbenchon</p>
<p>Academic Editor</p>
<p>PLOS ONE</p>
<p>Journal Requirements:</p>
<p>1. When submitting your revision, we need you to address these additional requirements.</p>
<p>Please ensure that your manuscript meets PLOS ONE's style requirements, including those for file naming. The PLOS ONE style templates can be found at</p>
<p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://www.journals.plos.org/plosone/s/file?id=wjVg/PLOSOne_formatting_sample_main_body.pdf" ns0:type="simple">http://www.journals.plos.org/plosone/s/file?id=wjVg/PLOSOne_formatting_sample_main_body.pdf</ext-link> and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://www.journals.plos.org/plosone/s/file?id=ba62/PLOSOne_formatting_sample_title_authors_affiliations.pdf" ns0:type="simple">http://www.journals.plos.org/plosone/s/file?id=ba62/PLOSOne_formatting_sample_title_authors_affiliations.pdf</ext-link></p>
<p>2. We note that you have stated that you will provide repository information for your data at acceptance. Should your manuscript be accepted for publication, we will hold it until you provide the relevant accession numbers or DOIs necessary to access your data. If you wish to make changes to your Data Availability statement, please describe these changes in your cover letter and we will update your Data Availability statement to reflect the information you provide.</p>
<p>[Note: HTML markup is below. Please do not edit.]</p>
<p>Reviewers' comments:</p>
<p>Reviewer's Responses to Questions</p>
<p><bold>Comments to the Author</bold></p>
<p>1. Is the manuscript technically sound, and do the data support the conclusions?</p>
<p>The manuscript must describe a technically sound piece of scientific research with data that supports the conclusions. Experiments must have been conducted rigorously, with appropriate controls, replication, and sample sizes. The conclusions must be drawn appropriately based on the data presented. </p>
<p>Reviewer #1: Yes</p>
<p>Reviewer #2: Yes</p>
<p>**********</p>
<p>2. Has the statistical analysis been performed appropriately and rigorously? </p>
<p>Reviewer #1: Yes</p>
<p>Reviewer #2: Yes</p>
<p>**********</p>
<p>3. Have the authors made all data underlying the findings in their manuscript fully available?</p>
<p>The <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://www.plosone.org/static/policies.action#sharing" ns0:type="simple">PLOS Data policy</ext-link> requires authors to make all data underlying the findings described in their manuscript fully available without restriction, with rare exception (please refer to the Data Availability Statement in the manuscript PDF file). The data should be provided as part of the manuscript or its supporting information, or deposited to a public repository. For example, in addition to summary statistics, the data points behind means, medians and variance measures should be available. If there are restrictions on publicly sharing data&#8212;e.g. participant privacy or use of data from a third party&#8212;those must be specified.</p>
<p>Reviewer #1: Yes</p>
<p>Reviewer #2: Yes</p>
<p>**********</p>
<p>4. Is the manuscript presented in an intelligible fashion and written in standard English?</p>
<p>PLOS ONE does not copyedit accepted manuscripts, so the language in submitted articles must be clear, correct, and unambiguous. Any typographical or grammatical errors should be corrected at revision, so please note any specific errors here.</p>
<p>Reviewer #1: Yes</p>
<p>Reviewer #2: Yes</p>
<p>**********</p>
<p>5. Review Comments to the Author</p>
<p>Please use the space provided to explain your answers to the questions above. You may also include additional comments for the author, including concerns about dual publication, research ethics, or publication ethics. (Please upload your review as an attachment if it exceeds 20,000 characters)</p>
<p>Reviewer #1: The manuscript &#8220;Winter habitats of bats in Texas&#8221; describes hibernaculum microclimate of locations selected by bat species in the southern United States. More specifically, the authors were interested in determining the suitability of winter bat habitats in regards to white-nose syndrome. The authors determined that most of the hibernacula remained in the optimal range of fungal growth, and that skin temperatures and microclimates selected varied among species and differed from other populations within different regions. This work is especially important as the fungus that causes white-nose syndrome continues to spread into areas where we are lacking information about hibernation physiology of novel species and the microclimate conditions they chose. Data such as these will be useful in predicting the impacts of the disease as it impacts novel species.</p>
<p>There are a few issues that I think will improve the quality of the manuscript outlined here:</p>
<p>&#8226; Just a personal preference, but there are a lot of abbreviations with &#8220;T&#8221; (Tr, Ts etc). Either note the abbreviation with more detail (Tskin) or spell the temperature out.</p>
<p>&#8226; There were inconsistences in using abbreviations versus text throughout the manuscript. Either stick with abbreviations or text.</p>
<p>&#8226; It may make sense to change absolute water vapor pressure to water vapor deficit (saturation pressure &#8211; absolute pressure), which would allow the authors to compare conditions across temperature.</p>
<p>&#8226; Lines 77- 78: The sentence is incomplete</p>
<p>&#8226; Lines 114-125: These are really predictions, not hypotheses</p>
<p>&#8226; Line 158: change &#8220;enumerated&#8221; to &#8220;counted&#8221;</p>
<p>&#8226; Lines 160-165: Where within the hibernacula were the loggers placed? The distance within the hibernacula would change the temperature. Additionally, how close were the measurements from PRISM to the hibernacula? And were bats located near where the dataloggers were placed?</p>
<p>&#8226; Line 385: EWL has not been defined yet</p>
<p>&#8226; Figure 2: explain what r180 represents in the Figure caption.</p>
<p>&#8226; Figure 3: perhaps order by group to make visual comparisons easier</p>
<p>&#8226; Figure 3C: switch to water vapor deficit to make comparisons easier</p>
<p>Reviewer #2: This study describes the temperature of bats and their roosts during hibernation in Texas. They analyze variation between bat species, ecoregions, and roost type. The results are discussed in relation to the potential infection with the fungus P. destructans, which has not affected bats in Texas yet. Based on their temperature data, the authors make conclusions about which bat species will develop or not WNS.</p>
<p>I enjoyed reading this manuscript. The introduction is well written and the statistical tests particularly well described. Therefore, I only have few comments, detailed below:</p>
<p>1) Introduction, lines 114-118: why these 3 bat species would select higher temperatures? Please explain your hypothesis.</p>
<p>2) Figure 1: It might be good to have a more detailed map showing the temperatures across Texas (annual mean, or for winter only). I also suggest adding information on bat species sampled in each site to give a better idea of their range. I understand that some regions were not sampled (e.g. High Plains, Southern Texas Plains): maybe not necessary to show this information in the map.</p>
<p>3) In the methods, the authors explain that they counted bats during their visits. Did they test if the number of bats in the hibernacula affects (increases) the roost temperature?</p>
<p>4) What was the target surface measured with the digital thermometer? Did the authors observe variation of temperature across the body of torpid bats? Did they point the all bat body, or only a part (back, head, ears)? I suggest to add these details for Tskin measurements.</p>
<p>Minor edits:</p>
<p>5) Line 77 : &#171; leading to dehydration and &#187; ? Please rephrase.</p>
<p>6) Line 190 : &#8220;for each species avoid pseudoreplication&#8221;. Please rephrase.</p>
<p>7) Line 191 : Please correct : &#8220;used Pearson&#8217;s product-moment correlations&#8221;.</p>
<p>8) Line 312 : Please rephrase &#8220;&#8230;temperatures, however, and the four hibernacula&#8230;&#8221;.</p>
<p>9) Line 315: Please correct &#8220;Temperatures within each (?) varied&#8230;&#8221;.</p>
<p>10) Line 345 : Please correct &#8220;the average temperature&#8221;.</p>
<p>11) Line 349 : Please correct &#8220;suggests&#8221;.</p>
<p>**********</p>
<p>6. PLOS authors have the option to publish the peer review history of their article (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://journals.plos.org/plosone/s/editorial-and-peer-review-process#loc-peer-review-history" ns0:type="simple">what does this mean?</ext-link>). If published, this will include your full peer review and any attached files.</p>
<p>If you choose &#8220;no&#8221;, your identity will remain anonymous but your review may still be made public.</p>
<p><bold>Do you want your identity to be public for this peer review?</bold> For information about this choice, including consent withdrawal, please see our <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://www.plos.org/privacy-policy" ns0:type="simple">Privacy Policy</ext-link>.</p>
<p>Reviewer #1: No</p>
<p>Reviewer #2: No</p>
<p>[NOTE: If reviewer comments were submitted as an attachment file, they will be attached to this email and accessible via the submission site. Please log into your account, locate the manuscript record, and check for the action link "View Attachments". If this link does not appear, there are no attachment files to be viewed.]</p>
<p>While revising your submission, please upload your figure files to the Preflight Analysis and Conversion Engine (PACE) digital diagnostic tool, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://pacev2.apexcovantage.com/" ns0:type="simple">https://pacev2.apexcovantage.com/</ext-link>. PACE helps ensure that figures meet PLOS requirements. To use PACE, you must first register as a user. Registration is free. Then, login and navigate to the UPLOAD tab, where you will find detailed instructions on how to use the tool. If you encounter any issues or have any questions when using PACE, please email us at <email ns0:type="simple">figures@plos.org</email>. Please note that Supporting Information files do not need this step.</p>
</body>
</sub-article>
