<sub-article xmlns:ns0="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="author-comment" id="pone.0223097.r002">
<front-stub>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0223097.r002</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title>Author response to Decision Letter 0</article-title>
</title-group>
<related-object document-id="10.1371/journal.pone.0223097" document-id-type="doi" document-type="peer-reviewed-article" id="rel-obj002" link-type="rebutted-decision-letter" object-id="10.1371/journal.pone.0223097.r001" object-id-type="doi" object-type="decision-letter" />
<custom-meta-group>
<custom-meta>
<meta-name>Submission Version</meta-name>
<meta-value>1</meta-value>
</custom-meta>
</custom-meta-group>
</front-stub>
<body>
<p>
<named-content content-type="author-response-date">8 Aug 2019</named-content>
</p>
<p>PONE-D-19-17515</p>
<p>Validating a Popular Outpatient Antibiotic Database</p>
<p>PLOS ONE</p>
<p>Dear Dr. Conly,</p>
<p>Thank you for the thoughtful review and helpful comments. We have incorporated all comments where possible and feel this has greatly improved the manuscript. We would like to be considered for the call for antimicrobial resistance papers. </p>
<p>The data for this study is not publically available. The data set from this study is held securely in coded form at ICES. While data sharing agreements prohibit ICES from making the data set publicly available, access may be granted to those who meet pre-specified criteria for confidential access, available at www.ices.on.ca/DAS. The full data set creation plan and underlying analytic code are available from the authors upon request, understanding that the programs may rely upon coding templates or macros that are unique to ICES. The IQVIA Xponent dataset is owned and proprietary by IQVIA. The contract between PHO and IQVIA does not permit us to share the data publically. The authors had no special access privileges and other researchers may purchase the data from IQVIA directly (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://www.iqvia.com" ns0:type="simple">www.iqvia.com</ext-link>). </p>
<p>Sincerely,</p>
<p>Kevin Schwartz</p>
<p>On behalf of the co-authors</p>
<p>&#8195;</p>
<p>==============================</p>
<p>ACADEMIC EDITOR: </p>
<p>Overall this manuscript addresses an important topic and has used a robust methodology and chose to use Bland Altman plots which was an excellent choice. However there are certain issues to address to improve the manuscript.</p>
<p>Please respond to all the peer reviewer comments . In addition please respond to the following Academic Editor 's comments</p>
<p>1.Reviewer 2 noted 2 previous citations presented in poster format that did comparisons from 2 Canadian provinces which had comprehensive data ( all ages)  on outpatient prescriptions and one compared the data from the Xponent database so the authors need to rephrase their comments " to our knowledge community antibiotic use data has neve been externally validated.." which appears in a couple of settings in the manuscript.</p>
<p>Response: Reference to this being the first validation study has been removed</p>
<p>2. You mention about a variety of prescription drug databases in the Introduction. Please add a couple of sentences to describe the commonly used ones and their differences eg Compuscript, the Canadian Disease and Therapeutic Index ,  National Prescription Audit  data and National Sales and Prescriptions data for the benefit of the readership.</p>
<p>Response: The following sentences have been added to line 53: &#8220;Various forms of antibiotic use data are available including dispensing data compiled by pharmacies (e.g. National Prescription Audit&#174; Compuscript&#174; or GPM&#174;)[7] or funders (e.g. Ontario Drug Benefit)[8] which can be population based. Other databases include dispensed data at the prescriber level (e.g. Xponent&#174;) [9] or by prescription from electronic medical records.[10] These data sources have important differences and may not correlate over time. [11,12]&#8221;</p>
<p>3. Provide an estimate of NIHB prescriptions that may have been missed .</p>
<p>Response: We do not have precise numbers for this. There are approximately 10,000 registered Indian Status seniors living in Ontario according to StatsCan (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://www12.statcan.gc.ca/nhs-enm/2011/as-sa/99-011-x/99-011-x2011001-eng.cfm" ns0:type="simple">https://www12.statcan.gc.ca/nhs-enm/2011/as-sa/99-011-x/99-011-x2011001-eng.cfm</ext-link>); roughly 2 million Ontario seniors are eligible for ODB. We feel this is unlikely to introduce significant bias at the physician level. We have added this line to the limitations line 257: &#8220;ODB does not fund First Nations populations with Non-insured Health Benefits, however this represents a small proportion of the included patient population.&#8221;</p>
<p>4. Please explicitly explain if the prescriptions from non physician prescribers eg dentists, midwives, podiatrists etc were excluded reliably from the Xponent database which has obvious important implications</p>
<p>Response: Non-physicians are not captured. We added this sentence line 93: &#8220;Non-physician prescribers (i.e. dentists, nurse practitioners, optometrists, etc.) are not included in this database.&#8221;</p>
<p>5. Please describe the geographic pharmacy difference if possible and what implications it may have</p>
<p>Response: We do not have granular data on the included and not included pharmacies from IQVIA. They will not share specific information but do admit that rural and smaller independent pharmacies are less likely to be included. This is reflected in the discussion line 221: &#8220;However, we identified an important limitation in the data with larger errors noted for physicians practicing in rural locations. This is most likely a reflection of a greater reliance on IQVIA&#8217;s projection algorithm as they collect less prescription data directly from pharmacies in rural locations.&#8221;</p>
<p>6. The Discussion is missing a limitations paragraph and there are several important ones - some mentioned earlier in the manuscript  but should be highlighted plus other mentioned about the limitations of the Xponenet database, non captured scripts eg NIHB, other prescribers, missing data and its influence and impact of a sensitivity analysis of &gt; 14 days use as opposed to 8 .</p>
<p>Response: The penultimate discussion paragraph has been edited to reflect the study's limitations (Line 247)</p>
<p>7. There are several typos that need to be fixed eg refs 7-35 , presume it is 7, 35, missing words in some of the sentences</p>
<p>Response: We have corrected all identified typos</p>
<p>8. The references are very sloppy and full of errors ( too numerous to count )  in case, non use of urls and date of access, inappropriate case, spacing, non use of italics for Latin terms , incomplete references, missing references, inappropriate journal abbreviations and appear not to have been proof read by the authors very carefully . Please clean up ALL errors in the references.</p>
<p>Response: Referencing formatting have been corrected to PLOS one standards and all errors have been corrected.</p>
<p>Journal Requirements:</p>
<p>1. When submitting your revision, we need you to address these additional requirements.</p>
<p>Please ensure that your manuscript meets PLOS ONE's style requirements, including those for file naming. The PLOS ONE style templates can be found at</p>
<p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://www.journals.plos.org/plosone/s/file?id=wjVg/PLOSOne_formatting_sample_main_body.pdf" ns0:type="simple">http://www.journals.plos.org/plosone/s/file?id=wjVg/PLOSOne_formatting_sample_main_body.pdf</ext-link> and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://www.journals.plos.org/plosone/s/file?id=ba62/PLOSOne_formatting_sample_title_authors_affiliations.pdf" ns0:type="simple">http://www.journals.plos.org/plosone/s/file?id=ba62/PLOSOne_formatting_sample_title_authors_affiliations.pdf</ext-link></p>
<p>Response: Manuscript modified to conform to these requirements</p>
<p>2. Please include captions for your Supporting Information files at the end of your manuscript, and update any in-text citations to match accordingly. Please see our Supporting Information guidelines for more information: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://journals.plos.org/plosone/s/supporting-information" ns0:type="simple">http://journals.plos.org/plosone/s/supporting-information</ext-link>.</p>
<p>Response: Done</p>
<p>3. Our internal editors have looked over your manuscript and determined that it is within the scope of our Antimicrobial Resistance call for papers. This collection of papers is headed by a team of Guest Editors for PLOS ONE: Kathryn Holt (Monash University and London School of Hygiene and Tropical Medicine), Alison H. Holmes (Imperial College London), Alessandro Cassini (WHO Infection Prevention and Control Global Unit), Jaap A. Wagenaar (Utrecht University). The Collection will encompass a diverse range of research articles; additional information can be found on our announcement page: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://collections.plos.org/s/antimicrobial-resistance" ns0:type="simple">https://collections.plos.org/s/antimicrobial-resistance</ext-link>. If you would like your manuscript to be considered for this collection, please let us know in your cover letter and we will ensure that your paper is treated as if you were responding to this call. If you would prefer to remove your manuscript from collection consideration, please specify this in the cover letter.</p>
<p>Response: We would like to be considered for the collection, and have added to the cover letter above.</p>
<p>3. We note that you have indicated that data from this study are available upon request. PLOS only allows data to be available upon request if there are legal or ethical restrictions on sharing data publicly. For information on unacceptable data access restrictions, please see <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://journals.plos.org/plosone/s/data-availability#loc-unacceptable-data-access-restrictions" ns0:type="simple">http://journals.plos.org/plosone/s/data-availability#loc-unacceptable-data-access-restrictions</ext-link>.</p>
<p>In your revised cover letter, please address the following prompts:</p>
<p>a) If there are ethical or legal restrictions on sharing a de-identified data set, please explain them in detail (e.g., data contain potentially identifying or sensitive patient information) and who has imposed them (e.g., an ethics committee). Please also provide contact information for a data access committee, ethics committee, or other institutional body to which data requests may be sent.</p>
<p>b) If there are no restrictions, please upload the minimal anonymized data set necessary to replicate your study findings as either Supporting Information files or to a stable, public repository and provide us with the relevant URLs, DOIs, or accession numbers. Please see <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://www.bmj.com/content/340/bmj.c181.long" ns0:type="simple">http://www.bmj.com/content/340/bmj.c181.long</ext-link> for guidelines on how to de-identify and prepare clinical data for publication. For a list of acceptable repositories, please see <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://journals.plos.org/plosone/s/data-availability#loc-recommended-repositories" ns0:type="simple">http://journals.plos.org/plosone/s/data-availability#loc-recommended-repositories</ext-link>.</p>
<p>We will update your Data Availability statement on your behalf to reflect the information you provide.</p>
<p>Response: We apologize for any confusion but ICES data and IQVIA data cannot be shared publically. We have provided the explanations in the cover letter above.</p>
<p>4. Thank you for stating the following in the Acknowledgments Section of your manuscript:</p>
<p>This study was funded by Public Health Ontario</p>
<p>We note that you have provided funding information that is not currently declared in your Funding Statement. However, funding information should not appear in the Acknowledgments section or other areas of your manuscript. We will only publish funding information present in the Funding Statement section of the online submission form.</p>
<p>Please remove any funding-related text from the manuscript and let us know how you would like to update your Funding Statement. Currently, your Funding Statement reads as follows:</p>
<p>The authors received no specific funding for this work</p>
<p>Response: Please change to: This study was funded by Public Health Ontario. We have removed this line from the manuscript </p>
<p>[Note: HTML markup is below. Please do not edit.]</p>
<p>Reviewers' comments:</p>
<p>Reviewer's Responses to Questions</p>
<p>Comments to the Author</p>
<p>1. Is the manuscript technically sound, and do the data support the conclusions?</p>
<p>The manuscript must describe a technically sound piece of scientific research with data that supports the conclusions. Experiments must have been conducted rigorously, with appropriate controls, replication, and sample sizes. The conclusions must be drawn appropriately based on the data presented. </p>
<p>Reviewer #1: Yes</p>
<p>Reviewer #2: Yes</p>
<p>________________________________________</p>
<p>2. Has the statistical analysis been performed appropriately and rigorously? </p>
<p>Reviewer #1: Yes</p>
<p>Reviewer #2: Yes</p>
<p>________________________________________</p>
<p>3. Have the authors made all data underlying the findings in their manuscript fully available?</p>
<p>The PLOS Data policy requires authors to make all data underlying the findings described in their manuscript fully available without restriction, with rare exception (please refer to the Data Availability Statement in the manuscript PDF file). The data should be provided as part of the manuscript or its supporting information, or deposited to a public repository. For example, in addition to summary statistics, the data points behind means, medians and variance measures should be available. If there are restrictions on publicly sharing data&#8212;e.g. participant privacy or use of data from a third party&#8212;those must be specified.</p>
<p>Reviewer #1: Yes</p>
<p>Reviewer #2: No</p>
<p>Response: Please see cover letter above for the explanation</p>
<p>________________________________________</p>
<p>4. Is the manuscript presented in an intelligible fashion and written in standard English?</p>
<p>PLOS ONE does not copyedit accepted manuscripts, so the language in submitted articles must be clear, correct, and unambiguous. Any typographical or grammatical errors should be corrected at revision, so please note any specific errors here.</p>
<p>Reviewer #1: Yes</p>
<p>Reviewer #2: Yes</p>
<p>________________________________________</p>
<p>5. Review Comments to the Author</p>
<p>Please use the space provided to explain your answers to the questions above. You may also include additional comments for the author, including concerns about dual publication, research ethics, or publication ethics. (Please upload your review as an attachment if it exceeds 20,000 characters)</p>
<p>Reviewer #1: Overall, this is a well written paper on a topic of considerable importance. Recognizing the need for reliable outpatient antibiotic utilization data, this study attempts to validate a pre-existing database that can be used to optimize outpatient antimicrobial stewardship. The study limitations were well recognized and stated clearly [ie. insufficient correlation between specific antibiotics and inability to validate for a) patients &lt;65 years old, b) refill prescriptions]. The study also identified a weakness in the database with respect to the rural population which was well explained. The article's greatest strength is its rigorous statistical analyses.</p>
<p>A few additional comments for author response are:</p>
<p>1. With a NPV of 73%, 23% of prescribers were classified as belonging to the highest quartile of antibiotic prescribing when really they belonged to the top 40% according to OBD (the gold standard database). From an antimicrobial stewardship perspective, this discrepancy is acceptable because it still represents a physician group that should be targeted for further stewardship education and optimization of antibiotic use. However, from a clinician's perspective, being labeled as within the top 25% is very different from top 40%, the former signalling higher end of normal and the latter potentially being close to the mean. This NPV may not be acceptable to a clinician receiving their antibiotic prescribing summary.</p>
<p>Response: Thank for this comment. We have added this line to the limitations paragraph line 247): &#8220;While we demonstrated that the misclassification of prescribers in the top 25th percentile was small, this error may be important to clinicians receiving feedback on their prescribing.&#8221;</p>
<p>2. Given a large subset of physicians are likely not represented (eg. rural physician etc), it would be interesting to see how many registered physicians within Ontario are excluded from the Xponent database entirely and therefore would not be subject to antibiotic utilization scrutiny. Is it possible to match the physicians to the College of Physicians and Surgeons of Ontario to obtain this number?</p>
<p>Response: We cannot be certain if some physicians are not captured as we did not obtain all physicians in the province, only those that prescribed 1+ antibiotics in the time period. We did use CPSO numbers as the link between databases. Our linkage success rate was 97%. We clarified in line 168 that we used CPSO numbers: &#8220;The Xponent database had 25,678 unique physicians and 24,878 (97%) were successfully linked to ODB at ICES using College of Physicians and Surgeons identifiers.&#8221;</p>
<p>3. The authors performed multiple separate analyses for female vs. male genders and demonstrated that there were was a slightly greater relative difference in prescribing for male patients. Nevertheless, the discussions section lacked explanations on the potential reasons and significance of this finding. This should be further elaborated on.</p>
<p>Response: Thank you for this comment. For the most part we found the analysis for male and female patients to be similar. However there did appear to be a difference in validity between male and female patients in rural areas. Reasons for this are unclear and we have added this line to the discussion (line 224): &#8220;This error was slightly more pronounced in female patients. Further exploration for the differences between male and female patients may be warranted.&#8221;</p>
<p>4. The antibiotic prescribing rate "antibiotic prescriptions/100 total prescriptions" is an interesting metric. It is conceivable that a clinician whom is prescribing antibiotics excessively would likely prescribe other drugs excessively as well thereby obscuring the increased antibiotic use. It was reassuring to see that "antibiotic prescriptions/100 total prescriptions" correlated well with "antibiotic prescriptions / 100 patient visits" given the denominator for antibiotic utilization is typically patient visits to take into account differences in patient volume. It is not clear to me where the patient visit denominator is coming from (is it from OBD or an alternate source) and could these not just be incorporated into the numerator generated from Xponent rather than relying on the "antibiotic prescriptions/100 total prescriptions".</p>
<p>Response: Outpatient visits were obtained from the OHIP database. We have clarified this in the methods line 119. To do this comparison we linked IQVIA data to ICES. We feel it adds value to leave the prescriptions per 100 total prescription variable as some jurisdictions may not have the capacity to link to administrative data, and even for those that do it adds a layer of complexity. We completely agree with your analysis of the potential limitations of this variable and the implications for it from our study.</p>
<p>Reviewer #2: This topic is of great interest to likely a small group of individuals. IQVIA formerly Brogan, formerly IMS has recorded data on antimicrobial and other drug utilization from retail pharmacies for many years. The validity of the methods to extrapolate from the sample of pharmacies to the whole population has never been public and therefore the science community has been left to wonder how well their proprietary methods work and can they be trusted for research. In addition to the cited work of Tan (reference 42), two other groups in Canada have completed similar work in conference papers and could be cited (Dalton, B; Sabuda D, Bresee L et al. External Validation of Estimates of Antibacterial Dispensing in the IMS Brogan Xponent&#174; Database in a Canadian Province. IDWeek 2013 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://idsa.confex.com/idsa/2013/webprogram/Paper41244.html" ns0:type="simple">https://idsa.confex.com/idsa/2013/webprogram/Paper41244.html</ext-link>) &amp; Chong M, Dutil L, Bhatia T, Marra F, Patrick DM. Assessing antimicrobial consumption</p>
<p>using two different methodologies in British Columbia. Can J Infect Dis Med Microbiol</p>
<p>2007; 18(1): 35 Abstract A3.</p>
<p>Response: References added to background</p>
<p>In general, the authors have conducted a careful analysis using appropriate methods, and this manuscript is likely deserving of publication. I have a few suggestions to help make small improvements in clarity.</p>
<p>The goal of this study was to reliably predict the top 25 percentile of prescribers of antimicrobials to patients 65 and older, by identifying them in a public database of all pharmacies and comparing to the IQVIA database. I think the authors could do a better job describing this objective in the title as one does not reflexively think that quantification and validation would be performed at a physician level. I think some discussion of how these data would relate to the exponent database derived data on population level antimicrobial utilization would be appropriate (or if not at all, please state) and the conclusion "that the xponent database is validated for patients 65 and older " is actually inaccurate considering the principle finding of validating the identification of high prescibers of antibiotics in a population of 65 and older. "</p>
<p>Response: This point is well taken and correct. We have modified the title to: &#8220;Validating a Popular Outpatient Antibiotic Database to Reliably Identify High Prescribing Physicians&#8221;. We also modified the language in the abstract, objectives, and conclusions to more clearly reflect this (Lines 25, 43, 75, 264)</p>
<p>The definition of physician antibiotic prescribing rate is unclear. Is this based on number of prescriptions, days of therapy or DDD etc.</p>
<p>Response: We have clarified this in the methods line 99: &#8220;number of antibiotic prescriptions/number of total prescriptions by that physician&#8221;</p>
<p>Physicians were excluded for "prescribing less than 9 antibiotics". Does this mean &lt;9 antibiotic prescriptions over the time period? Can you explain this number?</p>
<p>Response: Correct. We have clarified this in line 122 in the methods: &#8220;We excluded physicians who prescribed &lt;9 antibiotics to patients &#8805;65 years of age during the study year in either Xponent or ODB databases. We used this cut off, which removes 5% of all antibiotic prescriptions, in order to exclude infrequent antibiotic prescribers.&#8221;</p>
<p>Could you define "antibiotics" in the study methods better? eg "systemic antibacterials" rather than just referring reader to the supplement.</p>
<p>Response: Modified to (line 96): &#8220;Antibiotics were defined as WHO ATC J01 class antibacterials for systemic use limited to those taken orally and dispensed from an outpatient pharmacy (S1 Table).&#8221;</p>
<p>The methods and results for agreement are confusing. In the methods it is stated the agreement of quartile groupings was evaluated, so one expects results in terms of categorical analysis. However in the text of results and table 3 mean number of of antibiotics prescriptions per physicians is reported.</p>
<p>Response: We have clarified in the methods what was done (line 142). We feel using the mean numbers helps with the clinical meaning of the kappas which are sometimes hard to interpret: &#8220;We descriptively compared the mean number of antibiotics prescribed per physician. Then we used the quartiles and evaluated agreement of the quartile groupings using weighted kappa statistics with 95% CIs for total antibiotics as well as subclasses of antibiotics.&#8221;</p>
<p>The agreement on antibiotic prescribing per 100 prescriptions was assessed by Bland Altman plots. I am unclear of the relevance of antibiotic prescription per 100 prescriptions. This should be discussed in background </p>
<p>and discussion.</p>
<p>Response: We have clarified in the methods line 156: &#8220;IQVIA data does not contain numbers of patient visits. Therefore, we also assessed the correlation of the antibiotic prescribing rate (number of antibiotic prescriptions per 100 of total prescriptions) to number of antibiotic prescriptions per 100 patient visits using Spearman correlation coefficients.&#8221; We have also modified line 242 in the discussion to state: &#8220;We demonstrated that the number of antibiotic prescriptions per 100 total prescriptions is imperfect, but is highly correlated with the number of antibiotic prescriptions per 100 patient visits for primary care physicians in patients 65 years of age or older. This is a potentially useful metric from pharmacy data to indirectly account for differences in patient volume, when patient visits are unavailable.&#8221;</p>
<p>If there are a significant number of non physician prescribers in Ontario, are they captured in ODB and exponent? Even if their prescribing rates are lower than that of physicians, it would be useful to note if agreement is similar with non physicians.</p>
<p>Response: Non-physician prescribers are not captured in either database. We clarified this in the methods (lines 93 and 113) and added this to the limitations line 261. We do not have any data source in Ontario currently that captures non-physicians prescribers. </p>
<p>In figures 5 and S3 one can observe correlation but there appears to be bias with discounting of the xponent values. This is not commented upon. Can the slope of the regression line be provided? It would also provide easier interpretation if the x and y axes were given the same scales and number values.</p>
<p>Response: Figures modified as suggested</p>
</body>
</sub-article>
