<sub-article xmlns:ns0="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="aggregated-review-documents" id="pone.0222580.r001" specific-use="decision-letter">
<front-stub>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0222580.r001</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title>Decision Letter 0</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Bertolini</surname>
<given-names>Francesco</given-names>
</name>
<role>Academic Editor</role>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<permissions>
<copyright-year>2019</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>Francesco Bertolini</copyright-holder>
<license ns0:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
<license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" ns0:type="simple">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<related-object document-id="10.1371/journal.pone.0222580" document-id-type="doi" document-type="article" id="rel-obj001" link-type="peer-reviewed-article" />
<custom-meta-group>
<custom-meta>
<meta-name>Submission Version</meta-name>
<meta-value>0</meta-value>
</custom-meta>
</custom-meta-group>
</front-stub>
<body>
<p>
<named-content content-type="letter-date">2 Jul 2019</named-content>
</p>
<p>PONE-D-19-16716</p>
<p>Impact of metronomic UFT, cyclophosphamide, or when combined on mediators of breast cancer dissemination in vivo and 3D invasiveness in vitro</p>
<p>PLOS ONE</p>
<p>Dear Dr. Kerbel,</p>
<p>Thank you for submitting your manuscript to PLOS ONE. After careful consideration, we feel that it has merit but does not fully meet PLOS ONE&#8217;s publication criteria as it currently stands. Therefore, we invite you to submit a revised version of the manuscript that addresses the points raised during the review process by the two Reviewers, both experts in the metronomic field.</p>
<p>We would appreciate receiving your revised manuscript by Aug 16 2019 11:59PM. When you are ready to submit your revision, log on to <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://www.editorialmanager.com/pone/" ns0:type="simple">https://www.editorialmanager.com/pone/</ext-link> and select the 'Submissions Needing Revision' folder to locate your manuscript file.</p>
<p>If you would like to make changes to your financial disclosure, please include your updated statement in your cover letter.</p>
<p>To enhance the reproducibility of your results, we recommend that if applicable you deposit your laboratory protocols in protocols.io, where a protocol can be assigned its own identifier (DOI) such that it can be cited independently in the future. For instructions see: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://journals.plos.org/plosone/s/submission-guidelines#loc-laboratory-protocols" ns0:type="simple">http://journals.plos.org/plosone/s/submission-guidelines#loc-laboratory-protocols</ext-link></p>
<p>Please include the following items when submitting your revised manuscript:</p>
<p><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>A rebuttal letter that responds to each point raised by the academic editor and reviewer(s). This letter should be uploaded as separate file and labeled 'Response to Reviewers'.</p></list-item><list-item><p>A marked-up copy of your manuscript that highlights changes made to the original version. This file should be uploaded as separate file and labeled 'Revised Manuscript with Track Changes'.</p></list-item><list-item><p>An unmarked version of your revised paper without tracked changes. This file should be uploaded as separate file and labeled 'Manuscript'.</p></list-item></list></p>
<p>Please note while forming your response, if your article is accepted, you may have the opportunity to make the peer review history publicly available. The record will include editor decision letters (with reviews) and your responses to reviewer comments. If eligible, we will contact you to opt in or out.</p>
<p>We look forward to receiving your revised manuscript.</p>
<p>Kind regards,</p>
<p>Francesco Bertolini, MD, PhD</p>
<p>Academic Editor</p>
<p>PLOS ONE</p>
<p>Journal Requirements:</p>
<p>1. When submitting your revision, we need you to address these additional requirements.</p>
<p>Please ensure that your manuscript meets PLOS ONE's style requirements, including those for file naming. The PLOS ONE style templates can be found at</p>
<p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://www.journals.plos.org/plosone/s/file?id=wjVg/PLOSOne_formatting_sample_main_body.pdf" ns0:type="simple">http://www.journals.plos.org/plosone/s/file?id=wjVg/PLOSOne_formatting_sample_main_body.pdf</ext-link> and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://www.journals.plos.org/plosone/s/file?id=ba62/PLOSOne_formatting_sample_title_authors_affiliations.pdf" ns0:type="simple">http://www.journals.plos.org/plosone/s/file?id=ba62/PLOSOne_formatting_sample_title_authors_affiliations.pdf</ext-link></p>
<p>2. To comply with PLOS ONE submissions requirements, in your Methods section, please provide additional information regarding the experiments involving animals and ensure you have included details on (1) methods of sacrifice at the end of the study, (2) methods of anesthesia and/or analgesia, and (3) efforts to alleviate suffering.</p>
<p>3. We note that you have included the phrase &#8220;data not shown&#8221; in your manuscript. Unfortunately, this does not meet our data sharing requirements. PLOS does not permit references to inaccessible data. We require that authors provide all relevant data within the paper, Supporting Information files, or in an acceptable, public repository. Please add a citation to support this phrase or upload the data that corresponds with these findings to a stable repository (such as Figshare or Dryad) and provide and URLs, DOIs, or accession numbers that may be used to access these data. Or, if the data are not a core part of the research being presented in your study, we ask that you remove the phrase that refers to these data.</p>
<p>[Note: HTML markup is below. Please do not edit.]</p>
<p>Reviewers' comments:</p>
<p>Reviewer's Responses to Questions</p>
<p><bold>Comments to the Author</bold></p>
<p>1. Is the manuscript technically sound, and do the data support the conclusions?</p>
<p>The manuscript must describe a technically sound piece of scientific research with data that supports the conclusions. Experiments must have been conducted rigorously, with appropriate controls, replication, and sample sizes. The conclusions must be drawn appropriately based on the data presented. </p>
<p>Reviewer #1: Yes</p>
<p>Reviewer #2: Partly</p>
<p>**********</p>
<p>2. Has the statistical analysis been performed appropriately and rigorously? </p>
<p>Reviewer #1: No</p>
<p>Reviewer #2: No</p>
<p>**********</p>
<p>3. Have the authors made all data underlying the findings in their manuscript fully available?</p>
<p>The <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://www.plosone.org/static/policies.action#sharing" ns0:type="simple">PLOS Data policy</ext-link> requires authors to make all data underlying the findings described in their manuscript fully available without restriction, with rare exception (please refer to the Data Availability Statement in the manuscript PDF file). The data should be provided as part of the manuscript or its supporting information, or deposited to a public repository. For example, in addition to summary statistics, the data points behind means, medians and variance measures should be available. If there are restrictions on publicly sharing data&#8212;e.g. participant privacy or use of data from a third party&#8212;those must be specified.</p>
<p>Reviewer #1: Yes</p>
<p>Reviewer #2: Yes</p>
<p>**********</p>
<p>4. Is the manuscript presented in an intelligible fashion and written in standard English?</p>
<p>PLOS ONE does not copyedit accepted manuscripts, so the language in submitted articles must be clear, correct, and unambiguous. Any typographical or grammatical errors should be corrected at revision, so please note any specific errors here.</p>
<p>Reviewer #1: Yes</p>
<p>Reviewer #2: No</p>
<p>**********</p>
<p>5. Review Comments to the Author</p>
<p>Please use the space provided to explain your answers to the questions above. You may also include additional comments for the author, including concerns about dual publication, research ethics, or publication ethics. (Please upload your review as an attachment if it exceeds 20,000 characters)</p>
<p>Reviewer #1: In this paper, Munoz et al provide a possible explanation for a previous work by the same group reporting paradoxical effect of metronomic chemotherapy on primary tumor growth and metastatic disease in a TNBC model. The authors evaluate the effect of low-dose CTX and UFT, and their combination, on vascular density, collagen deposition and c-Met in the primary tumor setting via histochemistry/immunohistochemistry. Moreover, the authors evaluated the in vitro effect of continuous low-dose of active drug metabolites using a transwell migration assay and a 3D matrigel assay.</p>
<p>In order to better appreciate the manuscript, some minor revisions are needed:</p>
<p>1. The title is unclear, please rephrase it.</p>
<p>2. The introduction, even if it is clear and well written, is too long. It must be shortened.</p>
<p>3. In the results sections, Munoz and colleagues also include a discussion about the data. The authors should comment the data specifically in the discussion part. Furthermore, the titles of the paragraphs in the results section must be explicative of the data presented. Do not use general terms as &#8220;effects&#8221; and &#8220;assessment&#8221;, please focus more on the take-on message.</p>
<p>4. In general, I suggest to the authors to present the data reported in the tables with graphs. The raw data could be uploaded as supplementary materials. Also please, provide statistical analysis and a legend for the data in table 1.</p>
<p>5. The main scope of this manuscript is to shed light on the mechanism beyond the observation that UFT, either alone or in combination with CTX, had a modest effect on primary tumor growth, but is able to inhibit metastatic spread. My main concern regards the fact that the authors based most of the evidence from a previous paper (Munoz R et al, 2006). Have the authors performed new experiments to evaluate lung metastasis at mice sacrifice or after tumor resection? If not, they should provide them to corroborate the previous evidences.</p>
<p>Reviewer #2: Munoz et at reexamine a metronomic chemo drug schedule in a triple negative orthotopedic breast center model that they first described in 2006 (Ref #13), to determine how/why uracil-tegafur-cyclophosphamide (UFT + CTX) inhibits micro-metastasis development but has little inhibitory effects on primary tumor growth. They now find that, although the combination drug treatment has little effect on primary tumor volume (Fig. 1), it significantly increases necrosis and decreases vascularity in invasive border sections of the tumor (Fig. 2). Further, it decreases phosphorylation of the growth factor receptor c-Met, which contributes to tumor growth and metastasis (Fig. 5). Most interesting is the finding, using cell culture models and a trans-well invasion assay, that drug treatment inhibits tumor cell migratory and inhibitory potential but not tumor cell viability. Together, these finding provide a substantial advance in explaining the apparent discrepancy raised by findings in the 2006 study.</p>
<p>Specific concerns include the following:</p>
<p>1. Why did the authors not confirm their 2006 finding of inhibition of micrometastases by the UFT + CTX combination? Tumor cell models can drift/evolve over time (13 years, in this case), and there is some concern that the in vivo findings with primary tumors, reported here, might not be directly applicable to the earlier findings of inhibition of metastasis in what may only nominally be the same tumor model. Further, if the prior metastasis study was performed in a post-surgical model, then the current findings about impact of UFT + CTX on metastatic potential in a non-surgical model may not be directly relevant.</p>
<p>2. In several places, conclusions stated in the text need to be based on a more rigorous implementation of statistical analysis. For example:</p>
<p>- Line 177 - Fig. 1 conclusion of delayed tumor growth needs statistical support. (Also, mark day of first drug treatment along the x-axis)</p>
<p>- Line 281 &#8211; Any conclusion of reduced invasion into adjacent soft tissue requires statistical analysis of Table 1 results.</p>
<p>- Line 300 &#8211; Similarly, the conclusion stated in the text of reduced collagen deposition in all treatment groups requires statistical analysis of Table 2 data. Text on line 302 indicates that is not significant.</p>
<p>- - Line 387 &#8211; Staining scores should be listed for each individual tumor in a supplemental Table, similar to the format of Table 2.</p>
<p>3. The entire work is apparently based on a single in vivo experiment (Fig. 1) with only 4-5 tumors per group. This limitation should be explicitly noted, e.g., in Discussion.</p>
<p>4. What is the impact of drug treatment on MMP expression &#8211; in vitro or in vivo (line 464)?</p>
<p>5. Is the in vitro HC concentration really 10nM? Are there any prior studies showing a biological effect of HC at such a low concentration? That concentration is 100-500-fold lower that typically reported anti-tumor activities for HC.</p>
<p>6. Minor Points</p>
<p>- Shorten Introduction by editing.</p>
<p>- Line 61 &#8211; Correct text to indicate clinical trial metronomic (?) studies</p>
<p>- Line 381 &#8211; Arrow not visible on Figure</p>
<p>- Table 3 &#8211; Specify drug concentration. Same for Figure S6, etc. (see line 631).</p>
<p>- Line 617 ff. Specify sources for HC.</p>
<p>**********</p>
<p>6. PLOS authors have the option to publish the peer review history of their article (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://journals.plos.org/plosone/s/editorial-and-peer-review-process#loc-peer-review-history" ns0:type="simple">what does this mean?</ext-link>). If published, this will include your full peer review and any attached files.</p>
<p>If you choose &#8220;no&#8221;, your identity will remain anonymous but your review may still be made public.</p>
<p><bold>Do you want your identity to be public for this peer review?</bold> For information about this choice, including consent withdrawal, please see our <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://www.plos.org/privacy-policy" ns0:type="simple">Privacy Policy</ext-link>.</p>
<p>Reviewer #1: No</p>
<p>Reviewer #2: No</p>
<p>[NOTE: If reviewer comments were submitted as an attachment file, they will be attached to this email and accessible via the submission site. Please log into your account, locate the manuscript record, and check for the action link "View Attachments". If this link does not appear, there are no attachment files to be viewed.]</p>
<p>While revising your submission, please upload your figure files to the Preflight Analysis and Conversion Engine (PACE) digital diagnostic tool, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://pacev2.apexcovantage.com/" ns0:type="simple">https://pacev2.apexcovantage.com/</ext-link>. PACE helps ensure that figures meet PLOS requirements. To use PACE, you must first register as a user. Registration is free. Then, login and navigate to the UPLOAD tab, where you will find detailed instructions on how to use the tool. If you encounter any issues or have any questions when using PACE, please email us at <email ns0:type="simple">figures@plos.org</email>. Please note that Supporting Information files do not need this step.</p>
</body>
</sub-article>
