<sub-article xmlns:ns0="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="aggregated-review-documents" id="pcbi.1007383.r001" specific-use="decision-letter">
<front-stub>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1007383.r001</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title>Decision Letter 0</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Ben-Tal</surname>
<given-names>Nir</given-names>
</name>
<role>Deputy Editor</role>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Wei</surname>
<given-names>Guanghong</given-names>
</name>
<role>Associate Editor</role>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<permissions>
<copyright-year>2019</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>Ben-Tal, Wei</copyright-holder>
<license ns0:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
<license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" ns0:type="simple">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<related-object document-id="10.1371/journal.pcbi.1007383" document-id-type="doi" document-type="article" id="rel-obj001" link-type="peer-reviewed-article" />
<custom-meta-group>
<custom-meta>
<meta-name>Submission Version</meta-name>
<meta-value>0</meta-value>
</custom-meta>
</custom-meta-group>
</front-stub>
<body>
<p>
<named-content content-type="letter-date">18 Jul 2019</named-content>
</p>
<p>Dear Dr Czub,</p>
<p>Thank you very much for submitting your manuscript 'Why do G-quadruplexes dimerize through the 5&#8217;-ends? Driving forces for G4 DNA dimerization examined in atomic detail.' for review by PLOS Computational Biology. Your manuscript has been fully evaluated by the PLOS Computational Biology editorial team and in this case also by independent peer reviewers. The reviewers appreciated the attention to an important problem, but raised some substantial concerns about the manuscript as it currently stands. While your manuscript cannot be accepted in its present form, we are willing to consider a revised version in which the issues raised by the reviewers have been adequately addressed. We cannot, of course, promise publication at that time.</p>
<p>Please note while forming your response, if your article is accepted, you may have the opportunity to make the peer review history publicly available. The record will include editor decision letters (with reviews) and your responses to reviewer comments. If eligible, we will contact you to opt in or out.</p>
<p>Your revisions should address the specific points made by each reviewer. Please return the revised version within the next 60 days. If you anticipate any delay in its return, we ask that you let us know the expected resubmission date by email at <email ns0:type="simple">ploscompbiol@plos.org</email>. Revised manuscripts received beyond 60 days may require evaluation and peer review similar to that applied to newly submitted manuscripts.</p>
<p>In addition, when you are ready to resubmit, please be prepared to provide the following:</p>
<p>(1) A detailed list of your responses to the review comments and the changes you have made in the manuscript. We require a file of this nature before your manuscript is passed back to the editors.</p>
<p>(2) A copy of your manuscript with the changes highlighted (encouraged). We encourage authors, if possible to show clearly where changes have been made to their manuscript e.g. by highlighting text.</p>
<p>(3) A striking still image to accompany your article (optional). If the image is judged to be suitable by the editors, it may be featured on our website and might be chosen as the issue image for that month. These square, high-quality images should be accompanied by a short caption. Please note as well that there should be no copyright restrictions on the use of the image, so that it can be published under the Open-Access license and be subject only to appropriate attribution.</p>
<p>Before you resubmit your manuscript, please consult our Submission Checklist to ensure your manuscript is formatted correctly for PLOS Computational Biology: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://www.ploscompbiol.org/static/checklist.action" ns0:type="simple">http://www.ploscompbiol.org/static/checklist.action</ext-link>. Some key points to remember are:</p>
<p>- Figures uploaded separately as TIFF or EPS files (if you wish, your figures may remain in your main manuscript file in addition).</p>
<p>- Supporting Information uploaded as separate files, titled Dataset, Figure, Table, Text, Protocol, Audio, or Video.</p>
<p>- Funding information in the 'Financial Disclosure' box in the online system.</p>
<p>While revising your submission, please upload your figure files to the Preflight Analysis and Conversion Engine (PACE) digital diagnostic tool, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://pacev2.apexcovantage.com" ns0:type="simple">https://pacev2.apexcovantage.com</ext-link>&#160;PACE helps ensure that figures meet PLOS requirements. To use PACE, you must first register as a user. Then, login and navigate to the UPLOAD tab, where you will find detailed instructions on how to use the tool. If you encounter any issues or have any questions when using PACE, please email us at <email ns0:type="simple">figures@plos.org</email>.</p>
<p>To enhance the reproducibility of your results, we recommend that you deposit your laboratory protocols in protocols.io, where a protocol can be assigned its own identifier (DOI) such that it can be cited independently in the future. For instructions see <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://journals.plos.org/ploscompbiol/s/submission-guidelines#loc-materials-and-methods" ns0:type="simple">here</ext-link>.&#160;</p>
<p>We are sorry that we cannot be more positive about your manuscript at this stage, but if you have any concerns or questions, please do not hesitate to contact us.</p>
<p>Sincerely,</p>
<p>Guanghong Wei</p>
<p>Associate Editor</p>
<p>PLOS Computational Biology</p>
<p>Nir Ben-Tal</p>
<p>Deputy Editor</p>
<p>PLOS Computational Biology</p>
<p>A link appears below if there are any accompanying review attachments. If you believe any reviews to be missing, please contact <email ns0:type="simple">ploscompbiol@plos.org</email> immediately:</p>
<p>[LINK]</p>
<p>Reviewer's Responses to Questions</p>
<p><bold>Comments to the Authors:</bold></p>
<p><bold>Please note here if the review is uploaded as an attachment.</bold></p>
<p>Reviewer #1: In this work the authors studied the stacking patterns of two G-quadruplexes using large-scale replica exchange MD simulations. Based on the simulations, they gave the dominant stacking model, analyzed the corresponding structures in detail, and investigated the underlying interactions for the stability. They also studied the binding free energies as a function of salt concentrations. The knowledge gained in the study may facilitate controlling G4 assembling and designing new G4 oligomers. Overall, I found the simulations were well done, the analysis was sufficient, and the results were solid. I suggest with acceptance of the paper for publication, provided the following minor problems are fixed.</p>
<p>1) Figure captions are not complete, e.g., what are the shaded regions in Fig. 1, what are the color codes in Fig. 2 and 4?</p>
<p>2) In page 9, line 375, the author mentioned &#8220;with 42 K+ counterions &#8230;&#8221;The sentence is hard to understand. And what the equivalent concentration of this &#8220;with 42 K+ conterions&#8221;?</p>
<p>3) There are some relevant works published previously, e.g., Y. Bian, et al., PLOS CB 2014, v10, e1003562, and J. Zhou, et al., JACS 2017, v139, 7768, the author may want to discuss their relevance with this work.</p>
<p>Reviewer #2: The paper by Czub et al. is a computational study of preferential orientations of GQ dimerization process. From the well-converged free energy calculation as a function of a distance between two guanine cores, they found that G-quadruplexes preferentially dimerize through the 5'-ends. The reason for this 5'-end preference is due to fine balance between interphosphate repulsion and counterion binding. This paper is well written and demonstrates a power of molecular dynamics simulation methods. I would recommend this paper for the publication of PLOS Comp. Biol. after minor revisions.</p>
<p>1. Although the authors pointed out an important role of the enthalpic contribution for such dimerization process and decomposed the enthalpic contributions into several factors, it is difficult to find the total enthalpic and entropic changes in the manuscript. These total enthalpic and entropic changes need to be specified at the first place to clearly state whether the dimerization is due to enthalpic or entropic origin.</p>
<p>2. The authors concluded that 5'-end binding is preferred mainly due to less interphosphate repulsion. Are there any indications of sugar puckering changes for 5'-end, 5&#8217;-3&#8217; end, 3&#8217;-end dimerization cases to modulate such interphosphate repulsive interactions?</p>
<p>3. In the dimerization via 5'-end, 5&#8217;-3&#8217; end, or 3&#8217;-end, are there any distinctive perturbation of loop regions?</p>
<p>4. In the GQ dimer, spatial distribution of potassium ions was plotted. In comparison with ion distribution, it would be nice to plot spatial distribution of water at the binding interface to gauge any possible dehydration effect after the dimerization.</p>
<p>5. For 3,4-TMPyPz ligand, which was used for the 3-3 dimer, the partial charges they derived need to be included in SI.</p>
<p>Reviewer #3: Please see the attached review.</p>
<p>**********</p>
<p><bold>Have all data underlying the figures and results presented in the manuscript been provided?</bold></p>
<p>Large-scale datasets should be made available via a public repository as described in the <italic>PLOS Computational Biology</italic> <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://journals.plos.org/ploscompbiol/s/data-availability" ns0:type="simple">data availability policy</ext-link>, and numerical data that underlies graphs or summary statistics should be provided in spreadsheet form as supporting information.</p>
<p>Reviewer #1: Yes</p>
<p>Reviewer #2: Yes</p>
<p>Reviewer #3: Yes</p>
<p>**********</p>
<p>PLOS authors have the option to publish the peer review history of their article (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://journals.plos.org/ploscompbiol/s/editorial-and-peer-review-process#loc-peer-review-history" ns0:type="simple">what does this mean?</ext-link>). If published, this will include your full peer review and any attached files.</p>
<p>If you choose &#8220;no&#8221;, your identity will remain anonymous but your review may still be made public.</p>
<p><bold>Do you want your identity to be public for this peer review?</bold> For information about this choice, including consent withdrawal, please see our <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://www.plos.org/privacy-policy" ns0:type="simple">Privacy Policy</ext-link>.</p>
<p>Reviewer #1: No</p>
<p>Reviewer #2: No</p>
<p>Reviewer #3: Yes: Nanjie Deng</p>
<supplementary-material id="pcbi.1007383.s022" mimetype="application/pdf" position="float" ns0:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1007383.s022" ns0:type="simple">
<label>Attachment</label>
<caption>
<p>Submitted filename: <named-content content-type="submitted-filename">Review-G4-dimerization-PLOS-COMPBIOL-07-2019.pdf</named-content></p>
</caption>
</supplementary-material>
</body>
</sub-article>
