<sub-article xmlns:ns0="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="aggregated-review-documents" id="pone.0222209.r001" specific-use="decision-letter">
<front-stub>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0222209.r001</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title>Decision Letter 0</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Kalendar</surname>
<given-names>Ruslan</given-names>
</name>
<role>Academic Editor</role>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<permissions>
<copyright-year>2019</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>Ruslan Kalendar</copyright-holder>
<license ns0:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
<license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" ns0:type="simple">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<related-object document-id="10.1371/journal.pone.0222209" document-id-type="doi" document-type="article" id="rel-obj001" link-type="peer-reviewed-article" />
<custom-meta-group>
<custom-meta>
<meta-name>Submission Version</meta-name>
<meta-value>0</meta-value>
</custom-meta>
</custom-meta-group>
</front-stub>
<body>
<p>
<named-content content-type="letter-date">31 Jul 2019</named-content>
</p>
<p>PONE-D-19-19358</p>
<p>Development of highly sensitive and low-cost DNA agarose gel electrophoresis detection systems and evaluation of non-mutagenic and loading dye-type DNA-staining reagents</p>
<p>PLOS ONE</p>
<p>Dear Dr. MOTOHASHI,</p>
<p>Thank you for submitting your manuscript to PLOS ONE. After careful consideration, we feel that it has merit but does not fully meet PLOS ONE&#8217;s publication criteria as it currently stands. Therefore, we invite you to submit a revised version of the manuscript that addresses the points raised during the review process.</p>
<p>We would appreciate receiving your revised manuscript by Sep 14 2019 11:59PM. When you are ready to submit your revision, log on to <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://www.editorialmanager.com/pone/" ns0:type="simple">https://www.editorialmanager.com/pone/</ext-link> and select the 'Submissions Needing Revision' folder to locate your manuscript file.</p>
<p>If you would like to make changes to your financial disclosure, please include your updated statement in your cover letter.</p>
<p>To enhance the reproducibility of your results, we recommend that if applicable you deposit your laboratory protocols in protocols.io, where a protocol can be assigned its own identifier (DOI) such that it can be cited independently in the future. For instructions see: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://journals.plos.org/plosone/s/submission-guidelines#loc-laboratory-protocols" ns0:type="simple">http://journals.plos.org/plosone/s/submission-guidelines#loc-laboratory-protocols</ext-link></p>
<p>Please include the following items when submitting your revised manuscript:</p>
<p><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>A rebuttal letter that responds to each point raised by the academic editor and reviewer(s). This letter should be uploaded as separate file and labeled 'Response to Reviewers'.</p></list-item><list-item><p>A marked-up copy of your manuscript that highlights changes made to the original version. This file should be uploaded as separate file and labeled 'Revised Manuscript with Track Changes'.</p></list-item><list-item><p>An unmarked version of your revised paper without tracked changes. This file should be uploaded as separate file and labeled 'Manuscript'.</p></list-item></list></p>
<p>Please note while forming your response, if your article is accepted, you may have the opportunity to make the peer review history publicly available. The record will include editor decision letters (with reviews) and your responses to reviewer comments. If eligible, we will contact you to opt in or out.</p>
<p>We look forward to receiving your revised manuscript.</p>
<p>Kind regards,</p>
<p>Ruslan Kalendar, PhD</p>
<p>Academic Editor</p>
<p>PLOS ONE</p>
<p>Journal requirements:</p>
<p>When submitting your revision, we need you to address these additional requirements.</p>
<p>Please ensure that your manuscript meets PLOS ONE's style requirements, including those for file naming. The PLOS ONE style templates can be found at</p>
<p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://www.journals.plos.org/plosone/s/file?id=wjVg/PLOSOne_formatting_sample_main_body.pdf" ns0:type="simple">http://www.journals.plos.org/plosone/s/file?id=wjVg/PLOSOne_formatting_sample_main_body.pdf</ext-link> and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://www.journals.plos.org/plosone/s/file?id=ba62/PLOSOne_formatting_sample_title_authors_affiliations.pdf" ns0:type="simple">http://www.journals.plos.org/plosone/s/file?id=ba62/PLOSOne_formatting_sample_title_authors_affiliations.pdf</ext-link></p>
<p>1. PLOS ONE now requires that authors provide the original uncropped and unadjusted images underlying all blot or gel results reported in a submission&#8217;s figures or Supporting Information files. This policy and the journal&#8217;s other requirements for blot/gel reporting and figure preparation are described in detail at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://journals.plos.org/plosone/s/figures#loc-blot-and-gel-reporting-requirements" ns0:type="simple">https://journals.plos.org/plosone/s/figures#loc-blot-and-gel-reporting-requirements</ext-link> and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://journals.plos.org/plosone/s/figures#loc-preparing-figures-from-image-files" ns0:type="simple">https://journals.plos.org/plosone/s/figures#loc-preparing-figures-from-image-files</ext-link>. When you submit your revised manuscript, please ensure that your figures adhere fully to these guidelines and provide the original underlying images for all blot or gel data reported in your submission. See the following link for instructions on providing the original image data: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://journals.plos.org/plosone/s/figures#loc-original-images-for-blots-and-gels" ns0:type="simple">https://journals.plos.org/plosone/s/figures#loc-original-images-for-blots-and-gels</ext-link>.</p>
<p>In your cover letter, please note whether your blot/gel image data are in Supporting Information or posted at a public data repository, provide the repository URL if relevant, and provide specific details as to which raw blot/gel images, if any, are not available. Email us at <email ns0:type="simple">plosone@plos.org</email> if you have any questions.</p>
<p>Reviewers' comments:</p>
<p>Reviewer's Responses to Questions</p>
<p><bold>Comments to the Author</bold></p>
<p>&#160;5. Review Comments to the Author</p>
<p>&#160;&#160;</p>
<p>Reviewer #1:</p>
<p>Motohashi reports the use of different illumination systems to detect DNA fragments stained with a set of six intercalating dyes and separated by agarose gel electrophoresis. The illumination systems included a conventional UV transilluminator, a Blook Blue LED system, a cyan LED system, and a blacklight transilluminator. Samples are loaded in successively lower amounts on separate lanes of the gel. Data are presented as black-and-white photographs, which were generated using a Canon Powershot camera. The images were processed using Image-J.</p>
<p>I believe that the article satisfies most, but not all of PLOS ONE's criteria for publication:</p>
<p>1. The study presents the results of primary scientific research.</p>
<p>2. To the best of my knowledge, the results have not been published elsewhere.</p>
<p>3a. Some experimental details are missing. In particular, my searchs were unsuccessful for the "Compact LED viewer [470 nm], Sanplatec, for the Cyan LED (490&#8211;495 nm, Holkin), for the SV0510 shortness filter mentioned, and for the compact blacklight lamp (FPL27BLB; Sankyo Denki) mentioned on page 4 and 6 of the manuscript. URLs would be useful.</p>
<p>3b. I do not understand the design of the illumination systems, and those systems are not described in sufficient detail for me to reproduce the results. Were the LEDs and black lights used in a commercial transilluminator, or were illuminators used with a homemade illuminator? A diagram of the homebuilt illuminators is required.</p>
<p>3c. It is striking that intercalating dyes from Molecular Probes are not included in this study. In particular, SYBR Safe is marketed as having lower toxicity than ethidium bromide and is used with high sensitivity for DNA detection in gel electrophoresis.</p>
<p>3d. I do not see the Image-J data used to construct Table 2. The criterion for the sensitivity values in Table 2 are arbitrary because no definition of fragment detection is given. The definition of detection limit is not standard. Statistical analyses of the data are missing.</p>
<p>3e. The spectrometer used to generate the excitation and emission wavelengths used in Table 1 is not described in the text. It would be useful to include the spectra in the manuscript. Alternatively, if these are literature values, the source of the information should be listed.</p>
<p>4. The author makes several conclusions. Some appear to be justified by the data, but one set of conclusions is not justified. The author compares the cost of a commercial transilluminator with the cost of the components used to construct the black-light illumination system. As a rule of thumb, the hardware components for a commercial instrument are ~10% of the cost of the final product; the commercial instrument has additional costs associated with design and development, regulatory approval, manufacturing, and marketing; once commercialized, the systems proposed by the author will have the similar costs as the other commercial instruments. The conclusion concerning the relative costs of the various systems must be removed from the paper.</p>
<p>5. Except for the missing experimental details, the manuscript is presented in an intelligible fashion. While the paper would benefit from minor copyediting, that editing is not required to the paper to be interpretable</p>
<p>6. The paper apparently meets ethical standards.</p>
<p>7. The paper presents raw data as images. The corresponding Image-J data are not presented.</p>
<p>Reviewer #2:</p>
<p>The detection system described in the paper will be of significant interest to individuals and organizations for which the cost of a conventional system is prohibitively expensive. They will be able to build their own instrument based on this paper. I recommend that the author provide more details of how the system can be constructed from commercially available parts, including an image of what it looks like, so that a person who is interested will be able to replicate it.</p>
<p>Reviewer #3:</p>
<p>This manuscript describes the development of low-cost imaging systems for detecting DNA, with the goal of minimizing DNA damage due to the illumination wavelengths. The author described the detection limits using several different DNA-binding dyes and several different illumination systems.</p>
<p>I have several concerns about this report:</p>
<p>First, the sensitivity estimation relied completely on visual perception. A more rigorous numerical method should be used. These are digital images that can be easily quantified using free software tools such as ImageJ.</p>
<p>Second, the author did not mention how the images were displayed and if any image contrasting or enhancement was used. Was the camera mounted inside a light-tight enclosure or setup in an open space?</p>
<p>Third, the lanes of all gel images in all of the figures should be labeled.</p>
<p>Finally, and most importantly, since the goal of this work was to minimize photo-induced DNA damage, I assume the author's ultimate goal is to excise DNA fragments from gels for cloning purposes. The author needs to demonstrate the utility of these low cost systems for visualizing and excising gel fragments. Systems that require bandpass emission filters may not enable one to look directly at the gel for manually cutting out of gel fragments. In addition, are the home-built imagers amenable to the cutting of gel fragments. Commercial transilluminators are designed to enable gel cutting.</p>
<p>If the author's goal is to simply document DNA gels and not enable gel cutting, then it is not clear if these low-cost alternatives offer the uniformity and repeatability of commercial imaging systems.</p>
<p>While revising your submission, please upload your figure files to the Preflight Analysis and Conversion Engine (PACE) digital diagnostic tool, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://pacev2.apexcovantage.com/" ns0:type="simple">https://pacev2.apexcovantage.com/</ext-link>. PACE helps ensure that figures meet PLOS requirements. To use PACE, you must first register as a user. Registration is free. Then, login and navigate to the UPLOAD tab, where you will find detailed instructions on how to use the tool. If you encounter any issues or have any questions when using PACE, please email us at <email ns0:type="simple">figures@plos.org</email>. Please note that Supporting Information files do not need this step.</p>
</body>
</sub-article>
