<sub-article xmlns:ns0="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="aggregated-review-documents" id="pone.0220683.r003" specific-use="decision-letter">
<front-stub>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0220683.r003</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title>Decision Letter 1</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Garc&#237;a</surname>
<given-names>M&#237;riam R.</given-names>
</name>
<role>Academic Editor</role>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<permissions>
<copyright-year>2019</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>M&#237;riam R. Garc&#237;a</copyright-holder>
<license ns0:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
<license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" ns0:type="simple">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<related-object document-id="10.1371/journal.pone.0220683" document-id-type="doi" document-type="article" id="rel-obj003" link-type="peer-reviewed-article" />
<custom-meta-group>
<custom-meta>
<meta-name>Submission Version</meta-name>
<meta-value>1</meta-value>
</custom-meta>
</custom-meta-group>
</front-stub>
<body>
<p>
<named-content content-type="letter-date">9 Jul 2019</named-content>
</p>
<p>PONE-D-19-14978R1</p>
<p>On the use of in-silico simulations to support experimental design: a case study in microbial inactivation of foods</p>
<p>PLOS ONE</p>
<p>Dear Dr. Egea,</p>
<p>Thank you for submitting your manuscript to PLOS ONE. After careful consideration, we feel that the manuscript has improved considerably&#160;but still does not fully meet PLOS ONE&#8217;s publication criteria as it currently stands. Therefore, we invite you to submit a revised version of the manuscript that addresses the points raised during the review process.</p>
<p>Reviewer #2 has accepted the publication of the manuscript. However, previous reviewer #1 has declined the invitation for this&#160;second round, and we have had to invite&#160;a new reviewer with experience in the field. This&#160;new reviewer considers that there are still major concerns that&#160;should be clarified before publication. Also, please&#160;be more specific about the data availability. In the revised version of the manuscript we&#160;cannot find the supplementary material with the&#160;code or data used for the research.</p>
<p>We would appreciate receiving your revised manuscript by Aug 23 2019 11:59PM. When you are ready to submit your revision, log on to <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://www.editorialmanager.com/pone/" ns0:type="simple">https://www.editorialmanager.com/pone/</ext-link> and select the 'Submissions Needing Revision' folder to locate your manuscript file.</p>
<p>If you would like to make changes to your financial disclosure, please include your updated statement in your cover letter.</p>
<p>To enhance the reproducibility of your results, we recommend that if applicable you deposit your laboratory protocols in protocols.io, where a protocol can be assigned its own identifier (DOI) such that it can be cited independently in the future. For instructions see: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://journals.plos.org/plosone/s/submission-guidelines#loc-laboratory-protocols" ns0:type="simple">http://journals.plos.org/plosone/s/submission-guidelines#loc-laboratory-protocols</ext-link></p>
<p>Please include the following items when submitting your revised manuscript:</p>
<p><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>A rebuttal letter that responds to each point raised by the academic editor and reviewer(s). This letter should be uploaded as separate file and labeled 'Response to Reviewers'.</p></list-item><list-item><p>A marked-up copy of your manuscript that highlights changes made to the original version. This file should be uploaded as separate file and labeled 'Revised Manuscript with Track Changes'.</p></list-item><list-item><p>An unmarked version of your revised paper without tracked changes. This file should be uploaded as separate file and labeled 'Manuscript'.</p></list-item></list></p>
<p>Please note while forming your response, if your article is accepted, you may have the opportunity to make the peer review history publicly available. The record will include editor decision letters (with reviews) and your responses to reviewer comments. If eligible, we will contact you to opt in or out.</p>
<p>We look forward to receiving your revised manuscript.</p>
<p>Kind regards,</p>
<p>M&#237;riam R. Garc&#237;a</p>
<p>Academic Editor</p>
<p>PLOS ONE</p>
<p>[Note: HTML markup is below. Please do not edit.]</p>
<p>Reviewers' comments:</p>
<p>Reviewer's Responses to Questions</p>
<p><bold>Comments to the Author</bold></p>
<p>1. If the authors have adequately addressed your comments raised in a previous round of review and you feel that this manuscript is now acceptable for publication, you may indicate that here to bypass the &#8220;Comments to the Author&#8221; section, enter your conflict of interest statement in the &#8220;Confidential to Editor&#8221; section, and submit your "Accept" recommendation.</p>
<p>Reviewer #2: All comments have been addressed</p>
<p>Reviewer #3: (No Response)</p>
<p>**********</p>
<p>2. Is the manuscript technically sound, and do the data support the conclusions?</p>
<p>The manuscript must describe a technically sound piece of scientific research with data that supports the conclusions. Experiments must have been conducted rigorously, with appropriate controls, replication, and sample sizes. The conclusions must be drawn appropriately based on the data presented. </p>
<p>Reviewer #2: Yes</p>
<p>Reviewer #3: Partly</p>
<p>**********</p>
<p>3. Has the statistical analysis been performed appropriately and rigorously? </p>
<p>Reviewer #2: Yes</p>
<p>Reviewer #3: Yes</p>
<p>**********</p>
<p>4. Have the authors made all data underlying the findings in their manuscript fully available?</p>
<p>The <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://www.plosone.org/static/policies.action#sharing" ns0:type="simple">PLOS Data policy</ext-link> requires authors to make all data underlying the findings described in their manuscript fully available without restriction, with rare exception (please refer to the Data Availability Statement in the manuscript PDF file). The data should be provided as part of the manuscript or its supporting information, or deposited to a public repository. For example, in addition to summary statistics, the data points behind means, medians and variance measures should be available. If there are restrictions on publicly sharing data&#8212;e.g. participant privacy or use of data from a third party&#8212;those must be specified.</p>
<p>Reviewer #2: Yes</p>
<p>Reviewer #3: No</p>
<p>**********</p>
<p>5. Is the manuscript presented in an intelligible fashion and written in standard English?</p>
<p>PLOS ONE does not copyedit accepted manuscripts, so the language in submitted articles must be clear, correct, and unambiguous. Any typographical or grammatical errors should be corrected at revision, so please note any specific errors here.</p>
<p>Reviewer #2: Yes</p>
<p>Reviewer #3: No</p>
<p>**********</p>
<p>6. Review Comments to the Author</p>
<p>Please use the space provided to explain your answers to the questions above. You may also include additional comments for the author, including concerns about dual publication, research ethics, or publication ethics. (Please upload your review as an attachment if it exceeds 20,000 characters)</p>
<p>Reviewer #2: (No Response)</p>
<p>Reviewer #3: The manuscript focusses on the use of Optimal Experimental Design (OED) to identify the most informative sampling schedule for the calibration of the Bigelow model for thermal microbial inactivation.</p>
<p>Despite an overall improvement can be detected in the second version of the manuscript, some of the concerns highlighted by previous reviewers have not been adequately addressed by the authors.</p>
<p>Major comments</p>
<p>- [Lines 105- 120]: The authors should clarify what to they mean by &#8216;there is still high uncertainty&#8217; in the experimental designs used in predictive microbiology. Indeed the common tendency to set aspects of the experimental scheme adopted for model calibration based on past experience/technical limitations of the experimental system/acquisition platform applies to the proposed investigation (where only the effect of the number and location sampling times is considered, albeit not optimised). The authors should clearly state the reason for which they focus only on sampling times, as they could have investigated the effect of other aspects (e.g. the thermal perturbation profile). In addition, the use of scalar functions of the FIM to optimise experimental schemes is now routine. In this context, the actual contribution of this manuscript should be emphasised.</p>
<p>- The adopted formulation of the penalty function to set a constraint on the sampling frequency requires clarification. I understand that a similar formulation was adopted in a previous publication by the same authors, but i) hybrid solvers can cope with linear inequality constraints in FIM-based OED; ii) the optimisation cost cannot be too high in the considered case (1D model with 2 parameters).</p>
<p>- [Lines 167- 170]: E-criterion attempts to minimise the maximum uncertainty in parameter estimates (not the parameter with the highest error). In addition, the authors should clearly state which aspects of D-optimality meet &#8216;circumstances&#8217; in their study case.</p>
<p>- Among the mentioned limitations of the FIM-based approach, local validity in the parameter space (i.e. computations are performed in the neighbourhood of the a priori unknown optimal/true parameters values) is the most relevant. I could not find any reference to how the initial uncertainty in parameter estimates was accounted for. This is a crucial point for applicability of the outlined methods. The application of the methods cannot precede the acquisition of some experimental data.</p>
<p>- An elusive comparison of the informative content of thermal profiles is presented. Due to the low dimensionality of the mathematical model, the simultaneous optimisation of i) number of sampling times, ii) their location and iii) the perturbation profile would have been feasible and of high interest.</p>
<p>- The conclusions drawn from the research provide limited insights and a more in depth analysis should be performed. It is intuitive that experience-based experimental schemes provide a lower bound of the performances of OED, otherwise we would not put effort in optimisation. The fact that one perturbation scheme results more informative than others is useful only if patterns identified support the extrapolation of &#8216;rules for informativeness&#8217;. Finally it seems obvious that data are not equally informative, so that increasing their cardinality might not convey additional information in uniform schemes.</p>
<p>Major comments</p>
<p>I report only some of the required corrections, please carefully revise the manuscript</p>
<p>- [Line 32]: methods to</p>
<p>- [Line 33]: is illustrated</p>
<p>- [Line 88]: the volume of the confidence hyperellipsoid</p>
<p>- [Line 91]: include additional &#8216;)&#8217;</p>
<p>- Figure 1 y axes &#8216;microbial&#8217;</p>
<p>- [Line 109]: are selected</p>
<p>- [Line 153]: criteria of the FIM. [&#8230; ], which consists</p>
<p>- [Line 178]: the selected parameter values</p>
<p>- [Line 181]: Hence, their effect</p>
<p>- [Line 213]: located close to..</p>
<p>- [Line 439]: an OED</p>
<p>- [Line 449]: different from</p>
<p>- [Line 463]: &#8216;more informative&#8217;</p>
<p>- [Lines 458-461]: Unclear, rephrase the sentence</p>
<p>- Figure 5: y axes &#8216;100 simulations&#8217;</p>
<p>**********</p>
<p>7. PLOS authors have the option to publish the peer review history of their article (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://journals.plos.org/plosone/s/editorial-and-peer-review-process#loc-peer-review-history" ns0:type="simple">what does this mean?</ext-link>). If published, this will include your full peer review and any attached files.</p>
<p>If you choose &#8220;no&#8221;, your identity will remain anonymous but your review may still be made public.</p>
<p><bold>Do you want your identity to be public for this peer review?</bold> For information about this choice, including consent withdrawal, please see our <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://www.plos.org/privacy-policy" ns0:type="simple">Privacy Policy</ext-link>.</p>
<p>Reviewer #2: No</p>
<p>Reviewer #3: Yes: Dr. Lucia Bandiera</p>
<p>[NOTE: If reviewer comments were submitted as an attachment file, they will be attached to this email and accessible via the submission site. Please log into your account, locate the manuscript record, and check for the action link "View Attachments". If this link does not appear, there are no attachment files to be viewed.]</p>
<p>While revising your submission, please upload your figure files to the Preflight Analysis and Conversion Engine (PACE) digital diagnostic tool, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://pacev2.apexcovantage.com/" ns0:type="simple">https://pacev2.apexcovantage.com/</ext-link>. PACE helps ensure that figures meet PLOS requirements. To use PACE, you must first register as a user. Registration is free. Then, login and navigate to the UPLOAD tab, where you will find detailed instructions on how to use the tool. If you encounter any issues or have any questions when using PACE, please email us at <email ns0:type="simple">figures@plos.org</email>. Please note that Supporting Information files do not need this step.</p>
</body>
</sub-article>
