<sub-article article-type="author-comment" id="pone.0221778.r004">
<front-stub>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0221778.r004</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title>Author response to Decision Letter 1</article-title>
</title-group>
<related-object document-id="10.1371/journal.pone.0221778" document-id-type="doi" document-type="peer-reviewed-article" id="rel-obj004" link-type="rebutted-decision-letter" object-id="10.1371/journal.pone.0221778.r003" object-id-type="doi" object-type="decision-letter" />
<custom-meta-group>
<custom-meta>
<meta-name>Submission Version</meta-name>
<meta-value>2</meta-value>
</custom-meta>
</custom-meta-group>
</front-stub>
<body>
<p>
<named-content content-type="author-response-date">11 Jul 2019</named-content>
</p>
<p>Dear Editor</p>
<p>We are to submit the revised version of our manuscript. The comments provided during the review process have further enabled to strengthen our manuscript. We trust you will find that our manuscript has improved significantly during this process.  Our responses to the comments raised by the reviewers are found below.</p>
<p>Best regards </p>
<p>Anthony Ajayi</p>
<p>On behalf of all authors. </p>
<p>Reviewer #1: I commend the authors for reviewing an important topic and their ambitious plans to effect a positive change (improvement in women healthcare in Nigeria) from their findings.</p>
<p>The large data set and parameters reviewed gives strength to this research work. However, there is new and important reference survey from Nigeria DHS 2018 report which makes the research work outdated as it was based on the old NDHS 2013 report.</p>
<p>Response </p>
<p>We thank the reviewer for the constructive and positive feedback.</p>
<p> I appreciate the fact that authors have made an attempt to request the data from the 2018 report which is not fully available to the general public. Perhaps this research can be delayed and new analysis done based on the new report. Based on this submission, the conclusion does not add anything new to what is already known about this topic. Linking the disparity to maternity outcome variables within the data set might actually provide strong evidence and attract interest to effect change as intended.</p>
<p>Response: We thank the reviewer for the insightful comments. As we said previously, we intend to write a second paper examining the change in inequality in access to birth by caesarean section when the recently completed 2018 DHS data is released and becomes publicly available. We believe our paper fills an important gap given our focus on this important issue that affects the lives of many women in Nigeria as over 58, 000 maternal deaths are recorded annually. Our paper further contributes to the evidence base for understanding the reason for the high burden of maternal deaths in Nigeria. We outline inequality in access to caesarean section as a contributing factor to adverse maternal outcomes in Nigeria, thus, contributing to knowledge on why maternal deaths are prevalent in Nigeria. We hope to build on this study in the future utilizing datasets from previous as well as the 2018 DHS to perform trend analysis to show changes in caesarean section utilization as an emergency obstetric care and hopefully will lead to the desired changes in supply and demand aspect of maternal health delivery in Nigeria. </p>
<p>Reviewer #2: There are numerous grammatical errors throughout the text, albeit they do not detract from the meaning. However, they should be addressed. </p>
<p>Response: We have extensively proofread our manuscript and also engaged a language editor. </p>
<p>Reviewer #2: The main issue, however, is that of the depth of the discussion. That there is inequity across the continuum of care is well addressed in Countdown 2030, and Nigeria remains a Countdown country. Caesarean section rates may be seen to some extent as a surrogate for the accessibility and availability of obstetric care, but there are other important factors to consider, both on the supply and demand sides, that have relevance to the rate of caesarean sections in real life situations. Whereas the authors have focused briefly on some demand side issues that may contribute to women declining a caesarean delivery there are many supply side issues too. I would have been interested to see more of a discussion as to why better educated women in the top wealth quintile have a higher rate of caesarean deliveries as compared to those with the same wealth but less education. Also the issue of whether the woman has health insurance also plays a part. A considered discussion of the influence of these factors on possible decision making processes by doctors is of relevance. Another complicating factor is that not all caesareans are done for good reasons even when the underlying rate is low. There are many reasons for this, but one factor is that doctors with insufficient experience are left unsupported to make crucial obstetric decisions, resulting in some women being subjected to all the present and future risks of surgery to be delivered by a caesarean that wasn't even necessary. This is a limitation of choosing caesarean rates as a surrogate for quality care provision, and should be mentioned. I feel therefore that if caesarean section rate is the measure to be considered in this important discourse on equity than the discussion would greatly benefit from a re-write to look in greater depth at the possible "why" questions that lie behind the inequities. We already know from looking at both Countdown and the DHS that inequity is a big issue, but it is not likely that meaningful change will occur until the "why" questions are addressed more forensically.</p>
<p>Response: We agree with the points highlighted and thank the reviewer for these insightful comments, which have enabled us to significantly improve on the discussion section of our paper. We have revised our discussion to better focus on both supply and demand sides of the caesarean section. Also, we have discussed the effect of health insurance coverage in birth by caesarean section. The countdown 2030 is an enormous piece of work that monitors and measure women&#8217;s, children&#8217;s, and adolescents&#8217; health in the 81 countries that account for 95% of maternal and 90% of all child deaths worldwide. We have read several publications from the countdown work to gain more insight into the issue of inequity in health outcomes. We have benefited from the insight and experience of the reviewer.</p>
</body>
</sub-article>
