<sub-article xmlns:ns0="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="editor-report" id="pbio.3000460.r004" specific-use="decision-letter">
<front-stub>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pbio.3000460.r004</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title>Decision Letter 2</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Richardson</surname>
<given-names>Lauren A</given-names>
</name>
<role>Senior Editor</role>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<permissions>
<copyright-year>2019</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>Lauren A Richardson</copyright-holder>
<license ns0:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
<license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" ns0:type="simple">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<related-object document-id="10.1371/journal.pbio.3000460" document-id-type="doi" document-type="article" id="rel-obj004" link-type="peer-reviewed-article" />
<custom-meta-group>
<custom-meta>
<meta-name>Submission Version</meta-name>
<meta-value>2</meta-value>
</custom-meta>
</custom-meta-group>
</front-stub>
<body>
<p>
<named-content content-type="letter-date">13 Aug 2019</named-content>
</p>
<p>Dear Dr Ettensohn,</p>
<p>Thank you for submitting your revised Research Article entitled "The evolution of a new cell type was associated with competition for a signaling ligand" for publication in PLOS Biology. </p>
<p>The Academic Editor and I have now assessed your revision and we're delighted to let you know that we're now editorially satisfied with your manuscript. We will publish your manuscript, assuming you are willing to meet or final production requirements. Congratulations!</p>
<p>Before we can formally accept your paper and consider it "in press", we also need to ensure that your article conforms to our guidelines. A member of our team will be in touch shortly with a set of requests. As we can't proceed until these requirements are met, your swift response will help prevent delays to publication.</p>
<p>Upon acceptance of your article, your final files will be copyedited and typeset into the final PDF. While you will have an opportunity to review these files as proofs, PLOS will only permit corrections to spelling or significant scientific errors. Therefore, please take this final revision time to assess and make any remaining major changes to your manuscript.</p>
<p>Please note that you may have the opportunity to make the peer review history publicly available. The record will include editor decision letters (with reviews) and your responses to reviewer comments. If eligible, we will contact you to opt in or out.</p>
<p>Please note that an uncorrected proof of your manuscript will be published online ahead of the final version, unless you opted out when submitting your manuscript. If, for any reason, you do not want an earlier version of your manuscript published online, uncheck the box. Should you, your institution's press office or the journal office choose to press release your paper, you will automatically be opted out of early publication. We ask that you notify us as soon as possible if you or your institution is planning to press release the article.</p>
<p>To submit your revision, please go to <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://www.editorialmanager.com/pbiology/" ns0:type="simple">https://www.editorialmanager.com/pbiology/</ext-link> and log in as an Author. Click the link labelled 'Submissions Needing Revision' to find your submission record. Your revised submission must include a cover letter, a Response to Reviewers file that provides a detailed response to the reviewers' comments (if applicable), and a track-changes file indicating any changes that you have made to the manuscript. </p>
<p>Please do not hesitate to contact me should you have any questions.</p>
<p>Sincerely,</p>
<p>Lauren A Richardson, Ph.D</p>
<p>Senior Editor</p>
<p>PLOS Biology</p>
<p>------------------------------------------------------------------------</p>
<p>DATA POLICY:</p>
<p>You may be aware of the PLOS Data Policy, which requires that all data be made available without restriction: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://journals.plos.org/plosbiology/s/data-availability" ns0:type="simple">http://journals.plos.org/plosbiology/s/data-availability</ext-link>. For more information, please also see this editorial: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.1001797" ns0:type="simple">http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.1001797</ext-link></p>
<p>Note that we do not require all raw data. Rather, we ask that all individual quantitative observations that underlie the data summarized in the figures and results of your paper be made available in one of the following forms:</p>
<p>1) Supplementary files (e.g., excel). Please ensure that all data files are uploaded as 'Supporting Information' and are invariably referred to (in the manuscript, figure legends, and the Description field when uploading your files) using the following format verbatim: S1 Data, S2 Data, etc. Multiple panels of a single or even several figures can be included as multiple sheets in one excel file that is saved using exactly the following convention: S1_Data.xlsx (using an underscore).</p>
<p>2) Deposition in a publicly available repository. Please also provide the accession code or a reviewer link so that we may view your data before publication. </p>
<p>Regardless of the method selected, please ensure that you provide the individual numerical values that underlie the summary data displayed in the following figure panels: (e.g. Figs. 2H, 3B, 5F, 6D, 7F, 8D), as they are essential for readers to assess your analysis and to reproduce it. Please also ensure that figure legends in your manuscript include information on where the underlying data can be found.</p>
<p>Please ensure that your Data Statement in the submission system accurately describes where your data can be found.</p>
<p>------------------------------------------------------------------------</p>
<p>BLOT AND GEL REPORTING REQUIREMENTS:</p>
<p>For manuscripts submitted on or after 1st July 2019, we require the original, uncropped and minimally adjusted images supporting all blot and gel results reported in an article's figures or Supporting Information files. We will require these files before a manuscript can be accepted so please prepare them now, if you have not already uploaded them. Please carefully read our guidelines for how to prepare and upload this data: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://journals.plos.org/plosbiology/s/figures#loc-blot-and-gel-reporting-requirements" ns0:type="simple">https://journals.plos.org/plosbiology/s/figures#loc-blot-and-gel-reporting-requirements</ext-link>.</p>
</body>
</sub-article>
