<sub-article xmlns:ns0="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="aggregated-review-documents" id="pone.0218838.r001" specific-use="decision-letter">
<front-stub>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0218838.r001</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title>Decision Letter 0</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Chan</surname>
<given-names>Benny K.K.</given-names>
</name>
<role>Academic Editor</role>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<permissions>
<copyright-year>2019</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>Benny K.K. Chan</copyright-holder>
<license ns0:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
<license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" ns0:type="simple">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<related-object document-id="10.1371/journal.pone.0218838" document-id-type="doi" document-type="article" id="rel-obj001" link-type="peer-reviewed-article" />
<custom-meta-group>
<custom-meta>
<meta-name>Submission Version</meta-name>
<meta-value>0</meta-value>
</custom-meta>
</custom-meta-group>
</front-stub>
<body>
<p>
<named-content content-type="letter-date">2 Jul 2019</named-content>
</p>
<p>PONE-D-19-15745</p>
<p>Spatial distribution of epibionts on olive ridley sea turtles at Playa Ostional, Costa Rica</p>
<p>PLOS ONE</p>
<p>Dear Dr. Robinson,</p>
<p>Thank you for submitting your manuscript to PLOS ONE. After careful consideration, we feel that it has merit but does not fully meet PLOS ONE&#8217;s publication criteria as it currently stands. Therefore, we invite you to submit a revised version of the manuscript that addresses the points raised during the review process.</p>
<p>We would appreciate receiving your revised manuscript by Aug 16 2019 11:59PM. When you are ready to submit your revision, log on to <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://www.editorialmanager.com/pone/" ns0:type="simple">https://www.editorialmanager.com/pone/</ext-link> and select the 'Submissions Needing Revision' folder to locate your manuscript file.</p>
<p>If you would like to make changes to your financial disclosure, please include your updated statement in your cover letter.</p>
<p>To enhance the reproducibility of your results, we recommend that if applicable you deposit your laboratory protocols in protocols.io, where a protocol can be assigned its own identifier (DOI) such that it can be cited independently in the future. For instructions see: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://journals.plos.org/plosone/s/submission-guidelines#loc-laboratory-protocols" ns0:type="simple">http://journals.plos.org/plosone/s/submission-guidelines#loc-laboratory-protocols</ext-link></p>
<p>Please include the following items when submitting your revised manuscript:</p>
<p><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>A rebuttal letter that responds to each point raised by the academic editor and reviewer(s). This letter should be uploaded as separate file and labeled 'Response to Reviewers'.</p></list-item><list-item><p>A marked-up copy of your manuscript that highlights changes made to the original version. This file should be uploaded as separate file and labeled 'Revised Manuscript with Track Changes'.</p></list-item><list-item><p>An unmarked version of your revised paper without tracked changes. This file should be uploaded as separate file and labeled 'Manuscript'.</p></list-item></list></p>
<p>Please note while forming your response, if your article is accepted, you may have the opportunity to make the peer review history publicly available. The record will include editor decision letters (with reviews) and your responses to reviewer comments. If eligible, we will contact you to opt in or out.</p>
<p>We look forward to receiving your revised manuscript.</p>
<p>Kind regards,</p>
<p>Benny K.K. Chan, Ph.D</p>
<p>Academic Editor</p>
<p>PLOS ONE</p>
<p>Journal Requirements:</p>
<p>1. When submitting your revision, we need you to address these additional requirements.</p>
<p>Please ensure that your manuscript meets PLOS ONE's style requirements, including those for file naming. The PLOS ONE style templates can be found at</p>
<p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://www.journals.plos.org/plosone/s/file?id=wjVg/PLOSOne_formatting_sample_main_body.pdf" ns0:type="simple">http://www.journals.plos.org/plosone/s/file?id=wjVg/PLOSOne_formatting_sample_main_body.pdf</ext-link> and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://www.journals.plos.org/plosone/s/file?id=ba62/PLOSOne_formatting_sample_title_authors_affiliations.pdf" ns0:type="simple">http://www.journals.plos.org/plosone/s/file?id=ba62/PLOSOne_formatting_sample_title_authors_affiliations.pdf</ext-link></p>
<p>Additional Editor Comments:</p>
<p>Dear authors,</p>
<p>Your MS will need revisions. Please revise the MS and send back a letter point by point how the comments were addressed. I will send to the same reviewers for comments again.</p>
<p>Best wishes,</p>
<p>Benny</p>
<p>[Note: HTML markup is below. Please do not edit.]</p>
<p>Reviewers' comments:</p>
<p>Reviewer's Responses to Questions</p>
<p><bold>Comments to the Author</bold></p>
<p>1. Is the manuscript technically sound, and do the data support the conclusions?</p>
<p>The manuscript must describe a technically sound piece of scientific research with data that supports the conclusions. Experiments must have been conducted rigorously, with appropriate controls, replication, and sample sizes. The conclusions must be drawn appropriately based on the data presented. </p>
<p>Reviewer #1: No</p>
<p>Reviewer #2: Yes</p>
<p>**********</p>
<p>2. Has the statistical analysis been performed appropriately and rigorously? </p>
<p>Reviewer #1: No</p>
<p>Reviewer #2: Yes</p>
<p>**********</p>
<p>3. Have the authors made all data underlying the findings in their manuscript fully available?</p>
<p>The <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://www.plosone.org/static/policies.action#sharing" ns0:type="simple">PLOS Data policy</ext-link> requires authors to make all data underlying the findings described in their manuscript fully available without restriction, with rare exception (please refer to the Data Availability Statement in the manuscript PDF file). The data should be provided as part of the manuscript or its supporting information, or deposited to a public repository. For example, in addition to summary statistics, the data points behind means, medians and variance measures should be available. If there are restrictions on publicly sharing data&#8212;e.g. participant privacy or use of data from a third party&#8212;those must be specified.</p>
<p>Reviewer #1: Yes</p>
<p>Reviewer #2: Yes</p>
<p>**********</p>
<p>4. Is the manuscript presented in an intelligible fashion and written in standard English?</p>
<p>PLOS ONE does not copyedit accepted manuscripts, so the language in submitted articles must be clear, correct, and unambiguous. Any typographical or grammatical errors should be corrected at revision, so please note any specific errors here.</p>
<p>Reviewer #1: Yes</p>
<p>Reviewer #2: Yes</p>
<p>**********</p>
<p>5. Review Comments to the Author</p>
<p>Please use the space provided to explain your answers to the questions above. You may also include additional comments for the author, including concerns about dual publication, research ethics, or publication ethics. (Please upload your review as an attachment if it exceeds 20,000 characters)</p>
<p>Reviewer #1: The manuscript explores epibiont distribution on olive ridley sea turtles. The study is interesting but there are some critical problems to be corrected.</p>
<p>The manuscript claims that authors made quantitative analyses on the epibiont communities. However, the number of individuals and biomass should be divided by areas (cm2) of each body part, i.e., head, carapace, plastron, and tail, for the fair comparison.</p>
<p>It is unclear that how the p-values were corrected for the multiple comparison.</p>
<p>The manuscript lacks the discussion on the factors driving spatial variation in the distribution of epibionts.</p>
<p>I recommend to conduct more analyses on epibiont community structures, such as comparison of diversity index, and community compositions with nMDS ordination plot.</p>
<p>Reviewer #2: Review, Robinson et al.</p>
<p>Dear editor,</p>
<p>This manuscript provides results that suggest that sampling of epibionts of sea turtles should not only take place from the carapace or plastron, but indeed from all areas of the turtle, including the softer parts. Although the majority of epibionts confined to barnacles, the data (and the methods) might be useful for biologists working with conservation and epizoic organisms in general. I liked the approach and it is merited that we need to consider epibiont communities on the whole host rather than just the most convenient area. I think the authors write quite well around the problem of &#8220;sampling bias&#8221; if certain structures are only sampled.</p>
<p>I have some comments but recommend publication after a minor revision. The language is sound and sufficiently scientific, the perspective for the readers of Plos One is wide enough and the tests and field experiments seems appropriate.</p>
<p>Comments:</p>
<p>It would be nice with some photo material of the turtles and their epibionts. One of the advantages of publishing in Plos is that they provide high quality photo plates. Not many people might know what barnacles have been found and this might help other conservation biologists with limited time/lust for taxonomic identification of epibionts.</p>
<p>L49: not wide-range, but wide range</p>
<p>L53: insert can shed light &#8220;on&#8221;..</p>
<p>L54: What is varied associates really? Improve language</p>
<p>L55: How can the epibionts tell anything about the behavior of the hosts? Explain</p>
<p>L129-130: How can you really know? I think this argument is kind of vague. Think it is better to re-formulate or further explain how this &#8220;ensurance&#8221; is established. As I understand it, the area within each arribada where sampling took place is quite &#8220;small&#8221;</p>
<p>L145: did the authors define CCL upon first mentioning? I can&#8217;t find it, so please explain first and then abbreviate</p>
<p>L163 and onwards: Write genus name as single letter after first mentioning - this is proper taxonomic standard</p>
<p>L170: Why do you call it Platylepadidae? Is it referring to a familiy name (-dae)? Then why italics? I do not know the code of the zoological nomenclature entirely, but this seems odd.</p>
<p>L175: Test tests?</p>
<p>L222-225: What is this &#8220;ecology&#8221; the authors refer to here? What is &#8220;ecological importance&#8221;? I find this very vague and it doesn&#8217;t really say anything substantial</p>
<p>L227-228: Yes, the authors and right and they proved their point. However, I would like to see a discussion of potential epibionts that could have been overlooked. What about parasites embedded within the skin? What about &#8220;microorganisms&#8221; as the authors write about in the introduction? I do not know, but is there any knowledge on the bacteria on sea turtles? Can these be studied with the same approach here and species determined? This part could be relatively short and precise, but it might be good to consider that this method does not grant access to all &#8220;epibionts&#8221; per se</p>
<p>L241: I do not understand this expectation. Sea turtles (perhaps not this species?) shed their scutes and some even their skin. Any epibiont, particularly permanently attached barnacles would then fall off during successive molts. A natural expectation would be that the scutes at anytime hold fewer epibionts given that it is regularly replaced. I think the authors should write in the introduction that sampling only on the parts that are actually being shed might result in significant &#8220;sampling bias&#8221;. But I can appreciate if the authors are careful with such statements.</p>
<p>L255: it would be nice with a reference here and some elaboration of how turtle species differ in these properties. It appears a bit vague.</p>
<p>L263: The authors might have a point, but it cannot be out ruled that they spotted juvenile Chelonibia. I would mention this.</p>
<p>L266-267: This needs a reference or proper photo documentation. Is it the cyprid larva that digs into the tissue or is it the adults? Is the burrowing similar to the balanomorphan barnacle Xenobalanus globicipitis that settles and burrows into the integument of whales? If no, what is the difference? Have the two modes of &#8220;digging&#8221; been observed?</p>
<p>L306: This is plausible, but as the authors note, barnacles were scraped off with instruments. Barnacles generally attach firmly. I do not think it is likely that they are being scraped off, although some might. Would selection not impede settlement in those areas if it affected the survival of the species (i.e., they fall off and die)? Just a thought. I can buy it if the authors do not wish to go into detail.</p>
<p>L420: This reference has a bracket around it.</p>
<p>I recommend publication after a minor revision.</p>
<p>**********</p>
<p>6. PLOS authors have the option to publish the peer review history of their article (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://journals.plos.org/plosone/s/editorial-and-peer-review-process#loc-peer-review-history" ns0:type="simple">what does this mean?</ext-link>). If published, this will include your full peer review and any attached files.</p>
<p>If you choose &#8220;no&#8221;, your identity will remain anonymous but your review may still be made public.</p>
<p><bold>Do you want your identity to be public for this peer review?</bold> For information about this choice, including consent withdrawal, please see our <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://www.plos.org/privacy-policy" ns0:type="simple">Privacy Policy</ext-link>.</p>
<p>Reviewer #1: No</p>
<p>Reviewer #2: No</p>
<p>[NOTE: If reviewer comments were submitted as an attachment file, they will be attached to this email and accessible via the submission site. Please log into your account, locate the manuscript record, and check for the action link "View Attachments". If this link does not appear, there are no attachment files to be viewed.]</p>
<p>While revising your submission, please upload your figure files to the Preflight Analysis and Conversion Engine (PACE) digital diagnostic tool, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://pacev2.apexcovantage.com/" ns0:type="simple">https://pacev2.apexcovantage.com/</ext-link>. PACE helps ensure that figures meet PLOS requirements. To use PACE, you must first register as a user. Registration is free. Then, login and navigate to the UPLOAD tab, where you will find detailed instructions on how to use the tool. If you encounter any issues or have any questions when using PACE, please email us at <email ns0:type="simple">figures@plos.org</email>. Please note that Supporting Information files do not need this step.</p>
</body>
</sub-article>
