<sub-article xmlns:ns0="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="aggregated-review-documents" id="pone.0219639.r001" specific-use="decision-letter">
<front-stub>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0219639.r001</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title>Decision Letter 0</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Poulter</surname>
<given-names>Benjamin</given-names>
</name>
<role>Academic Editor</role>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<permissions>
<copyright-year>2019</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>Benjamin Poulter</copyright-holder>
<license ns0:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
<license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" ns0:type="simple">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<related-object document-id="10.1371/journal.pone.0219639" document-id-type="doi" document-type="article" id="rel-obj001" link-type="peer-reviewed-article" />
<custom-meta-group>
<custom-meta>
<meta-name>Submission Version</meta-name>
<meta-value>0</meta-value>
</custom-meta>
</custom-meta-group>
</front-stub>
<body>
<p>
<named-content content-type="letter-date">2 Aug 2019</named-content>
</p>
<p>PONE-D-19-17266</p>
<p>Downscaling Satellite Soil Moisture using Geomorphometry and Machine Learning</p>
<p>PLOS ONE</p>
<p>Dear Dr. Vargas,</p>
<p>Thank you for submitting your manuscript to PLOS ONE. After careful consideration, we feel that it has merit but does not fully meet PLOS ONE&#8217;s publication criteria as it currently stands. Therefore, we invite you to submit a revised version of the manuscript that addresses the points raised during the review process.</p>
<p>We would appreciate receiving your revised manuscript by Sep 16 2019 11:59PM. When you are ready to submit your revision, log on to <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://www.editorialmanager.com/pone/" ns0:type="simple">https://www.editorialmanager.com/pone/</ext-link> and select the 'Submissions Needing Revision' folder to locate your manuscript file.</p>
<p>If you would like to make changes to your financial disclosure, please include your updated statement in your cover letter.</p>
<p>To enhance the reproducibility of your results, we recommend that if applicable you deposit your laboratory protocols in protocols.io, where a protocol can be assigned its own identifier (DOI) such that it can be cited independently in the future. For instructions see: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://journals.plos.org/plosone/s/submission-guidelines#loc-laboratory-protocols" ns0:type="simple">http://journals.plos.org/plosone/s/submission-guidelines#loc-laboratory-protocols</ext-link></p>
<p>Please include the following items when submitting your revised manuscript:</p>
<p><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>A rebuttal letter that responds to each point raised by the academic editor and reviewer(s). This letter should be uploaded as separate file and labeled 'Response to Reviewers'.</p></list-item><list-item><p>A marked-up copy of your manuscript that highlights changes made to the original version. This file should be uploaded as separate file and labeled 'Revised Manuscript with Track Changes'.</p></list-item><list-item><p>An unmarked version of your revised paper without tracked changes. This file should be uploaded as separate file and labeled 'Manuscript'.</p></list-item></list></p>
<p>Please note while forming your response, if your article is accepted, you may have the opportunity to make the peer review history publicly available. The record will include editor decision letters (with reviews) and your responses to reviewer comments. If eligible, we will contact you to opt in or out.</p>
<p>We look forward to receiving your revised manuscript.</p>
<p>Kind regards,</p>
<p>Benjamin Poulter</p>
<p>Academic Editor</p>
<p>PLOS ONE</p>
<p>Journal Requirements:</p>
<p>When submitting your revision, we need you to address these additional requirements.</p>
<p>1. Please ensure that your manuscript meets PLOS ONE's style requirements, including those for file naming. The PLOS ONE style templates can be found at</p>
<p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://www.journals.plos.org/plosone/s/file?id=wjVg/PLOSOne_formatting_sample_main_body.pdf" ns0:type="simple">http://www.journals.plos.org/plosone/s/file?id=wjVg/PLOSOne_formatting_sample_main_body.pdf</ext-link> and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://www.journals.plos.org/plosone/s/file?id=ba62/PLOSOne_formatting_sample_title_authors_affiliations.pdf" ns0:type="simple">http://www.journals.plos.org/plosone/s/file?id=ba62/PLOSOne_formatting_sample_title_authors_affiliations.pdf</ext-link></p>
<p>2. Thank you for stating the following in the Acknowledgments Section of your manuscript:</p>
<p>"MG acknowledges a fellowship from CONACyT. RV acknowledges support from the National Science Foundation CIF21 DIBBs (Grant #1724843)."</p>
<p>We note that you have provided funding information that is not currently declared in your Funding Statement. However, funding information should not appear in the Acknowledgments section or other areas of your manuscript. We will only publish funding information present in the Funding Statement section of the online submission form.</p>
<p>Please remove any funding-related text from the manuscript and let us know how you would like to update your Funding Statement. Currently, your Funding Statement reads as follows:</p>
<p>"RV acknowledges support from the National Science Foundation CIF21 DIBBs (Grant #1724843). "</p>
<p><list list-type="order"><list-item><p>Please provide an amended Funding Statement that declares *all* the funding or sources of support received during this specific study (whether external or internal to your organization) as detailed online in our guide for authors at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://journals.plos.org/plosone/s/submit-now" ns0:type="simple">http://journals.plos.org/plosone/s/submit-now</ext-link>&#160;</p></list-item></list><list list-type="order"><list-item><p>Please state what role the funders took in the study.&#160; If any authors received a salary from any of your funders, please state which authors and which funder. If the funders had no role, please state: "The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript."</p></list-item></list></p>
<p>c. Please include your amended statements within your cover letter; we will change the online submission form on your behalf.</p>
<p>3. We note that you have stated that you will provide repository information for your data at acceptance. Should your manuscript be accepted for publication, we will hold it until you provide the relevant accession numbers or DOIs necessary to access your data. If you wish to make changes to your Data Availability statement, please describe these changes in your cover letter and we will update your Data Availability statement to reflect the information you provide.</p>
<p>4. Please include captions for your Supporting Information files at the end of your manuscript, and update any in-text citations to match accordingly. Please see our Supporting Information guidelines for more information: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://journals.plos.org/plosone/s/supporting-information" ns0:type="simple">http://journals.plos.org/plosone/s/supporting-information</ext-link></p>
<p>Additional Editor Comments:</p>
<p>Dear Authors,</p>
<p>I have received two reviews for your manuscript, both consider the work interesting and important for publication. One reviewer has several detailed questions that need to be addressed and will improve the manuscript's clarity and robustness. Consider the decision between and minor and major revision as the responses need to be addressed in detail.</p>
<p>Ben</p>
<p>[Note: HTML markup is below. Please do not edit.]</p>
<p>Reviewers' comments:</p>
<p>Reviewer's Responses to Questions</p>
<p><bold>Comments to the Author</bold></p>
<p>1. Is the manuscript technically sound, and do the data support the conclusions?</p>
<p>The manuscript must describe a technically sound piece of scientific research with data that supports the conclusions. Experiments must have been conducted rigorously, with appropriate controls, replication, and sample sizes. The conclusions must be drawn appropriately based on the data presented. </p>
<p>Reviewer #1: Yes</p>
<p>Reviewer #2: Partly</p>
<p>**********</p>
<p>2. Has the statistical analysis been performed appropriately and rigorously? </p>
<p>Reviewer #1: Yes</p>
<p>Reviewer #2: No</p>
<p>**********</p>
<p>3. Have the authors made all data underlying the findings in their manuscript fully available?</p>
<p>The <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://www.plosone.org/static/policies.action#sharing" ns0:type="simple">PLOS Data policy</ext-link> requires authors to make all data underlying the findings described in their manuscript fully available without restriction, with rare exception (please refer to the Data Availability Statement in the manuscript PDF file). The data should be provided as part of the manuscript or its supporting information, or deposited to a public repository. For example, in addition to summary statistics, the data points behind means, medians and variance measures should be available. If there are restrictions on publicly sharing data&#8212;e.g. participant privacy or use of data from a third party&#8212;those must be specified.</p>
<p>Reviewer #1: Yes</p>
<p>Reviewer #2: No</p>
<p>**********</p>
<p>4. Is the manuscript presented in an intelligible fashion and written in standard English?</p>
<p>PLOS ONE does not copyedit accepted manuscripts, so the language in submitted articles must be clear, correct, and unambiguous. Any typographical or grammatical errors should be corrected at revision, so please note any specific errors here.</p>
<p>Reviewer #1: Yes</p>
<p>Reviewer #2: Yes</p>
<p>**********</p>
<p>5. Review Comments to the Author</p>
<p>Please use the space provided to explain your answers to the questions above. You may also include additional comments for the author, including concerns about dual publication, research ethics, or publication ethics. (Please upload your review as an attachment if it exceeds 20,000 characters)</p>
<p>Reviewer #1: I enjoyed reading the paper by Guevara et al., which addresses the downscaling of soil moisture data using geo-morphometry. The work is useful and very well explained in the manuscript. I recommend to accept it with few minor comments:</p>
<p>1. Authors can add some references about different disaggregation methods applied on soil moisture datasets for downscaling, specifically related to topography or geomorphology, like:</p>
<p>Pellenq et al 2003, A disaggregation scheme for soil moisture based on topography and soil depth</p>
<p>2. Line 193: It will be nice to provide explicitly what are the primary hydrologically meaningful terrain parameters authors are referring to.</p>
<p>3. A little description of these terrain parameters are required to be discussed.</p>
<p>4. It will be great to add some discussion about the systematic error (Bias)</p>
<p>Reviewer #2: The manuscript by Guevara and Vargas, entitled 'Downscaling Satellite Soil Moisture using Geomorphometry and Machine Learning', covers an interesting topic appropriate for PLOS ONE. The authors developed an approach to downscale the annual soil moisture at 25 km resolution derived from ESA CCI satellite products to 1 km resolution using a machine learning approach. A set of geomorphological parameters were applied to train the model using a k-NN algorithm. I think the study is original in the sense that it provides an alternative approach for downscaling methodologies. However, I feel the downscaled results were not well justified and the writing are not clear and can be strengthened. I have several concerns as listed below:</p>
<p>- The title is a bit misleading as it's too generalized. The current title doesn't suggest for what temporal resolution (annual or monthly), nor for what regions this approach can be applied. Validating the results for the US continent doesn't necessarily prove that it can be applied in other regions that have different climate (e.g. high latitudes and tropics).</p>
<p>- The calculation of terrain parameters. It is surprised to see that some of the parameters in Figure 2 show fairly low values with almost none spatial heterogeneity. Is that a rendering problem or due to the normalization? This seems incorrect. For example, the wetness index is supposed to have significant spatial heterogeneity. See HYDRO1K or HydroSHEDS products for some of these parameters.</p>
<p>- The downscaled 1k soil moisture. The results don&#8217;t suggest that it maintain the original values of the satellite product. Why the downscaled results seem to have a systematical lower value than the original one? Is that because of the calculation of terrain parameters? Also, the spatial heterogeneity is not higher in the downscaled product as it&#8217;s supposed to be. Downscaled products are supposed to provide more details at a higher resolution. The legend of Figure 3 and Figure S2 are not consistent, which makes it hard to compare the downscaled with the original visually.</p>
<p>- The parameters used in the machine learning. This study uses a few terrain parameters to train their model - Here is an implicit assumption that the soil moisture is mainly controlled by geomorphological information. But soil moisture is proved to be strongly influenced by vegetation via its regulation of evapotranspiration.</p>
<p>Specific comments:</p>
<p>Paragraph Line58-68. It seems the first outline sentence doesn&#8217;t match the following content.</p>
<p>Line 164-165: need to be more specific on how you did the downscale.</p>
<p>Line 175: not a standard format. Is this a personal communication?</p>
<p>Line 177: why the ISMN is unlike the NASMD? Please elaborate</p>
<p>Line 181-182? Be specific on what parameters are used, or at least mention the list in Table S1.</p>
<p>Line 198: how to harmonize? Not clear</p>
<p>Line 199: where is section 2.3?</p>
<p>Line 214: what soil moisture map ? daily or annual? If it is daily, how did you do the aggregation?</p>
<p>Line 241-249. I don&#8217;t understand why a spatial interpolation for R2 map is needed. I don't think an interpolated R2 can be used for justification. Using an Ordinary Kriging doesn't make sense as Ordinary Kriging assumes your R2 points is spatially-correlated.</p>
<p>Supplement Figure 3A. There is no dotted blue line.</p>
<p>Table 1. The Unit of RMSE is needed.</p>
<p>**********</p>
<p>6. PLOS authors have the option to publish the peer review history of their article (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://journals.plos.org/plosone/s/editorial-and-peer-review-process#loc-peer-review-history" ns0:type="simple">what does this mean?</ext-link>). If published, this will include your full peer review and any attached files.</p>
<p>If you choose &#8220;no&#8221;, your identity will remain anonymous but your review may still be made public.</p>
<p><bold>Do you want your identity to be public for this peer review?</bold> For information about this choice, including consent withdrawal, please see our <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://www.plos.org/privacy-policy" ns0:type="simple">Privacy Policy</ext-link>.</p>
<p>Reviewer #1: No</p>
<p>Reviewer #2: No</p>
<p>[NOTE: If reviewer comments were submitted as an attachment file, they will be attached to this email and accessible via the submission site. Please log into your account, locate the manuscript record, and check for the action link "View Attachments". If this link does not appear, there are no attachment files to be viewed.]</p>
<p>While revising your submission, please upload your figure files to the Preflight Analysis and Conversion Engine (PACE) digital diagnostic tool, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://pacev2.apexcovantage.com/" ns0:type="simple">https://pacev2.apexcovantage.com/</ext-link>. PACE helps ensure that figures meet PLOS requirements. To use PACE, you must first register as a user. Registration is free. Then, login and navigate to the UPLOAD tab, where you will find detailed instructions on how to use the tool. If you encounter any issues or have any questions when using PACE, please email us at <email ns0:type="simple">figures@plos.org</email>. Please note that Supporting Information files do not need this step.</p>
</body>
</sub-article>
