<sub-article xmlns:ns0="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="author-comment" id="pone.0221784.r002">
<front-stub>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0221784.r002</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title>Author response to Decision Letter 0</article-title>
</title-group>
<related-object document-id="10.1371/journal.pone.0221784" document-id-type="doi" document-type="peer-reviewed-article" id="rel-obj002" link-type="rebutted-decision-letter" object-id="10.1371/journal.pone.0221784.r001" object-id-type="doi" object-type="decision-letter" />
<custom-meta-group>
<custom-meta>
<meta-name>Submission Version</meta-name>
<meta-value>1</meta-value>
</custom-meta>
</custom-meta-group>
</front-stub>
<body>
<p>
<named-content content-type="author-response-date">28 Jun 2019</named-content>
</p>
<p>23.6.2019</p>
<p>Dear Editor</p>
<p>Enclosed please find our revised manuscript PONE-D-19-14839 entitled &#8220;Cognitive performance in multiple sclerosis: A Long-term look on the bright side&#8221;, which we submit after revision after we addressed the points raised during the review process as follows:</p>
<p>Comment 1. Overall, there needs to be consistencies in terminologies throughout the manuscript. Low cognitive, moderate cognitive, and high cognitive performance or severe cognitive, moderate cognitive, and low cognitive impairments. </p>
<p>Specifically, define cognitive resilience in light of the terminology you choose. These will facilitate better comprehension of the manuscript.</p>
<p>Response: As suggested, we have better defined the cognitive terminologies throughout the manuscript, using the terminology of low cognitive, moderate cognitive, and high cognitive performance.</p>
<p>Accordingly, we have defined cognitive resilience as patients with high cognitive performance after a long-disease duration.</p>
<p>Comment 2. Results: Page 6, end of the first paragraph: As shown in Table 1, there was also no significant difference in visual functions. This fact needs to be included in the narrative as well.</p>
<p>Response: We added to the narrative the fact that there was no significant difference in visual function, Results end of first paragraph.. </p>
<p>Comment 3. Figure 1 is exactly the same information as in Table 2. Either one, plus the narrative should be sufficient.</p>
<p>Response: We omitted Table 2 and added the data to the narrative. Accordingly we changed the order of the figures (Figure 1is now Figure 2, and Figure 2 is now Figure 1), and explained in the narrative the numbers of the inconsistency groups.</p>
<p>Comment 4. Discussion: Page 7, end of the first paragraph: Can you discuss some of side effects of DMDs?</p>
<p>Added to the Discussion. </p>
<p>Comment 5. Page 9: beginning of the second paragraph: If this is a prospective study, how is it possible that data was collected prospectively?</p>
<p>We mentioned that the study was retrospective cross-sectional, but the data was collected prospectively &#8211; as we wanted to highlight the point that patients were evaluated on an on-going basis prospectively. As it seems confusing we omitted the term prospectively. </p>
<p>. </p>
<p>I hope you will find the revised version merit for publication in PlosOne.</p>
<p>With respects</p>
<p>Anat Achiron, MD, PhD</p>
<p>Sheba Medical Center </p>
<p>Tel-Hashomer, 52621, Israel.</p>
<p>Tel: 972-3-5303932; Fax: 972-3-5348186</p>
<p>Email: <email ns0:type="simple">Anat.Achiron@sheba.health.gov.il</email></p>
<supplementary-material id="pone.0221784.s001" mimetype="application/vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.wordprocessingml.document" position="float" ns0:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0221784.s001" ns0:type="simple">
<label>Attachment</label>
<caption>
<p>Submitted filename: <named-content content-type="submitted-filename">Achiron.PlosOne.Response to Reviewers.docx</named-content></p>
</caption>
</supplementary-material>
</body>
</sub-article>
