<sub-article xmlns:ns0="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="aggregated-review-documents" id="pone.0221887.r001" specific-use="decision-letter">
<front-stub>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0221887.r001</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title>Decision Letter 0</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Kriwet</surname>
<given-names>J&#252;rgen</given-names>
</name>
<role>Academic Editor</role>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<permissions>
<copyright-year>2019</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>J&#252;rgen Kriwet</copyright-holder>
<license ns0:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
<license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" ns0:type="simple">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<related-object document-id="10.1371/journal.pone.0221887" document-id-type="doi" document-type="article" id="rel-obj001" link-type="peer-reviewed-article" />
<custom-meta-group>
<custom-meta>
<meta-name>Submission Version</meta-name>
<meta-value>0</meta-value>
</custom-meta>
</custom-meta-group>
</front-stub>
<body>
<p>
<named-content content-type="letter-date">7 Aug 2019</named-content>
</p>
<p>PONE-D-19-16788</p>
<p>Resource partitioning among brachiopods and bivalves at ancient hydrocarbon seeps: a hypothesis</p>
<p>PLOS ONE</p>
<p>Dear Prof. Peckmann,</p>
<p>Thank you for submitting your manuscript to PLOS ONE. After careful consideration, we feel that it has merit but does not fully meet PLOS ONE&#8217;s publication criteria as it currently stands. Therefore, we invite you to submit a revised version of the manuscript that addresses the points raised during the review process.</p>
<p>We would appreciate receiving your revised manuscript by Sep 21 2019 11:59PM. When you are ready to submit your revision, log on to <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://www.editorialmanager.com/pone/" ns0:type="simple">https://www.editorialmanager.com/pone/</ext-link> and select the 'Submissions Needing Revision' folder to locate your manuscript file.</p>
<p>If you would like to make changes to your financial disclosure, please include your updated statement in your cover letter.</p>
<p>To enhance the reproducibility of your results, we recommend that if applicable you deposit your laboratory protocols in protocols.io, where a protocol can be assigned its own identifier (DOI) such that it can be cited independently in the future. For instructions see: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://journals.plos.org/plosone/s/submission-guidelines#loc-laboratory-protocols" ns0:type="simple">http://journals.plos.org/plosone/s/submission-guidelines#loc-laboratory-protocols</ext-link></p>
<p>Please include the following items when submitting your revised manuscript:</p>
<p><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>A rebuttal letter that responds to each point raised by the academic editor and reviewer(s). This letter should be uploaded as separate file and labeled 'Response to Reviewers'.</p></list-item><list-item><p>A marked-up copy of your manuscript that highlights changes made to the original version. This file should be uploaded as separate file and labeled 'Revised Manuscript with Track Changes'.</p></list-item><list-item><p>An unmarked version of your revised paper without tracked changes. This file should be uploaded as separate file and labeled 'Manuscript'.</p></list-item></list></p>
<p>Please note while forming your response, if your article is accepted, you may have the opportunity to make the peer review history publicly available. The record will include editor decision letters (with reviews) and your responses to reviewer comments. If eligible, we will contact you to opt in or out.</p>
<p>We look forward to receiving your revised manuscript.</p>
<p>Kind regards,</p>
<p>J&#252;rgen Kriwet</p>
<p>Academic Editor</p>
<p>PLOS ONE</p>
<p>Journal Requirements:</p>
<p>When submitting your revision, we need you to address these additional requirements.</p>
<p>Please ensure that your manuscript meets PLOS ONE's style requirements, including those for file naming. The PLOS ONE style templates can be found at</p>
<p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://www.journals.plos.org/plosone/s/file?id=wjVg/PLOSOne_formatting_sample_main_body.pdf" ns0:type="simple">http://www.journals.plos.org/plosone/s/file?id=wjVg/PLOSOne_formatting_sample_main_body.pdf</ext-link> and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://www.journals.plos.org/plosone/s/file?id=ba62/PLOSOne_formatting_sample_title_authors_affiliations.pdf" ns0:type="simple">http://www.journals.plos.org/plosone/s/file?id=ba62/PLOSOne_formatting_sample_title_authors_affiliations.pdf</ext-link></p>
<p>Additional Editor Comments (if provided):</p>
<p>Dear authors,</p>
<p>This manuscript represents a very interesting study that has a lot of merits. Nevertheless, I would like to ask you to carefully address alll comments of the two reviewers.</p>
<p>Best wishes,</p>
<p>J&#252;rgen</p>
<p>[Note: HTML markup is below. Please do not edit.]</p>
<p>Reviewers' comments:</p>
<p>Reviewer's Responses to Questions</p>
<p><bold>Comments to the Author</bold></p>
<p>1. Is the manuscript technically sound, and do the data support the conclusions?</p>
<p>The manuscript must describe a technically sound piece of scientific research with data that supports the conclusions. Experiments must have been conducted rigorously, with appropriate controls, replication, and sample sizes. The conclusions must be drawn appropriately based on the data presented. </p>
<p>Reviewer #1: Yes</p>
<p>Reviewer #2: Yes</p>
<p>**********</p>
<p>2. Has the statistical analysis been performed appropriately and rigorously? </p>
<p>Reviewer #1: Yes</p>
<p>Reviewer #2: Yes</p>
<p>**********</p>
<p>3. Have the authors made all data underlying the findings in their manuscript fully available?</p>
<p>The <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://www.plosone.org/static/policies.action#sharing" ns0:type="simple">PLOS Data policy</ext-link> requires authors to make all data underlying the findings described in their manuscript fully available without restriction, with rare exception (please refer to the Data Availability Statement in the manuscript PDF file). The data should be provided as part of the manuscript or its supporting information, or deposited to a public repository. For example, in addition to summary statistics, the data points behind means, medians and variance measures should be available. If there are restrictions on publicly sharing data&#8212;e.g. participant privacy or use of data from a third party&#8212;those must be specified.</p>
<p>Reviewer #1: Yes</p>
<p>Reviewer #2: Yes</p>
<p>**********</p>
<p>4. Is the manuscript presented in an intelligible fashion and written in standard English?</p>
<p>PLOS ONE does not copyedit accepted manuscripts, so the language in submitted articles must be clear, correct, and unambiguous. Any typographical or grammatical errors should be corrected at revision, so please note any specific errors here.</p>
<p>Reviewer #1: Yes</p>
<p>Reviewer #2: Yes</p>
<p>**********</p>
<p>5. Review Comments to the Author</p>
<p>Please use the space provided to explain your answers to the questions above. You may also include additional comments for the author, including concerns about dual publication, research ethics, or publication ethics. (Please upload your review as an attachment if it exceeds 20,000 characters)</p>
<p>Reviewer #1: This is a review of manuscript &#8222;Resource partitioning among brachiopods and bivalves at ancient hydrocarbon seeps: a hypothesis&#8221; by Steffen Kiel and Joern Peckmann. The manuscript tackles and interesting topic of seemingly contrasting brachiopod and bivalve evolutionary histories at seeps throughout the Phanerozoic. The authors present an interesting hypothesis that bivalves and brachiopods utilized different resources, and that the contrasting evolutionary pathways are apparent rather than real. Authors present evidence to support this hypothesis, which makes the manuscript a quality work eligible for publication after a minor revision.</p>
<p>I have reviewed the previous version of this manuscript, where I have pointed several drawbacks in the reasoning, which were improved since then. The manuscript is properly referenced, although there are several important references missing, as I outline below. There are some minor drawbacks left to be corrected, outlined below.:</p>
<p>Line 40: please don&#8217;t get overly enthusiastic, it is difficult to judge what is most, and what is least extreme environment, it all depends on for whom; &#8220;&#8230;a similar pattern was also seen at deep-sea hydrothermal vents and hydrocarbon seeps&#8221; is enough</p>
<p>Line 182: we are unable to say whether they indeed have never developed methanotrophic symbioses, or they developed them only to have those symbioses extinct; better to write: Remarkable in this context is that other bivalve families with intracellular symbionts have not developed methanotrophic symbioses, or have not developed methanotrophic symbioses that would survive to the present day</p>
<p>Line 261-263: Phreagena kilmeri, rather than Archivesica kilmeri (check out vesicomyid taxonomy update paper by Krylova and Sahling (2010), PLoS one; line 262: C. pacifica, rather than P. pacifica</p>
<p>Line 308-309: Remove the sentence &#8220;Despite the presence of early diagenetic fibrous cement, Anarhynchia smithi probably lived in a low sulfide environment.&#8221; It doesn&#8217;t bring anything into the discussion, later you give some reasons why this might have been a low sulfide seep.</p>
<p>Line 332-333: There are two Greylock Butte seep deposits; one contains micrite, mass accumulations of Halorella up to 10 cm along longer axis, and no other fossils; the second Greylock Butte deposit contains somewhat rare Halorella up to 3-4 cm along longer axis, and some molluscs (anomalodesmatan and modiomorphid bivalves, among others); it is not true that both seep deposits in Oregon contain mass accumulations of Halorella, both are different, with second one being somewhat similar to Turkish deposit; please rewrite accordingly.</p>
<p>Line 350-351: remove &#8220;which, in turn, was suitable for the filter-feeding brachiopods&#8221;. Unnecessary.</p>
<p>Line 385-386: Eucalathis methanophila at Omagari occurs in some sort of monospecific brachiopod accumulations, although it doesn&#8217;t for such mass accumulations as dimerelloids did, please consider that; please add citation of Hryniewicz et al. (2019), describing another non-dimerelloid brachiopod from seep, Neoliothyrina nakremi</p>
<p>Another figure, with two schematic subfigures illustrating geochemical gradients and fauna at low-sulfide seeps with dimerelloids, and high sulfide seeps with bivalves, respectively, would be useful in this manuscript.</p>
<p>Table 1: clarify why you asterisk fossil genera erected after 1995 (presumably because after Campbell and Bottjer paper); you should asterisk also extant genera with fossil record erected after 1995 (they were unknown for Campbell and Bottjer, just as the fossil genera were)</p>
<p>Neogene:</p>
<p>Cubatea, rather than Cubathea, consider asterisking Elliptiolucina, Meganodontia according to my previous comments</p>
<p>Adulomya vs. Pleurophopsis: in your (SK) recent paper on Japanese Neogene vesis you consider Adulomya and Pleurophopsis as synonyms, with Pleurophopsis having priority. These seems to be true at least for Neogene species. Please be consistent here.</p>
<p>Samiolus from your 2017 paper (SK) paper on Miocene chemosymbiotic seep bivalves from Italy is missing &#8211; why? Also &#8220;Anodontia&#8221; from Ca&#8217;Fornace is missing (citation: Kiel et al. 2018), and Megaxinus from Stirone river (citation: Kiel and Taviani 2018), please complement the reference list and adjust fig. 1 according to missing genera</p>
<p>Paleogene:</p>
<p>Cubatea, not Cubathea</p>
<p>add Rhacothyas (citation: Hryniewicz et al. 2019), also Solemya species recorded there; adjust figure 1</p>
<p>Adulomya/Pleurophopsis problem again</p>
<p>Jurassic: Please note that there were 15 seep carbonates in Sassenfjorden area, with 3 of them Jurassic in age and the 8 Cretaceous (remainder not dated; details of stratigraphy in Wierzbowski et al. 2011, available from me on request). Therefore, putting all Sassenfjorden seep carbonates into Early Cretaceous category is an error. The significance of that is Solemya from one of the Jurassic seeps from Sassenfjorden, which is missing from your list and should be added (cite Hryniewicz et al. 2014, Zootaxa)</p>
<p>Table 2</p>
<p>be consistent and use &#8220;Fm&#8221; or &#8220;fm&#8221;; some of the terms used later are not lithostratigraphic in any way, but geographic (e.g. Beskidy Range, Musenalp, Wollaston Forland), therefore</p>
<p>Neogene: Ca&#8217;Fornace seep deposit missing (citation: Kiel et al. 2018)</p>
<p>Paleogene</p>
<p>Paleocene seep sites from Spitsbergen from Spitsbergen missing (citation: Hryniewicz et al. 2016, Palaeo3x, describing site, not fauna; do not cite 2019 paper here as it discusses the fauna)</p>
<p>Satsop Weatherwax seep deposit missing (citation: Hybertsen and Kiel, 2018, APP)</p>
<p>Late Cretaceous: separate Omagari lens and Yasukawa seep, these are two very different deposits</p>
<p>There are two Late Cretaceous seep deposits on Antarctic Peninsula; one on Seymour Island (Lopez de Bertodano Fm), one on Snow Hill Island (Snow Hill Island Formation), both are lumped into one here which is a mistake; worse, the deposit from Seymour Island is referred to as belonging to Snow Hill Island Formation, the seep-bearing lithologies of which do not even cropp out on Seymour Island; please correct that</p>
<p>Devonian</p>
<p>Regarding Sidi-Amar: in your 2007 paper you write about a limestone layer yielding Dzieduszyckia which was sampled, please include that next to &#8220;erratic limestone&#8221;; and &#8220;Devonian erratic limestones&#8221; does not look good as it suggest glacial erratics to most people, perhaps write &#8220;Devono-Carboniferous melange&#8221; or something like that</p>
<p>Despite numerous studies, I have seen the host lithological unit of Hollard Mound named just once, and that would be Pinacites limestone indeed (Peckmann et al. 1999); this is an informal unit, so small &#8220;l&#8221; and italics for Pinacites</p>
<p>Missing references:</p>
<p>Hryniewicz, K., Little, C.T.S., and Nakrem, H.A. 2014. Bivalves from the latest Jurassic&#8211;earliest Cretaceous hydrocarbon seep carbonates from Spitsbergen, Svalbard. Zootaxa 3859: 1&#8211;66.</p>
<p>Hryniewicz, K., Bitner, M.A., Durska, E., Hagstr&#246;m, J., Hj&#225;lm&#225;rsdottir H.R., Jenkins, R.G., Little, C.T.S., Miyajima, Y., Nakrem, H.A., and Kaim, A. 2016. Paleocene methane seep and wood-fall marine environments from Spitsbergen, Svalbard. Palaeogeography, Palaeoclimatology,Palaeoecology 462: 41&#8211;56.</p>
<p>Hryniewicz, K., Amano, A., Bitner, M.A., Hagstr&#246;m, J., Kiel, S., Klompmaker, A.A., M&#246;rs, T., Robins, C.M., and Kaim, A. 2019. A late Paleocene fauna from shallow-water chemosynthesis-based ecosystems, Spitsbergen, Svalbard. Acta Palaeontologica Polonica 64 (1): 101&#8211;141.</p>
<p>Hybertsen, F. and Kiel, S. 2018. A middle Eocene seep deposit with silicified fauna from the Humptulips Formation in western Washington State, USA. Acta Palaeontologica Polonica 63 (4): 751&#8211;768.</p>
<p>Kiel, S., Taviani, M. 2017. Chemosymbiotic bivalves from Miocene methane seep carbonates in Italy. Journal of Paleontology 91, 444&#8211;466.</p>
<p>Kiel, S. and Taviani, M. 2018. Chemosymbiotic bivalves from the late Pliocene Stirone River hydrocarbon seep complex in northern Italy. Acta Palaeontologica Polonica 63 (3): 557&#8211;568.</p>
<p>Kiel, S., Sami, M., and Taviani, M. 2018. A serpulid-Anodontia-dominated methane-seep deposit from the Miocene ofnorthern Italy. Acta Palaeontologica Polonica 63 (3): 569&#8211;577.</p>
<p>Krzysztof Hryniewicz</p>
<p>Reviewer #2: To authors</p>
<p>It is challenging paper which try to answer to one of the most interesting issue on faunal change in seep environment through the Phanerozoic; brachiopods vs bivalves in seeps.</p>
<p>Although your hypothesis, seep obligate dimerelloid brachiopods had mainly consumed methanotrophic and/or hydrocarbon-consuming bacteria, is seemed to established upon many assumptions, I think the idea based on you detailed review on the current our knowledge is fair. The paper would be a starting point to make better understanding of on brachiopods vs bivalves in seeps. Followings are minor point to be revised.</p>
<p>Minor points:</p>
<p>l. 72-76: Although I know authors stated in the discussion parts, it would be better to mention about non-dimerelloid brachiopod, e.g. terebratulide Eucalathis, occurrences in seep.</p>
<p>l. 238-240: Authors mentioned that the seep dwelling brachiopods disappeared after the Early Cretaceous, however, there are several occurrences of terebratulide brachiopods in Late Cretaceous and Cenozoic seeps. May be authors think those terebratulide brachiopods are not seep obligate group, author should state their thinking with reasonable reason before this sentence.</p>
<p>l. 262: not P. pacifica, C. pacifica</p>
<p>l. 287-290: So, do you think the dimerelloid brachiopods fed on free living hydrocarbon-consuming microbes only? Don&#8217;t you think they have epi-symbiotic bacteria on the surface of lophophor? Why you can exclude this possibility? Please state.</p>
<p>It is also better to argue or state the internal morphology of dimerelloid compared to other brachiopods. If they have special features, please state.</p>
<p>Table 1: I couldn&#8217;t understand why author put Conchocele bivalves as &#8220;semi-infauna.&#8221; I know they sometimes lived on the sea floor, like in Sea of Okhotsk, but in most cases they lived within sediments, beneath the sea floor. So, it shout be categorized into &#8220;infauna&#8221;.</p>
<p>l. 374-379: It is just comment. As authors already noted, it is big contrary that the dimerelloids couldn&#8217;t flourished in low sulfate concentration period, L. Cretaceous.</p>
<p>l. 778: delete &#8220;pdf ed.&#8221;</p>
<p>**********</p>
<p>6. PLOS authors have the option to publish the peer review history of their article (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://journals.plos.org/plosone/s/editorial-and-peer-review-process#loc-peer-review-history" ns0:type="simple">what does this mean?</ext-link>). If published, this will include your full peer review and any attached files.</p>
<p>If you choose &#8220;no&#8221;, your identity will remain anonymous but your review may still be made public.</p>
<p><bold>Do you want your identity to be public for this peer review?</bold> For information about this choice, including consent withdrawal, please see our <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://www.plos.org/privacy-policy" ns0:type="simple">Privacy Policy</ext-link>.</p>
<p>Reviewer #1: Yes: Krzysztof Hryniewicz</p>
<p>Reviewer #2: No</p>
<p>[NOTE: If reviewer comments were submitted as an attachment file, they will be attached to this email and accessible via the submission site. Please log into your account, locate the manuscript record, and check for the action link "View Attachments". If this link does not appear, there are no attachment files to be viewed.]</p>
<p>While revising your submission, please upload your figure files to the Preflight Analysis and Conversion Engine (PACE) digital diagnostic tool, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://pacev2.apexcovantage.com/" ns0:type="simple">https://pacev2.apexcovantage.com/</ext-link>. PACE helps ensure that figures meet PLOS requirements. To use PACE, you must first register as a user. Registration is free. Then, login and navigate to the UPLOAD tab, where you will find detailed instructions on how to use the tool. If you encounter any issues or have any questions when using PACE, please email us at <email ns0:type="simple">figures@plos.org</email>. Please note that Supporting Information files do not need this step.</p>
<supplementary-material id="pone.0221887.s001" mimetype="application/vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.wordprocessingml.document" position="float" ns0:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0221887.s001" ns0:type="simple">
<label>Attachment</label>
<caption>
<p>Submitted filename: <named-content content-type="submitted-filename">Kiel_Peckmann_2019_review.docx</named-content></p>
</caption>
</supplementary-material>
</body>
</sub-article>
