<sub-article xmlns:ns0="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="aggregated-review-documents" id="pone.0220451.r001" specific-use="decision-letter">
<front-stub>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0220451.r001</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title>Decision Letter 0</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Khan</surname>
<given-names>M. Firoze</given-names>
</name>
<role>Academic Editor</role>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<permissions>
<copyright-year>2019</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>M. Firoze Khan</copyright-holder>
<license ns0:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
<license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" ns0:type="simple">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<related-object document-id="10.1371/journal.pone.0220451" document-id-type="doi" document-type="article" id="rel-obj001" link-type="peer-reviewed-article" />
<custom-meta-group>
<custom-meta>
<meta-name>Submission Version</meta-name>
<meta-value>0</meta-value>
</custom-meta>
</custom-meta-group>
</front-stub>
<body>
<p>
<named-content content-type="letter-date">9 Jul 2019</named-content>
</p>
<p>PONE-D-19-15877</p>
<p>Changes in human peripheral blood mononuclear cell (HPBMC) populations and T-cell subsets associated with arsenic and polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbon exposures in a Bangladesh cohort</p>
<p>PLOS ONE</p>
<p>Dear Dr. Burchiel,</p>
<p>Thank you for submitting your manuscript to PLOS ONE. After careful consideration, we feel that it has merit, but does not fully meet PLOS ONE&#8217;s publication criteria as it currently stands. Reviewers were generally enthusiastic about the study, and only have a few minor comments/suggestions. Therefore, we invite you to submit a revised version of the manuscript that addresses all the points raised by the reviewers.</p>
<p>We would appreciate receiving your revised manuscript by August 25, 2019. When you are ready to submit your revision, log on to <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://www.editorialmanager.com/pone/" ns0:type="simple">https://www.editorialmanager.com/pone/</ext-link> and select the 'Submissions Needing Revision' folder to locate your manuscript file.</p>
<p>If you would like to make changes to your financial disclosure, please include your updated statement in your cover letter.</p>
<p>To enhance the reproducibility of your results, we recommend that if applicable you deposit your laboratory protocols in protocols.io, where a protocol can be assigned its own identifier (DOI) such that it can be cited independently in the future. For instructions see: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://journals.plos.org/plosone/s/submission-guidelines#loc-laboratory-protocols" ns0:type="simple">http://journals.plos.org/plosone/s/submission-guidelines#loc-laboratory-protocols</ext-link></p>
<p>Please include the following items when submitting your revised manuscript:</p>
<p><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>A rebuttal letter that responds to each point raised by the academic editor and reviewer(s). This letter should be uploaded as separate file and labeled 'Response to Reviewers'.</p></list-item><list-item><p>A marked-up copy of your manuscript that highlights changes made to the original version. This file should be uploaded as separate file and labeled 'Revised Manuscript with Track Changes'.</p></list-item><list-item><p>An unmarked version of your revised paper without tracked changes. This file should be uploaded as separate file and labeled 'Manuscript'.</p></list-item></list></p>
<p>Please note while forming your response, if your article is accepted, you may have the opportunity to make the peer review history publicly available. The record will include editor decision letters (with reviews) and your responses to reviewer comments. If eligible, we will contact you to opt in or out.</p>
<p>We look forward to receiving your revised manuscript.</p>
<p>Kind regards,</p>
<p>M. Firoze Khan, Ph.D.</p>
<p>Academic Editor</p>
<p>PLOS ONE</p>
<p>Journal Requirements:</p>
<p>1. When submitting your revision, we need you to address these additional requirements.</p>
<p>Please ensure that your manuscript meets PLOS ONE's style requirements, including those for file naming. The PLOS ONE style templates can be found at</p>
<p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://www.journals.plos.org/plosone/s/file?id=wjVg/PLOSOne_formatting_sample_main_body.pdf" ns0:type="simple">http://www.journals.plos.org/plosone/s/file?id=wjVg/PLOSOne_formatting_sample_main_body.pdf</ext-link> and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://www.journals.plos.org/plosone/s/file?id=ba62/PLOSOne_formatting_sample_title_authors_affiliations.pdf" ns0:type="simple">http://www.journals.plos.org/plosone/s/file?id=ba62/PLOSOne_formatting_sample_title_authors_affiliations.pdf</ext-link></p>
<p>2. Please include captions for your Supporting Information files at the end of your manuscript, and update any in-text citations to match accordingly. Please see our Supporting Information guidelines for more information: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://journals.plos.org/plosone/s/supporting-information" ns0:type="simple">http://journals.plos.org/plosone/s/supporting-information</ext-link>.</p>
<p>[Note: HTML markup is below. Please do not edit.]</p>
<p>Reviewers' comments:</p>
<p>Reviewer's Responses to Questions</p>
<p><bold>Comments to the Author</bold></p>
<p>1. Is the manuscript technically sound, and do the data support the conclusions?</p>
<p>The manuscript must describe a technically sound piece of scientific research with data that supports the conclusions. Experiments must have been conducted rigorously, with appropriate controls, replication, and sample sizes. The conclusions must be drawn appropriately based on the data presented. </p>
<p>Reviewer #1: Yes</p>
<p>Reviewer #2: Yes</p>
<p>Reviewer #3: Yes</p>
<p>**********</p>
<p>2. Has the statistical analysis been performed appropriately and rigorously? </p>
<p>Reviewer #1: Yes</p>
<p>Reviewer #2: I Don't Know</p>
<p>Reviewer #3: Yes</p>
<p>**********</p>
<p>3. Have the authors made all data underlying the findings in their manuscript fully available?</p>
<p>The <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://www.plosone.org/static/policies.action#sharing" ns0:type="simple">PLOS Data policy</ext-link> requires authors to make all data underlying the findings described in their manuscript fully available without restriction, with rare exception (please refer to the Data Availability Statement in the manuscript PDF file). The data should be provided as part of the manuscript or its supporting information, or deposited to a public repository. For example, in addition to summary statistics, the data points behind means, medians and variance measures should be available. If there are restrictions on publicly sharing data&#8212;e.g. participant privacy or use of data from a third party&#8212;those must be specified.</p>
<p>Reviewer #1: Yes</p>
<p>Reviewer #2: Yes</p>
<p>Reviewer #3: Yes</p>
<p>**********</p>
<p>4. Is the manuscript presented in an intelligible fashion and written in standard English?</p>
<p>PLOS ONE does not copyedit accepted manuscripts, so the language in submitted articles must be clear, correct, and unambiguous. Any typographical or grammatical errors should be corrected at revision, so please note any specific errors here.</p>
<p>Reviewer #1: Yes</p>
<p>Reviewer #2: Yes</p>
<p>Reviewer #3: Yes</p>
<p>**********</p>
<p>5. Review Comments to the Author</p>
<p>Please use the space provided to explain your answers to the questions above. You may also include additional comments for the author, including concerns about dual publication, research ethics, or publication ethics. (Please upload your review as an attachment if it exceeds 20,000 characters)</p>
<p>Reviewer #1: Both arsenic (As) and polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons (PAH) are common environmental contaminants. The manuscript titled &#8220;Changes in human peripheral blood mononuclear cell (HPBMC) populations and T-cell subsets associated with arsenic and polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbon exposures in a Bangladesh cohort&#8221; examined associations between As and PAH exposures with lymphoid cell populations in human peripheral blood mononuclear cells (PBMC), as well as alterations in differentiation and activation of B and T cells. Even though the authors did not find evidence of interactions between As and PAH exposures, they obtained a large amount of interesting findings such as the associations between individual exposures (As or PAH) and changes to immune cell populations (particularly Th cells) and immune cell activation. The findings are useful in understanding the mechanisms of As- or PAH-mediated adverse health outcomes, such as immune suppression or autoimmunity</p>
<p>This manuscript should be suitable for publication in Plos One if the minor issues below are addressed:</p>
<p>1) The authors may consider reducing the length of method section. Some methods such as collection of PBMC, cell surface and intracellular staining are common techniques and should be described briefly with appropriated references.</p>
<p>2) The authors may need to provide information on why they selected the current exposure biomarkers (UAs and PAH-DNA adducts) in this study.</p>
<p>Reviewer #2: This is a very written manuscript and detailed, although methodology can be shortened with relevant citations rather than extensive description. Arsenic exposure in drinking water in Bangladesh is a genuine heath problem along with PAH exposure through cigarette smoking. As described on page 5, goal of the study was to examine the combined effect of As and PAH, where half of the participants were identified drinking from the wells with water contamination of As &gt;50 ppb and remainder with &lt;50 ppb with or without smoking. I for see four study groups or more in the "Recruitment and consent of study participants" section, which needs to be translated in the tables and figures so that comparisons can be understood. Otherwise, this is a significant study addressing an important health issue in a population group ignorant of serious adverse health effects of As and PAH.</p>
<p>Reviewer #3: In this investigation, the authors have investigated the associations between arsenic (As) and PAH exposures with lymphoid cell populations in human peripheral blood mononuclear cells (PBMC), as well as alterations in differentiation and activation of B and T cells.. The authors have analyzed blood and urine from 200 men participating in the Health Effects of Arsenic Longitudinal Study (HEALS) in Bangladesh were selected for the present study based on their exposure to As from drinking water and their cigarette smoking status. The major findings were; (i) There was no evidence of interactions between As and PAH exposures; however, individual exposures (As or PAH) were associated with changes to immune cell populations, including Th cell subsets; (ii) As exposure was associated with an increase in the percentage of Th cells, and dose dependent changes in monocytes, NKT cells and a monocyte subset, and within the Th cell subset the authors found that arsenic exposure was also associated with a significant increase in the percentage of circulating pro-inflammatory Th17 cells; and (iii) PAH exposure was associated with changes in T cells, monocytes and T memory (Tmem) cells and with changes in Th, Th1, Th2 and Th17 subsets all of which were dose dependent. Based on these observations, the authors suggest that alterations of immune cell populations caused by environmental exposures to As and PAH may result in adverse health outcomes, such as changes in systemic inflammation, immune suppression, or autoimmunity. The manuscript is well written, and study appears to have been well conducted. This work is highly significant because little data exists regarding the associations between combined exposures to As and PAH with immunotoxicity in humans I have a few minor concerns that need to be addressed:</p>
<p>1. In the abstract (line 29 ) the sentence should not start with a number.</p>
<p>2. Since cigarette smoke contains over 4000 chemicals in addition to PAHs and As, the authors should include in the discussion the possible contribution of other chemicals to the changes in systemic inflammation and autoimmunity.</p>
<p>**********</p>
<p>6. PLOS authors have the option to publish the peer review history of their article (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://journals.plos.org/plosone/s/editorial-and-peer-review-process#loc-peer-review-history" ns0:type="simple">what does this mean?</ext-link>). If published, this will include your full peer review and any attached files.</p>
<p>If you choose &#8220;no&#8221;, your identity will remain anonymous but your review may still be made public.</p>
<p><bold>Do you want your identity to be public for this peer review?</bold> For information about this choice, including consent withdrawal, please see our <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://www.plos.org/privacy-policy" ns0:type="simple">Privacy Policy</ext-link>.</p>
<p>Reviewer #1: No</p>
<p>Reviewer #2: No</p>
<p>Reviewer #3: Yes: Bhagavatula Moorthy</p>
<p>[NOTE: If reviewer comments were submitted as an attachment file, they will be attached to this email and accessible via the submission site. Please log into your account, locate the manuscript record, and check for the action link "View Attachments". If this link does not appear, there are no attachment files to be viewed.]</p>
<p>While revising your submission, please upload your figure files to the Preflight Analysis and Conversion Engine (PACE) digital diagnostic tool, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://pacev2.apexcovantage.com/" ns0:type="simple">https://pacev2.apexcovantage.com/</ext-link>. PACE helps ensure that figures meet PLOS requirements. To use PACE, you must first register as a user. Registration is free. Then, login and navigate to the UPLOAD tab, where you will find detailed instructions on how to use the tool. If you encounter any issues or have any questions when using PACE, please email us at <email ns0:type="simple">figures@plos.org</email>. Please note that Supporting Information files do not need this step.</p>
</body>
</sub-article>
