<sub-article article-type="author-comment" id="pone.0221784.r004">
<front-stub>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0221784.r004</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title>Author response to Decision Letter 1</article-title>
</title-group>
<related-object document-id="10.1371/journal.pone.0221784" document-id-type="doi" document-type="peer-reviewed-article" id="rel-obj004" link-type="rebutted-decision-letter" object-id="10.1371/journal.pone.0221784.r003" object-id-type="doi" object-type="decision-letter" />
<custom-meta-group>
<custom-meta>
<meta-name>Submission Version</meta-name>
<meta-value>2</meta-value>
</custom-meta>
</custom-meta-group>
</front-stub>
<body>
<p>
<named-content content-type="author-response-date">10 Aug 2019</named-content>
</p>
<p>Comment 1. Page 6: Consider adding "disability" in the sentence with: Neurological disability by EDSS score and the functional system "disability" scores (except for visual functional score) were &#8230;..</p>
<p>Response: Corrected</p>
<p>Comment 2. Page 6, last paragraph: Table 2 shows 45/1010 while the narrative reports 45/1010 for high cognitive performance and severe disability. Which is correct?</p>
<p>Response: The title column in Table 2 shows: High cognitive performance &amp; Severe disability, so essentially both are the same and correct. </p>
<p>Comment 3. Page 7, second paragraph in "Discussion": Consider changing the sentence to "The use of DMD significantly changed the pattern of MS progression."</p>
<p>Response: corrected.</p>
<p>Comment 4. check all citations and references for accuracy.</p>
<p>Response: We checked all citations and references to ensure accuracy.</p>
<p>Review Comments to the Author</p>
<p>1. The discussion around cognitive resilience could be strengthened. Devote at least a paragraph explaining what cognitive resilience is, how it can be captured, what predisposing factors contribute to cognitive resilience, and how that may impact disability and quality of life. Provide references.</p>
<p>Response: We have added to the Discussion a paragraph explaining what cognitive resilience is, how it can be captured, what predisposing factors contribute to cognitive resilience, and how that may impact disability and quality of life. In accordance we have provide references as follows:</p>
<p>The term resilience was derived from the Latin words salire (to leap or jump), and resilire (to spring back). When applied to cognition it stands for the capacity of the brain to resist deteriorating processes or injuries (SternY. What is cognitive reserve? Theory and research applications of the reserve concept. J Int Neuropsychol Soc 2002; 8:448&#8211;460. McEwen BS. In pursuit of resilience: stress, epigenetics, and brain plasticity. Ann N Y Acad Sci. 2016;1373:56-64). Cognitive resilience literature has focused on specific contexts in which individuals differ in their capabilities to withstand or overcome brain insults and to explain the difference in the patterns of cognitive decline associated with aging and neurodegenerative diseases (de Frias CM, Dixon RA, B&#228;ckman L. Use of memory compensation strategies is related to psychosocial and health indicators. J Gerontol B Psychol Sci Soc Sci. 2003;58:12-22.). Various predisposing interacting factors may contribute to the road map for brain resilience including education, gender, prior brain injuries, family history, participation in cognitively stimulating activities, physical exercises, social relationships and apoE genotype. (Christensen H1, Hofer SM, Mackinnon AJ, Korten AE, Jorm AF, Henderson AS. Age is no kinder to the better educated: absence of an association investigated using latent growth techniques in a community sample. Psychol Med. 2001;31:15-28. Kirk-Sanchez NJ, McGough EL. Physical exercise and cognitive performance in the elderly: current perspectives. Clin Interv Aging. 2014;9:51-62. Hofer SM, Christensen H, Mackinnon AJ, Korten AE, Jorm AF, Henderson AS, Easteal S. Change in cognitive functioning associated with apoE genotype in a community sample of older adults. Psychol Aging. 2002;17:194-208. Wilson RS, Mendes De Leon CF, Barnes LL, Schneider JA, Bienias JL, Evans DA, Bennett DA. Participation in cognitively stimulating activities and risk of incident Alzheimer disease. JAMA. 2002;287:742-8. Seeman TE, Lusignolo TM, Albert M, Berkman L. Social relationships, social support, and patterns of cognitive aging in healthy, high-functioning older adults: MacArthur studies of successful aging. Health Psychol. 2001;20:243-55.). In young patients with a chronic long-lasting disease like MS, characterizing differences between cognitive subgroups in relation to clinical variables may afford new insights into the on-going neuroplasticity mechanisms and in accordance suggest plasticity&#8208;facilitating treatments to enhance cognitive resilience. </p>
<p>2. The leap from good performance on cognitive tests to &#8220;cognitive resilience&#8221; needs better argumentation. The authors report that 33.7% are cognitive resilient because they score well on cognitive tests despite long disease duration. However, they also have mild disability. It is logical to assume that those with mild disability will also have less cognitive impairments. The 33.7% with good performance in cognitive tests reported here do well because they are generally less disabled; not necessarily because they show better cognitive resilience. You could also argue then that these individuals have better physical resilience, or respond better to disease modifying treatment. It would be more important to focus on the persons who show high cognitive performance despite moderate to severe disability, e.g., those individuals reported in Table 2.</p>
<p>Response: As the Reviewer commented, indeed, cognitive resilience in patients with long disease duration and mild disability probably signifies MS resilience, e.g., resilience to the disease pathogenic mechanisms. These patients are defined as patients with benign disease course and therefore also manifest with less cognitive impairments. Our findings implicate that cognition as a part of the functional neurological spectrum of MS is better reserved in patients with less active disease, as patients with low disability were found to be more cognitively resilient. </p>
<p>Regarding the group of patients who show high cognitive performance despite moderate to severe disability as compared to patients with low cognitive performance despite mild disability, we have specified in the Discussion a possible explanation related to anatomical involvement. We suggest that patients with moderate to severe disability but high cognitive performance the spinal cord will be more involved as compared to patients with mild disability but with low cognitive performance that probably present widespread brain disease and relatively lower spinal cord involvement.</p>
<p>We have added these paragraphs to the Discussion.</p>
<p>minor comments:</p>
<p>3. How were the three groups of cognitive performance and the three groups of neurological disability determined. Please provide references on the categorization of cognitive performance and neurological disability.</p>
<p>Response: As specified in the Methods - Cognitive assessment, last paragraph, the three groups of cognitive performance and the three groups of neurological disability were determined according to the global cognitive score (GCS) and the Expanded Disability Status Scale (EDSS) score as follows:</p>
<p>Cognitive performance was categorized by GCS as &#8220;high&#8221; (GCS &gt;100), &#8220;moderate&#8221; (GCS 85-100) or &#8220;low&#8221; (GCS&lt;85). Neurological disability was classified according to EDSS score as &#8220;mild&#8221; (EDSS &#8804;3), "moderate&#8221; (EDSS 3.5-5.5), or "severe" (EDSS &gt;6.0).</p>
<p>Both are referenced.</p>
<p>We better detailed this by adding the title of Group categorization to this paragraph.</p>
<p>4. Please add in the limitations section that this study included only relapsing-remitting and secondary progressive MS.</p>
<p>Response: Added.</p>
<p>5. Please elaborate on exclusion criterion 5. How was it determined from chart review whether a patient had severe upper limb or visual impairment?</p>
<p>Response: This exclusion criteria is determined as a part of the cognitive test. Patients that have severe upper limb dysfunction like paralysis or tremor are not able to hold the computer-mouse and therefore are technically excluded from preforming the test. Similarly, at the beginning of the cognitive test visual acuity is assessed and patients that can not read the instructions are technically excluded from performing the test. </p>
<p>The explanation was added to exclusion criterion 5.</p>
<p>6. On that note, visual performance did not differ between the three groups (Table 1), probably because visual impairment was an exclusion criterion. Please add this to the discussion.</p>
<p> Response: Added.</p>
</body>
</sub-article>
