<sub-article xmlns:ns0="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="editor-report" id="pmed.1002929.r003" specific-use="decision-letter">
<front-stub>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pmed.1002929.r003</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title>Decision Letter 1</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>McBride</surname>
<given-names>Thomas J</given-names>
</name>
<role>Senior Editor</role>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<permissions>
<copyright-year>2019</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>Thomas J McBride</copyright-holder>
<license ns0:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
<license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" ns0:type="simple">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<related-object document-id="10.1371/journal.pmed.1002929" document-id-type="doi" document-type="article" id="rel-obj003" link-type="peer-reviewed-article" />
<custom-meta-group>
<custom-meta>
<meta-name>Submission Version</meta-name>
<meta-value>1</meta-value>
</custom-meta>
</custom-meta-group>
</front-stub>
<body>
<p>
<named-content content-type="letter-date">19 Aug 2019</named-content>
</p>
<p>Dear Dr. Suthar,</p>
<p>Thank you very much for re-submitting your manuscript "Strengthening civil registration and vital statistics systems: a systematic review and synthesis of policies to improve birth and death registration" (PMEDICINE-D-19-01902R1) for review by PLOS Medicine.</p>
<p>I have discussed the paper with my colleagues and the academic editor. I am pleased to say that provided the remaining editorial and production issues are dealt with we are planning to accept the paper for publication in the journal.</p>
<p>The remaining issues that need to be addressed are listed at the end of this email. Any accompanying reviewer attachments can be seen via the link below. Please take these into account before resubmitting your manuscript:</p>
<p>[LINK]</p>
<p>Our publications team (<email ns0:type="simple">plosmedicine@plos.org</email>) will be in touch shortly about the production requirements for your paper, and the link and deadline for resubmission. DO NOT RESUBMIT BEFORE YOU'VE RECEIVED THE PRODUCTION REQUIREMENTS.</p>
<p>***Please note while forming your response, if your article is accepted, you may have the opportunity to make the peer review history publicly available. The record will include editor decision letters (with reviews) and your responses to reviewer comments. If eligible, we will contact you to opt in or out.***</p>
<p>In revising the manuscript for further consideration here, please ensure you address the specific points made by each reviewer and the editors. In your rebuttal letter you should indicate your response to the reviewers' and editors' comments and the changes you have made in the manuscript. Please submit a clean version of the paper as the main article file. A version with changes marked must also be uploaded as a marked up manuscript file.</p>
<p>Please also check the guidelines for revised papers at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://journals.plos.org/plosmedicine/s/revising-your-manuscript" ns0:type="simple">http://journals.plos.org/plosmedicine/s/revising-your-manuscript</ext-link> for any that apply to your paper.</p>
<p>We expect to receive your revised manuscript within 1 week. Please email us (<email ns0:type="simple">plosmedicine@plos.org</email>) if you have any questions or concerns.</p>
<p>We ask every co-author listed on the manuscript to fill in a contributing author statement. If any of the co-authors have not filled in the statement, we will remind them to do so when the paper is revised. If all statements are not completed in a timely fashion this could hold up the re-review process. Should there be a problem getting one of your co-authors to fill in a statement we will be in contact. YOU MUST NOT ADD OR REMOVE AUTHORS UNLESS YOU HAVE ALERTED THE EDITOR HANDLING THE MANUSCRIPT TO THE CHANGE AND THEY SPECIFICALLY HAVE AGREED TO IT.</p>
<p>Please ensure that the paper adheres to the PLOS Data Availability Policy (see <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://journals.plos.org/plosmedicine/s/data-availability" ns0:type="simple">http://journals.plos.org/plosmedicine/s/data-availability</ext-link>), which requires that all data underlying the study's findings be provided in a repository or as Supporting Information. For data residing with a third party, authors are required to provide instructions with contact information for obtaining the data. PLOS journals do not allow statements supported by "data not shown" or "unpublished results." For such statements, authors must provide supporting data or cite public sources that include it.</p>
<p>If you have any questions in the meantime, please contact me or the journal staff on <email ns0:type="simple">plosmedicine@plos.org</email>.  </p>
<p>We look forward to receiving the revised manuscript by Aug 26 2019 11:59PM.   </p>
<p>Sincerely,</p>
<p>Thomas McBride, PhD</p>
<p>Senior Editor </p>
<p>PLOS Medicine</p>
<p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://plosmedicine.org" ns0:type="simple">plosmedicine.org</ext-link></p>
<p>------------------------------------------------------------</p>
<p>Requests from Editors:</p>
<p>1- Thank you for editing the Title. I still think it could be more descriptive though. Perhaps: &#8220;Evaluation of approaches to strengthen civil registration and vital statistics systems: a systematic review and synthesis of policies in 25 countries&#8221;</p>
<p>2- Thank you for including an Author Summary. Some of the bullet points are a bit lengthy (eg, point 3 of the &#8220;What Did the Researchers Do and Find?&#8221; section), please cut a bit or split into multiple bullets (but not sub-points).</p>
<p>3- The limitation that most studies did not have a comparator group could be mentioned in the Discussion, along with the other methodological limitations of the studies included.</p>
<p>4- Discussion limitations could also note the geographic limitations, eg very few European countries represented.</p>
<p>5- Please include your response regarding Taiwan inthe main text.</p>
<p>6- Line 253: "Association with birth and death registration rates"?</p>
</body>
</sub-article>
