<sub-article xmlns:ns0="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="aggregated-review-documents" id="pone.0222934.r001" specific-use="decision-letter">
<front-stub>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0222934.r001</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title>Decision Letter 0</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Bergsland</surname>
<given-names>Niels</given-names>
</name>
<role>Academic Editor</role>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<permissions>
<copyright-year>2019</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>Niels Bergsland</copyright-holder>
<license ns0:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
<license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" ns0:type="simple">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<related-object document-id="10.1371/journal.pone.0222934" document-id-type="doi" document-type="article" id="rel-obj001" link-type="peer-reviewed-article" />
<custom-meta-group>
<custom-meta>
<meta-name>Submission Version</meta-name>
<meta-value>0</meta-value>
</custom-meta>
</custom-meta-group>
</front-stub>
<body>
<p>
<named-content content-type="letter-date">6 Aug 2019</named-content>
</p>
<p>PONE-D-19-14760</p>
<p>Quantitative magnetic resonance imaging indicates brain tissue alterations in patients after liver transplantation</p>
<p>PLOS ONE</p>
<p>Dear Dr. Ding,</p>
<p>Thank you for submitting your manuscript to PLOS ONE. After careful consideration, we feel that it has merit but does not fully meet PLOS ONE&#8217;s publication criteria as it currently stands. Therefore, we invite you to submit a revised version of the manuscript that addresses the points raised during the review process.</p>
<p>In addition to addressing the comments raised by the Reviewers, please also address/respond to the following points:</p>
<p>1. Please review the STROBE statement and ensure that all points have been addressed (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://www.strobe-statement.org/index.php?id=strobe-home" ns0:type="simple">https://www.strobe-statement.org/index.php?id=strobe-home</ext-link>). As of now, there are a number of aspects that are missing (e.g. reporting of time frame of enrolled participants, addressing potential sources of bias).</p>
<p>2. Please avoid the use of "Results not shown" (See the following for link for additional details:&#160;<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://journals.plos.org/plosone/s/data-availability" ns0:type="simple">https://journals.plos.org/plosone/s/data-availability</ext-link>)</p>
<p>3.&#160;The word &#8216;gender&#8217; is used throughout the manuscript (in addition to 'sex'). Usually, &#8220;sex&#8221; (the biological designation) is meant. &#8220;Gender&#8221; is the social construct and is rarely relevant in neurologic disease. Please revise the text to use &#8220;sex&#8221; rather than &#8220;gender&#8221; throughout.</p>
<p>4. Were there any changes to the MRI scanner (e.g. hardware, software) throughout the course of the study? If so, were patients and controls equally distributed before/after updates?</p>
<p>We would appreciate receiving your revised manuscript by Sep 14 2019 11:59PM. When you are ready to submit your revision, log on to <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://www.editorialmanager.com/pone/" ns0:type="simple">https://www.editorialmanager.com/pone/</ext-link> and select the 'Submissions Needing Revision' folder to locate your manuscript file.</p>
<p>If you would like to make changes to your financial disclosure, please include your updated statement in your cover letter.</p>
<p>To enhance the reproducibility of your results, we recommend that if applicable you deposit your laboratory protocols in protocols.io, where a protocol can be assigned its own identifier (DOI) such that it can be cited independently in the future. For instructions see: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://journals.plos.org/plosone/s/submission-guidelines#loc-laboratory-protocols" ns0:type="simple">http://journals.plos.org/plosone/s/submission-guidelines#loc-laboratory-protocols</ext-link></p>
<p>Please include the following items when submitting your revised manuscript:</p>
<p><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>A rebuttal letter that responds to each point raised by the academic editor and reviewer(s). This letter should be uploaded as separate file and labeled 'Response to Reviewers'.</p></list-item><list-item><p>A marked-up copy of your manuscript that highlights changes made to the original version. This file should be uploaded as separate file and labeled 'Revised Manuscript with Track Changes'.</p></list-item><list-item><p>An unmarked version of your revised paper without tracked changes. This file should be uploaded as separate file and labeled 'Manuscript'.</p></list-item></list></p>
<p>Please note while forming your response, if your article is accepted, you may have the opportunity to make the peer review history publicly available. The record will include editor decision letters (with reviews) and your responses to reviewer comments. If eligible, we will contact you to opt in or out.</p>
<p>We look forward to receiving your revised manuscript.</p>
<p>Kind regards,</p>
<p>Niels Bergsland</p>
<p>Academic Editor</p>
<p>PLOS ONE</p>
<p>Journal Requirements:</p>
<p>1. When submitting your revision, we need you to address these additional requirements.</p>
<p>Please ensure that your manuscript meets PLOS ONE's style requirements, including those for file naming. The PLOS ONE style templates can be found at</p>
<p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://www.journals.plos.org/plosone/s/file?id=wjVg/PLOSOne_formatting_sample_main_body.pdf" ns0:type="simple">http://www.journals.plos.org/plosone/s/file?id=wjVg/PLOSOne_formatting_sample_main_body.pdf</ext-link> and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://www.journals.plos.org/plosone/s/file?id=ba62/PLOSOne_formatting_sample_title_authors_affiliations.pdf" ns0:type="simple">http://www.journals.plos.org/plosone/s/file?id=ba62/PLOSOne_formatting_sample_title_authors_affiliations.pdf</ext-link></p>
<p>2. Thank you for submitting the above manuscript to PLOS ONE. During our internal evaluation of the manuscript, we found some text overlap between your submission and the following previously published works, on which you are an author: Eylers, Vanessa V., et al. "Detection of normal aging effects on human brain metabolite concentrations and microstructure with whole-brain MR spectroscopic imaging and quantitative MR imaging." American Journal of Neuroradiology 37.3 (2016): 447-454. The re-use of text from a previous publication may have implications for the copyright or license that applies to the published article. To avoid any concerns in this respect, we would recommend that you revise the manuscript, particularly outside the methods section, to either remove any text overlap where possible/appropriate, or to clearly indicate that the text reproduces information already reported in detail elsewhere (e.g. &#8220;As described in detail previously [ref],&#8230;&#8221;) citing the relevant sources.</p>
<p>3. We suggest you thoroughly copyedit your manuscript for language usage, spelling, and grammar. If you do not know anyone who can help you do this, you may wish to consider employing a professional scientific editing service. &#160;</p>
<p>Whilst you may use any professional scientific editing service of your choice, PLOS has partnered with both American Journal Experts (AJE) and Editage to provide discounted services to PLOS authors. Both organizations have experience helping authors meet PLOS guidelines and can provide language editing, translation, manuscript formatting, and figure formatting to ensure your manuscript meets our submission guidelines. To take advantage of our partnership with AJE, visit the AJE website (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://learn.aje.com/plos/" ns0:type="simple">http://learn.aje.com/plos/</ext-link>) for a 15% discount off AJE services. To take advantage of our partnership with Editage, visit the Editage website (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://www.editage.com" ns0:type="simple">www.editage.com</ext-link>) and enter referral code PLOSEDIT for a 15% discount off Editage services.&#160; If the PLOS editorial team finds any language issues in text that either AJE or Editage has edited, the service provider will re-edit the text for free.</p>
<p>Upon resubmission, please provide the following:</p>
<p><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>The name of the colleague or the details of the professional service that edited your manuscript</p></list-item><list-item><p>A copy of your manuscript showing your changes by either highlighting them or using track changes (uploaded as a *supporting information* file)</p></list-item><list-item><p>A clean copy of the edited manuscript (uploaded as the new *manuscript* file)</p></list-item></list></p>
<p>4. We noted in your submission details that a portion of your manuscript may have been presented or published elsewhere: "Neither the submitted material nor portions thereof have been published previously or are under consideration for publication elsewhere.</p>
<p>Preliminary results of this study have been presented at the International Society for Hepatic Encephalopathy and Nitrogen Metabolism (ISHEN) 2017 in New Delhi, India, as a poster. The according abstract has been published in the Journal of Clinical and Experimental Hepatology in February 2017."</p>
<p>Please clarify whether this [conference proceeding or publication] was peer-reviewed and formally published. If this work was previously peer-reviewed and published, in the cover letter please provide the reason that this work does not constitute dual publication and should be included in the current manuscript.</p>
<p>[Note: HTML markup is below. Please do not edit.]</p>
<p>Reviewers' comments:</p>
<p>Reviewer's Responses to Questions</p>
<p><bold>Comments to the Author</bold></p>
<p>1. Is the manuscript technically sound, and do the data support the conclusions?</p>
<p>The manuscript must describe a technically sound piece of scientific research with data that supports the conclusions. Experiments must have been conducted rigorously, with appropriate controls, replication, and sample sizes. The conclusions must be drawn appropriately based on the data presented. </p>
<p>Reviewer #1: Yes</p>
<p>Reviewer #2: Yes</p>
<p>**********</p>
<p>2. Has the statistical analysis been performed appropriately and rigorously? </p>
<p>Reviewer #1: Yes</p>
<p>Reviewer #2: Yes</p>
<p>**********</p>
<p>3. Have the authors made all data underlying the findings in their manuscript fully available?</p>
<p>The <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://www.plosone.org/static/policies.action#sharing" ns0:type="simple">PLOS Data policy</ext-link> requires authors to make all data underlying the findings described in their manuscript fully available without restriction, with rare exception (please refer to the Data Availability Statement in the manuscript PDF file). The data should be provided as part of the manuscript or its supporting information, or deposited to a public repository. For example, in addition to summary statistics, the data points behind means, medians and variance measures should be available. If there are restrictions on publicly sharing data&#8212;e.g. participant privacy or use of data from a third party&#8212;those must be specified.</p>
<p>Reviewer #1: Yes</p>
<p>Reviewer #2: Yes</p>
<p>**********</p>
<p>4. Is the manuscript presented in an intelligible fashion and written in standard English?</p>
<p>PLOS ONE does not copyedit accepted manuscripts, so the language in submitted articles must be clear, correct, and unambiguous. Any typographical or grammatical errors should be corrected at revision, so please note any specific errors here.</p>
<p>Reviewer #1: Yes</p>
<p>Reviewer #2: Yes</p>
<p>**********</p>
<p>5. Review Comments to the Author</p>
<p>Please use the space provided to explain your answers to the questions above. You may also include additional comments for the author, including concerns about dual publication, research ethics, or publication ethics. (Please upload your review as an attachment if it exceeds 20,000 characters)</p>
<p>Reviewer #1: Dr Goede et al. present a study using quantitative MRI for neurological assessment after liver transplantation (LT). They compare, more than 2 years after LT patients under normal dosage of CNI, patients under lowered dosage of CNI and patients without CNI.</p>
<p>Here are some comments:</p>
<p>- page 12, how were "pre-existing neurological or psychiatric diseases" defined ?</p>
<p>- page 12, how was "regular intake of drugs (besides CNI and steroids) which might affect brain function" defined?</p>
<p>- were possible per-operative or ICU complications taken in account ?</p>
<p>- the cause of reducing the dosage of CNIs could constitute a bias. This is however discussed in discussion</p>
<p>- page 13, maybe a comparison to patients that underwent renal grafting and being under CNIs would have be valuable</p>
<p>- page 15, there is a figure legend included in the manuscript but there is no figure</p>
<p>- it seems that the present study constitute an ancillary study of the study previously described in ref 15. Please, if it is so, clearly explain that the patients are the same that those described in a previous study</p>
<p>- page 18, were RBANS profiles different in patients that had previous to LT bouts of hepatic encephalopathy ?</p>
<p>- table 2 is difficult to understand since only significant results are presented</p>
<p>- "p14", "p24" "p34" are difficult to understand. Please provide are clearer way to describe this comparution: "p1v4" maybe ?</p>
<p>- the figure 1 is not clear. Please add in the A part, a A1 and so on in order to be more precise</p>
<p>-</p>
<p>Reviewer #2: This is a very important manuscript that describes concerning long term disorders that are secondary to immunosuppression on patients after liver transplant. Well designed study and methods are sound and clear for the results.</p>
<p>The only aspect that I see that is needing is the degree of liver decompensation prior to liver transplant. The other factor that I think is missing is the effect of decompensated liver disease in the brain and different areas of the central nervous system. If there is predisposition for this deleterious effect of the CNI in a previously injured CNS.</p>
<p>**********</p>
<p>6. PLOS authors have the option to publish the peer review history of their article (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://journals.plos.org/plosone/s/editorial-and-peer-review-process#loc-peer-review-history" ns0:type="simple">what does this mean?</ext-link>). If published, this will include your full peer review and any attached files.</p>
<p>If you choose &#8220;no&#8221;, your identity will remain anonymous but your review may still be made public.</p>
<p><bold>Do you want your identity to be public for this peer review?</bold> For information about this choice, including consent withdrawal, please see our <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://www.plos.org/privacy-policy" ns0:type="simple">Privacy Policy</ext-link>.</p>
<p>Reviewer #1: Yes: Nicolas WEISS, MD, PhD</p>
<p>Reviewer #2: No</p>
<p>[NOTE: If reviewer comments were submitted as an attachment file, they will be attached to this email and accessible via the submission site. Please log into your account, locate the manuscript record, and check for the action link "View Attachments". If this link does not appear, there are no attachment files to be viewed.]</p>
<p>While revising your submission, please upload your figure files to the Preflight Analysis and Conversion Engine (PACE) digital diagnostic tool, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://pacev2.apexcovantage.com/" ns0:type="simple">https://pacev2.apexcovantage.com/</ext-link>. PACE helps ensure that figures meet PLOS requirements. To use PACE, you must first register as a user. Registration is free. Then, login and navigate to the UPLOAD tab, where you will find detailed instructions on how to use the tool. If you encounter any issues or have any questions when using PACE, please email us at <email ns0:type="simple">figures@plos.org</email>. Please note that Supporting Information files do not need this step.</p>
</body>
</sub-article>
