<sub-article xmlns:ns0="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="aggregated-review-documents" id="pone.0222861.r002" specific-use="decision-letter">
<front-stub>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0222861.r002</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title>Decision Letter 0</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Lee</surname>
<given-names>Leo T.O.</given-names>
</name>
<role>Academic Editor</role>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<permissions>
<copyright-year>2019</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>Leo T.O. Lee</copyright-holder>
<license ns0:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
<license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" ns0:type="simple">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<related-object document-id="10.1371/journal.pone.0222861" document-id-type="doi" document-type="article" id="rel-obj002" link-type="peer-reviewed-article" />
<custom-meta-group>
<custom-meta>
<meta-name>Submission Version</meta-name>
<meta-value>0</meta-value>
</custom-meta>
</custom-meta-group>
</front-stub>
<body>
<p>
<named-content content-type="letter-date">17 Jul 2019</named-content>
</p>
<p>PONE-D-19-15932</p>
<p>AP-1 complex induces mouse translocator protein (18 kDa) expression by lipopolysaccharide in microglial cell line, BV-2</p>
<p>PLOS ONE</p>
<p>Dear Professor Nakamura,</p>
<p>Thank you for submitting your manuscript to PLOS ONE. After careful consideration, we feel that it has merit but does not fully meet PLOS ONE&#8217;s publication criteria as it currently stands. Therefore, we invite you to submit a revised version of the manuscript that addresses the points raised during the review process.</p>
<p>We would appreciate receiving your revised manuscript by Aug 31 2019 11:59PM. When you are ready to submit your revision, log on to <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://www.editorialmanager.com/pone/" ns0:type="simple">https://www.editorialmanager.com/pone/</ext-link> and select the 'Submissions Needing Revision' folder to locate your manuscript file.</p>
<p>If you would like to make changes to your financial disclosure, please include your updated statement in your cover letter.</p>
<p>To enhance the reproducibility of your results, we recommend that if applicable you deposit your laboratory protocols in protocols.io, where a protocol can be assigned its own identifier (DOI) such that it can be cited independently in the future. For instructions see: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://journals.plos.org/plosone/s/submission-guidelines#loc-laboratory-protocols" ns0:type="simple">http://journals.plos.org/plosone/s/submission-guidelines#loc-laboratory-protocols</ext-link></p>
<p>Please include the following items when submitting your revised manuscript:</p>
<p><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>A rebuttal letter that responds to each point raised by the academic editor and reviewer(s). This letter should be uploaded as separate file and labeled 'Response to Reviewers'.</p></list-item><list-item><p>A marked-up copy of your manuscript that highlights changes made to the original version. This file should be uploaded as separate file and labeled 'Revised Manuscript with Track Changes'.</p></list-item><list-item><p>An unmarked version of your revised paper without tracked changes. This file should be uploaded as separate file and labeled 'Manuscript'.</p></list-item></list></p>
<p>Please note while forming your response, if your article is accepted, you may have the opportunity to make the peer review history publicly available. The record will include editor decision letters (with reviews) and your responses to reviewer comments. If eligible, we will contact you to opt in or out.</p>
<p>We look forward to receiving your revised manuscript.</p>
<p>Kind regards,</p>
<p>Leo T.O. Lee, Ph.D.</p>
<p>Academic Editor</p>
<p>PLOS ONE</p>
<p>Journal Requirements:</p>
<p>1. When submitting your revision, we need you to address these additional requirements.</p>
<p>Please ensure that your manuscript meets PLOS ONE's style requirements, including those for file naming. The PLOS ONE style templates can be found at</p>
<p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://www.journals.plos.org/plosone/s/file?id=wjVg/PLOSOne_formatting_sample_main_body.pdf" ns0:type="simple">http://www.journals.plos.org/plosone/s/file?id=wjVg/PLOSOne_formatting_sample_main_body.pdf</ext-link> and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://www.journals.plos.org/plosone/s/file?id=ba62/PLOSOne_formatting_sample_title_authors_affiliations.pdf" ns0:type="simple">http://www.journals.plos.org/plosone/s/file?id=ba62/PLOSOne_formatting_sample_title_authors_affiliations.pdf</ext-link></p>
<p>[Note: HTML markup is below. Please do not edit.]</p>
<p>Reviewers' comments:</p>
<p>Reviewer's Responses to Questions</p>
<p><bold>Comments to the Author</bold></p>
<p>1. Is the manuscript technically sound, and do the data support the conclusions?</p>
<p>The manuscript must describe a technically sound piece of scientific research with data that supports the conclusions. Experiments must have been conducted rigorously, with appropriate controls, replication, and sample sizes. The conclusions must be drawn appropriately based on the data presented. </p>
<p>Reviewer #1: Yes</p>
<p>Reviewer #2: Yes</p>
<p>Reviewer #3: Partly</p>
<p>**********</p>
<p>2. Has the statistical analysis been performed appropriately and rigorously? </p>
<p>Reviewer #1: Yes</p>
<p>Reviewer #2: Yes</p>
<p>Reviewer #3: N/A</p>
<p>**********</p>
<p>3. Have the authors made all data underlying the findings in their manuscript fully available?</p>
<p>The <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://www.plosone.org/static/policies.action#sharing" ns0:type="simple">PLOS Data policy</ext-link> requires authors to make all data underlying the findings described in their manuscript fully available without restriction, with rare exception (please refer to the Data Availability Statement in the manuscript PDF file). The data should be provided as part of the manuscript or its supporting information, or deposited to a public repository. For example, in addition to summary statistics, the data points behind means, medians and variance measures should be available. If there are restrictions on publicly sharing data&#8212;e.g. participant privacy or use of data from a third party&#8212;those must be specified.</p>
<p>Reviewer #1: Yes</p>
<p>Reviewer #2: Yes</p>
<p>Reviewer #3: Yes</p>
<p>**********</p>
<p>4. Is the manuscript presented in an intelligible fashion and written in standard English?</p>
<p>PLOS ONE does not copyedit accepted manuscripts, so the language in submitted articles must be clear, correct, and unambiguous. Any typographical or grammatical errors should be corrected at revision, so please note any specific errors here.</p>
<p>Reviewer #1: Yes</p>
<p>Reviewer #2: Yes</p>
<p>Reviewer #3: No</p>
<p>**********</p>
<p>5. Review Comments to the Author</p>
<p>Please use the space provided to explain your answers to the questions above. You may also include additional comments for the author, including concerns about dual publication, research ethics, or publication ethics. (Please upload your review as an attachment if it exceeds 20,000 characters)</p>
<p>Reviewer #1: The manuscript could be improved by considering the following points</p>
<p>1. I think it would be important to include something about PU.1 in the discussion (The binding motif of PU.1 is in enhancer region (-593-520) and lies 3 bp apart from the AP1 core binding motif). The expression pattern of TSPO in microglia is very specific, and therefore Lineage dependent transcription factors (LDTFs) such as PU.1 have to play a role (Especially since we have already provided evidence of strong Pu.1 enrichment in this region). Infact, the initial steps of enhancer selection in closed chromatin regions containing regularly positioned nucleosomes involves the binding of LDTFs. This binding results in the depletion/sliding of nucleosomes to expose enhancer DNA sequences. Indeed, in microglia/macrophages, enhancers controlling endotoxin-stimulated gene expression are almost invariably bound by the lineage dependent Ets transcription factor Pu.1 (Ghisletti et al., 2010; Holtman et al., 2017). These LDTFs bound to enhancers induce histone modifications (such as H3K4me1) associated with a primed state of activity (Smale and Natoli, 2014). Histone mark H3K4me1 is a core chromatin signature of primed enhancers and serves as a beacon for signal-dependent effectors of signaling pathways such as nuclear factor-&#954;B (NF&#954;B), interferon responsive factors (IRFs) and activator protein 1 (AP-1) (Ghisletti et al., 2010; Heinz et al., 2010; Smale and Natoli, 2014).</p>
<p>Ghisletti, S., Barozzi, I., Mietton, F., Polletti, S., De Santa, F., Venturini, E., Gregory, L., Lonie, L., Chew, A., Wei, C.-L., et al. (2010). Identification and Characterization of Enhancers Controlling the Inflammatory Gene Expression Program in Macrophages. Immunity 32, 317&#8211;328.</p>
<p>Heinz, S., Benner, C., Spann, N., Bertolino, E., Lin, Y.C., Laslo, P., Cheng, J.X., Murre, C., Singh, H., and Glass, C.K. (2010). Simple combinations of lineage-determining transcription factors prime cis-regulatory elements required for macrophage and B cell identities. Mol. Cell 38, 576&#8211;589.</p>
<p>Holtman, I.R., Skola, D., and Glass, C.K. (2017). Transcriptional control of microglia phenotypes in health and disease. J. Clin. Invest. 127, 3220&#8211;3229.</p>
<p>Smale, S.T., and Natoli, G. (2014). Transcriptional control of inflammatory responses. Cold Spring Harb. Perspect. Biol. 6, a016261.</p>
<p>2. It would be important to comment on differences observed in TSPO expression following knockdown of cFos and cJun. In a recent paper (Raashid et al.Biochim Biophys Acta Gene Regul Mech. 2018 Dec;1861(12):1119-1133.), decreased TSPO expression was only observed following a combined knockdown of cJun and cFos. In the current paper, the authors report a decrease in TSPO expression when either cJun or cFos is knockdown. Is this due to cell-line differences? (I noticed they used a different BV-2 cell-line which was maintained in DMEM medium).</p>
<p>3. In paragraph 4 of the discussion, Sp1 transcription factor is discussed. There is no mention of either Sp3 or Sp4, despite Rashid et al. showing that these factors bind the GC-boxes in the proximal promoter (Sp1, Sp3 and Sp4 share common binding site motifs) and that knockdown of either Sp3 or Sp4 significantly reduces TSPO promoter activity in BV-2 microglia.</p>
<p>4. In paragraph 5 of the discussion, the authors state &#8220; human TSPO expression increases during the embryo to prenatal period and decreases during the neonatal period, and the TSPO expression level in the neonatal period is maintained throughout life. These data suggest that the TSPO functions, such as increasing cholesterol transport from cytosol to mitochondria and promoting pregnenolone production, might be important for fetal development.&#8221; While this statement might be true, I think it also important to acknowledge that the increase in TSPO expression during development might simply be a reflection of an activated microglia state. During development, microglia are predominantly in the amoeboid state as they play a major role in removing excessive produced apoptotic neurons and large amounts of extracellular debris from the developing CNS.</p>
<p>Reviewer #2: The authors adequately addressed the issues from the original review. The paper describes a data-supported mechanism for transcriptional regulation of TSPO in LPS-treated microglia. A few minor points:</p>
<p>1) Regarding M1/M2 classification - it should be noted that the range of microglial activation phenotypes is complex and that the M1/M2 classification in the paper is being used for the sake of simplicity.</p>
<p>2) The antibodies and oligonucleotide sequences used can be placed in supplemental information.</p>
<p>3) There were a few grammatical errors throughout the manuscript.</p>
<p>Reviewer #3: In this manuscript the authors described a potential mechanism of the increased TSPO expression after LPS treatment which were regulated by AP-1 complex and HDAC1 in BV-2 microglia cell at the transcriptional level. I have some specific issues that need clarification.</p>
<p>1. The title should be replaced as &#8220;Lipopolysaccharide induces mouse translocator protein (18 kDa) expression by AP-1 complex in microglial cell line, BV-2&#8221;.</p>
<p>2. As the authors stated in the manuscript, the concentration of HDAC1 (a transcriptional repressor) was decreased in the enhancer region of TSPO at the AP-1 binding site after LPS treatment. I have concerns about the potential effects of HDAC1 intervention on TSPO expression or LPS induced inflammatory reaction.</p>
<p>3. Writing of the paper might be improved to meet sufficient quality.</p>
<p>**********</p>
<p>6. PLOS authors have the option to publish the peer review history of their article (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://journals.plos.org/plosone/s/editorial-and-peer-review-process#loc-peer-review-history" ns0:type="simple">what does this mean?</ext-link>). If published, this will include your full peer review and any attached files.</p>
<p>If you choose &#8220;no&#8221;, your identity will remain anonymous but your review may still be made public.</p>
<p><bold>Do you want your identity to be public for this peer review?</bold> For information about this choice, including consent withdrawal, please see our <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://www.plos.org/privacy-policy" ns0:type="simple">Privacy Policy</ext-link>.</p>
<p>Reviewer #1: No</p>
<p>Reviewer #2: No</p>
<p>Reviewer #3: No</p>
<p>[NOTE: If reviewer comments were submitted as an attachment file, they will be attached to this email and accessible via the submission site. Please log into your account, locate the manuscript record, and check for the action link "View Attachments". If this link does not appear, there are no attachment files to be viewed.]</p>
<p>While revising your submission, please upload your figure files to the Preflight Analysis and Conversion Engine (PACE) digital diagnostic tool, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://pacev2.apexcovantage.com/" ns0:type="simple">https://pacev2.apexcovantage.com/</ext-link>. PACE helps ensure that figures meet PLOS requirements. To use PACE, you must first register as a user. Registration is free. Then, login and navigate to the UPLOAD tab, where you will find detailed instructions on how to use the tool. If you encounter any issues or have any questions when using PACE, please email us at <email ns0:type="simple">figures@plos.org</email>. Please note that Supporting Information files do not need this step.</p>
</body>
</sub-article>
