<sub-article xmlns:ns0="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="aggregated-review-documents" id="pone.0220683.r001" specific-use="decision-letter">
<front-stub>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0220683.r001</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title>Decision Letter 0</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Garc&#237;a</surname>
<given-names>M&#237;riam R.</given-names>
</name>
<role>Academic Editor</role>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<permissions>
<copyright-year>2019</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>M&#237;riam R. Garc&#237;a</copyright-holder>
<license ns0:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
<license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" ns0:type="simple">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<related-object document-id="10.1371/journal.pone.0220683" document-id-type="doi" document-type="article" id="rel-obj001" link-type="peer-reviewed-article" />
<custom-meta-group>
<custom-meta>
<meta-name>Submission Version</meta-name>
<meta-value>0</meta-value>
</custom-meta>
</custom-meta-group>
</front-stub>
<body>
<p>
<named-content content-type="letter-date">14 Jun 2019</named-content>
</p>
<p>PONE-D-19-14978</p>
<p>On the use of in-silico simulations to support experimental design: a case study in microbial inactivation of foods</p>
<p>PLOS ONE</p>
<p>Dear Dr. Egea,</p>
<p>Thank you for submitting your manuscript to PLOS ONE. After careful consideration, we feel that it has merit but does not fully meet PLOS ONE&#8217;s publication criteria as it currently stands. Therefore, we invite you to submit a revised version of the manuscript that addresses the points raised during the review process.</p>
<p>Both reviewers agree that the manuscript needs major corrections.&#160; Authors should pay special attention to critics regarding the methodology and data availability, as well as be clear on how data support the conclusions. Besides, although novelty and impact are not requisites in PLOS ONE, authors should be clear on how this work is original and different from the works in the literature.&#160;</p>
<p>We would appreciate receiving your revised manuscript by Jul 29 2019 11:59PM. When you are ready to submit your revision, log on to <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://www.editorialmanager.com/pone/" ns0:type="simple">https://www.editorialmanager.com/pone/</ext-link> and select the 'Submissions Needing Revision' folder to locate your manuscript file.</p>
<p>If you would like to make changes to your financial disclosure, please include your updated statement in your cover letter.</p>
<p>To enhance the reproducibility of your results, we recommend that if applicable you deposit your laboratory protocols in protocols.io, where a protocol can be assigned its own identifier (DOI) such that it can be cited independently in the future. For instructions see: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://journals.plos.org/plosone/s/submission-guidelines#loc-laboratory-protocols" ns0:type="simple">http://journals.plos.org/plosone/s/submission-guidelines#loc-laboratory-protocols</ext-link></p>
<p>Please include the following items when submitting your revised manuscript:</p>
<p><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>A rebuttal letter that responds to each point raised by the academic editor and reviewer(s). This letter should be uploaded as separate file and labeled 'Response to Reviewers'.</p></list-item><list-item><p>A marked-up copy of your manuscript that highlights changes made to the original version. This file should be uploaded as separate file and labeled 'Revised Manuscript with Track Changes'.</p></list-item><list-item><p>An unmarked version of your revised paper without tracked changes. This file should be uploaded as separate file and labeled 'Manuscript'.</p></list-item></list></p>
<p>Please note while forming your response, if your article is accepted, you may have the opportunity to make the peer review history publicly available. The record will include editor decision letters (with reviews) and your responses to reviewer comments. If eligible, we will contact you to opt in or out.</p>
<p>We look forward to receiving your revised manuscript.</p>
<p>Kind regards,</p>
<p>M&#237;riam R. Garc&#237;a</p>
<p>Academic Editor</p>
<p>PLOS ONE</p>
<p>Journal Requirements:</p>
<p>When submitting your revision, we need you to address these additional requirements.</p>
<p>1. Please ensure that your manuscript meets PLOS ONE's style requirements, including those for file naming. The PLOS ONE style templates can be found at</p>
<p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://www.journals.plos.org/plosone/s/file?id=wjVg/PLOSOne_formatting_sample_main_body.pdf" ns0:type="simple">http://www.journals.plos.org/plosone/s/file?id=wjVg/PLOSOne_formatting_sample_main_body.pdf</ext-link> and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://www.journals.plos.org/plosone/s/file?id=ba62/PLOSOne_formatting_sample_title_authors_affiliations.pdf" ns0:type="simple">http://www.journals.plos.org/plosone/s/file?id=ba62/PLOSOne_formatting_sample_title_authors_affiliations.pdf</ext-link></p>
<p>[Note: HTML markup is below. Please do not edit.]</p>
<p>Reviewers' comments:</p>
<p>Reviewer's Responses to Questions</p>
<p><bold>Comments to the Author</bold></p>
<p>1. Is the manuscript technically sound, and do the data support the conclusions?</p>
<p>The manuscript must describe a technically sound piece of scientific research with data that supports the conclusions. Experiments must have been conducted rigorously, with appropriate controls, replication, and sample sizes. The conclusions must be drawn appropriately based on the data presented. </p>
<p>Reviewer #1: Yes</p>
<p>Reviewer #2: Partly</p>
<p>**********</p>
<p>2. Has the statistical analysis been performed appropriately and rigorously? </p>
<p>Reviewer #1: Yes</p>
<p>Reviewer #2: No</p>
<p>**********</p>
<p>3. Have the authors made all data underlying the findings in their manuscript fully available?</p>
<p>The <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://www.plosone.org/static/policies.action#sharing" ns0:type="simple">PLOS Data policy</ext-link> requires authors to make all data underlying the findings described in their manuscript fully available without restriction, with rare exception (please refer to the Data Availability Statement in the manuscript PDF file). The data should be provided as part of the manuscript or its supporting information, or deposited to a public repository. For example, in addition to summary statistics, the data points behind means, medians and variance measures should be available. If there are restrictions on publicly sharing data&#8212;e.g. participant privacy or use of data from a third party&#8212;those must be specified.</p>
<p>Reviewer #1: No</p>
<p>Reviewer #2: Yes</p>
<p>**********</p>
<p>4. Is the manuscript presented in an intelligible fashion and written in standard English?</p>
<p>PLOS ONE does not copyedit accepted manuscripts, so the language in submitted articles must be clear, correct, and unambiguous. Any typographical or grammatical errors should be corrected at revision, so please note any specific errors here.</p>
<p>Reviewer #1: Yes</p>
<p>Reviewer #2: Yes</p>
<p>**********</p>
<p>5. Review Comments to the Author</p>
<p>Please use the space provided to explain your answers to the questions above. You may also include additional comments for the author, including concerns about dual publication, research ethics, or publication ethics. (Please upload your review as an attachment if it exceeds 20,000 characters)</p>
<p>Reviewer #1: Summary:</p>
<p>The authors discuss the use of OED for identifying the Bigelow model for thermal microbial inactivation. Specifically, the manuscript focusses on the selection of the sampling times and the type of temperature profile.</p>
<p>Major comments:</p>
<p>- The statement on lines 88 and 89 is either not really correct or the authors did not clearly state what they meant. Since OED has been applied in predictive microbiology for over 20 years, it definitely falls already in the category of &#8220;currently available techniques&#8221;. As stated in the article, by simply calculating the inverse of the FIM for a proposed experimental design, it is already possible to have an idea of the precision that will be obtained on the parameter estimates (and this is just the underlying principle of OED). Therefore, currently available techniques can definitely provide such information.</p>
<p>- In general, the final section of the introduction (lines 88-100) should more clearly state the novelty of this research. Is it just providing information on optimal sampling schemes? Or is it the underlying method for determining such sampling schemes? Try to state more clearly what knowledge was already available and what is novel about this work with respect to the available research.</p>
<p>- The penalty function that is used (lines 153-162), appears to provide a weighting that is very arbitrary. Why don&#8217;t the authors apply constraints on the sampling times to be optimised? Using a set of linear inequality constraints could lead to a much less arbitrary solution to the same problem.</p>
<p>- For the results presented in Section 3.1, the sampling points of the OED designs should be illustrated and discussed. Use, e.g., a relative frequency bar chart to illustrate all sample points over the Monte Carlo simulation. These charts can be represented as three subfigures, corresponding with those of Figure 1. It should be possible to link these sampling points with the sensitivity equations in Figure 3.</p>
<p>- It is not really clear to me what the advantage is of the Monte Carlo method proposed in this publication. Why would you not just use the approximation of the variance-covariance matrix based on the inverse of the FIM of your design to estimate the uncertainty on the model parameters? What is the added value of this Monte Carlo simulation?</p>
<p>Minor comments:</p>
<p>- Line 21: Remove &#8220;)&#8221;.</p>
<p>- Figures 1 - 3: Use a line width of minimum 2 for the curves.</p>
<p>- Line 211: calculate -&gt; calculating.</p>
<p>- Line 311: Takes what into account? Complete this sentence.</p>
<p>- Line 334-335: Use a capital letter for &#8220;Van Derlinden&#8221;.</p>
<p>- Line 345: smallest -&gt; smaller.</p>
<p>- Simulation data should be made available.</p>
<p>Reviewer #2: The manuscript shows an interesting case study of microbial inactivation in foods with in-silico simulation analysis to support the suggestion of the two complementary methodologies to predict the parameter precision for a given experimental design. The manuscript is sound, but some major concerns are listed, and minor corrections are suggested below.</p>
<p>Major:</p>
<p>- Lines 115-121: The three profiles proposed have very different heating rates which impact on microbial inactivation. What assumptions were made to propose these temperature profiles? Can authors propose other temperature profiles, based on some thermal treatment of real food or other more realistic profiles for the case study (e.g. with residence time)? This is a concerning limitation issue, as suggested by own authors (lines 196-198) &#8220;Although previous studies have proposed algorithms to select optimal profiles, this example will be limited to the study of the three inactivation profiles shown in Figure 1&#8221;.</p>
<p>- Lines 144-145: Did authors test FIM criterions other than D-optimal? Why was D-optimal chosen? Advantages/disadvantages of that criterion against others in the context of the study (model and assumptions) should be presented.</p>
<p>- Lines 229-232: &#8220;One hundred Monte Carlo simulations have been performed, considering ten sampling points for each experimental design (OED and uniform) for each temperature profile. Simulations have been repeated with a higher number of simulations without observing differences in the results (not shown)&#8221;. Why the simulation tests started from ten sampling points? Kinetic inactivation experiments often have less than ten sampling points due to practical experimental issues. Furthermore, experiments should be simulated from less than ten sampling points in order to identify differences in the results (since no differences were reported with ten or more sampling points).</p>
<p>- Lines 249-251: &#8220;Therefore, the shape of the temperature profile should be taken into account when designing experiments for characterization of microbial inactivation under dynamic conditions&#8221;. Did authors try to design optimal temperature profiles before or together with optimal sampling points?</p>
<p>Minor:</p>
<p>- Lines 22-24. Present some reference about &#8220;scarce contributions&#8221;.</p>
<p>- Lines 78-81: FIM to quantify information in OED has been applied before Lehmann and Casella (1998).</p>
<p>- Line 120: 0.5 &#186;C/min and 10 &#186;C/min (and instead comma).</p>
<p>- Line 147: The &#8220;equation&#8221; (2) is incomplete (equal to?).</p>
<p>- Lines 183-226: Many information is about method and should be presented in appropriate section. Unnecessary repeated information can be removed. Results effectively start to be shown at line 231.</p>
<p>- Lines 242-243: &#8220;most of the inactivation occurs in a short time at the end of the experiment&#8221;. In Profile B most of the inactivation occurs at the middle of the experiment. In the end of the experiment, almost no inactivation occurs (due to the low temperature), as can be seen in Figure 1.</p>
<p>- Lines 298-318: Authors discussed about loss of information in uniform design measured by the inverse of the FIM determinant. In Figure 2C, there is an unexpected loss of information of OED experiment when adding from 16 to 17 points. How authors can explain this fact?</p>
<p>- Lines 374-375: &#8220;(3) that increasing the number of points in a uniform design does not ensure a higher precision&#8221;, as well as in some OED (e.g. profile C).</p>
<p>- Lines 471-472: Garre et al. 2017b reference is incomplete.</p>
<p>- Figure 3: The elements of the figure should have complete description in the caption. Information about A and B, red and green curves.</p>
<p>- Results of Monte Carlo simulations to D and z values could be used to presented and assess additional information.</p>
<p>**********</p>
<p>6. PLOS authors have the option to publish the peer review history of their article (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://journals.plos.org/plosone/s/editorial-and-peer-review-process#loc-peer-review-history" ns0:type="simple">what does this mean?</ext-link>). If published, this will include your full peer review and any attached files.</p>
<p>If you choose &#8220;no&#8221;, your identity will remain anonymous but your review may still be made public.</p>
<p><bold>Do you want your identity to be public for this peer review?</bold> For information about this choice, including consent withdrawal, please see our <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://www.plos.org/privacy-policy" ns0:type="simple">Privacy Policy</ext-link>.</p>
<p>Reviewer #1: Yes: Simen Akkermans</p>
<p>Reviewer #2: No</p>
<p>[NOTE: If reviewer comments were submitted as an attachment file, they will be attached to this email and accessible via the submission site. Please log into your account, locate the manuscript record, and check for the action link "View Attachments". If this link does not appear, there are no attachment files to be viewed.]</p>
<p>While revising your submission, please upload your figure files to the Preflight Analysis and Conversion Engine (PACE) digital diagnostic tool, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://pacev2.apexcovantage.com/" ns0:type="simple">https://pacev2.apexcovantage.com/</ext-link>. PACE helps ensure that figures meet PLOS requirements. To use PACE, you must first register as a user. Registration is free. Then, login and navigate to the UPLOAD tab, where you will find detailed instructions on how to use the tool. If you encounter any issues or have any questions when using PACE, please email us at <email ns0:type="simple">figures@plos.org</email>. Please note that Supporting Information files do not need this step.</p>
</body>
</sub-article>
