<sub-article xmlns:ns0="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="aggregated-review-documents" id="pone.0222467.r001" specific-use="decision-letter">
<front-stub>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0222467.r001</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title>Decision Letter 0</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Wolffsohn</surname>
<given-names>James</given-names>
</name>
<role>Academic Editor</role>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<permissions>
<copyright-year>2019</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>James Wolffsohn</copyright-holder>
<license ns0:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
<license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" ns0:type="simple">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<related-object document-id="10.1371/journal.pone.0222467" document-id-type="doi" document-type="article" id="rel-obj001" link-type="peer-reviewed-article" />
<custom-meta-group>
<custom-meta>
<meta-name>Submission Version</meta-name>
<meta-value>0</meta-value>
</custom-meta>
</custom-meta-group>
</front-stub>
<body>
<p>
<named-content content-type="letter-date">31 Jul 2019</named-content>
</p>
<p>PONE-D-19-15509</p>
<p>Impact of tear dynamics on the reliability of perimetry in patients with dry eye</p>
<p>PLOS ONE</p>
<p>Dear Dr. Sagara,</p>
<p>Thank you for submitting your manuscript to PLOS ONE. After careful consideration, we feel that it has merit but does not fully meet PLOS ONE&#8217;s publication criteria as it currently stands. Therefore, we invite you to submit a revised version of the manuscript that addresses the points raised during the review process.</p>
<p>We would appreciate receiving your revised manuscript by Sep 14 2019 11:59PM. When you are ready to submit your revision, log on to <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://www.editorialmanager.com/pone/" ns0:type="simple">https://www.editorialmanager.com/pone/</ext-link> and select the 'Submissions Needing Revision' folder to locate your manuscript file.</p>
<p>If you would like to make changes to your financial disclosure, please include your updated statement in your cover letter.</p>
<p>To enhance the reproducibility of your results, we recommend that if applicable you deposit your laboratory protocols in protocols.io, where a protocol can be assigned its own identifier (DOI) such that it can be cited independently in the future. For instructions see: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://journals.plos.org/plosone/s/submission-guidelines#loc-laboratory-protocols" ns0:type="simple">http://journals.plos.org/plosone/s/submission-guidelines#loc-laboratory-protocols</ext-link></p>
<p>Please include the following items when submitting your revised manuscript:</p>
<p><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>A rebuttal letter that responds to each point raised by the academic editor and reviewer(s). This letter should be uploaded as separate file and labeled 'Response to Reviewers'.</p></list-item><list-item><p>A marked-up copy of your manuscript that highlights changes made to the original version. This file should be uploaded as separate file and labeled 'Revised Manuscript with Track Changes'.</p></list-item><list-item><p>An unmarked version of your revised paper without tracked changes. This file should be uploaded as separate file and labeled 'Manuscript'.</p></list-item></list></p>
<p>Please note while forming your response, if your article is accepted, you may have the opportunity to make the peer review history publicly available. The record will include editor decision letters (with reviews) and your responses to reviewer comments. If eligible, we will contact you to opt in or out.</p>
<p>We look forward to receiving your revised manuscript.</p>
<p>Kind regards,</p>
<p>James Wolffsohn, PhD</p>
<p>Academic Editor</p>
<p>PLOS ONE</p>
<p>Journal Requirements:</p>
<p>1. When submitting your revision, we need you to address these additional requirements.</p>
<p>Please ensure that your manuscript meets PLOS ONE's style requirements, including those for file naming. The PLOS ONE style templates can be found at</p>
<p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://www.journals.plos.org/plosone/s/file?id=wjVg/PLOSOne_formatting_sample_main_body.pdf" ns0:type="simple">http://www.journals.plos.org/plosone/s/file?id=wjVg/PLOSOne_formatting_sample_main_body.pdf</ext-link> and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://www.journals.plos.org/plosone/s/file?id=ba62/PLOSOne_formatting_sample_title_authors_affiliations.pdf" ns0:type="simple">http://www.journals.plos.org/plosone/s/file?id=ba62/PLOSOne_formatting_sample_title_authors_affiliations.pdf</ext-link></p>
<p>2. We note that you have stated that you will provide repository information for your data at acceptance. Should your manuscript be accepted for publication, we will hold it until you provide the relevant accession numbers or DOIs necessary to access your data. If you wish to make changes to your Data Availability statement, please describe these changes in your cover letter and we will update your Data Availability statement to reflect the information you provide.</p>
<p>Additional Editor Comments (if provided):</p>
<p>There are some significant issues to address including further data analysis for this research to be published in PlosOne so please respond to each of the reviewers comments carefully.</p>
<p>[Note: HTML markup is below. Please do not edit.]</p>
<p>Reviewers' comments:</p>
<p>Reviewer's Responses to Questions</p>
<p><bold>Comments to the Author</bold></p>
<p>1. Is the manuscript technically sound, and do the data support the conclusions?</p>
<p>The manuscript must describe a technically sound piece of scientific research with data that supports the conclusions. Experiments must have been conducted rigorously, with appropriate controls, replication, and sample sizes. The conclusions must be drawn appropriately based on the data presented. </p>
<p>Reviewer #1: Partly</p>
<p>Reviewer #2: Partly</p>
<p>**********</p>
<p>2. Has the statistical analysis been performed appropriately and rigorously? </p>
<p>Reviewer #1: Yes</p>
<p>Reviewer #2: No</p>
<p>**********</p>
<p>3. Have the authors made all data underlying the findings in their manuscript fully available?</p>
<p>The <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://www.plosone.org/static/policies.action#sharing" ns0:type="simple">PLOS Data policy</ext-link> requires authors to make all data underlying the findings described in their manuscript fully available without restriction, with rare exception (please refer to the Data Availability Statement in the manuscript PDF file). The data should be provided as part of the manuscript or its supporting information, or deposited to a public repository. For example, in addition to summary statistics, the data points behind means, medians and variance measures should be available. If there are restrictions on publicly sharing data&#8212;e.g. participant privacy or use of data from a third party&#8212;those must be specified.</p>
<p>Reviewer #1: Yes</p>
<p>Reviewer #2: Yes</p>
<p>**********</p>
<p>4. Is the manuscript presented in an intelligible fashion and written in standard English?</p>
<p>PLOS ONE does not copyedit accepted manuscripts, so the language in submitted articles must be clear, correct, and unambiguous. Any typographical or grammatical errors should be corrected at revision, so please note any specific errors here.</p>
<p>Reviewer #1: Yes</p>
<p>Reviewer #2: Yes</p>
<p>**********</p>
<p>5. Review Comments to the Author</p>
<p>Please use the space provided to explain your answers to the questions above. You may also include additional comments for the author, including concerns about dual publication, research ethics, or publication ethics. (Please upload your review as an attachment if it exceeds 20,000 characters)</p>
<p>Reviewer #1: I read this article with interest. Although, I would like to bring to your attentions some comments and thoughts I had while reviewing your manuscript.</p>
<p>May I begin saying that I suggest to find an alternative title as I don't agree that the research has evaluated the dynamics of the tear film. In fact, if we consider the Oxford English Dictionary, the term "dynamics" is explained as follow: "dynamics [uncountable] the science of the forces involved in movement (belongs to fluid dynamics)". For this, reason I think "tear dynamics" can be replaced with "tear characteristics" or "tear metrics" or "tear properties".</p>
<p>Secondly, in the "Examinations" section (line 98 and further) it is not clearly defined in which order the "tear dynamics and ocular surface condition" have been performed. As you know, some of the tear tests performed may affect the measurements because of their invasiviness (e.g. TFBUT, Schirmer test, etc.). Additionally, it is not clear how the "expert perimetrists" counted the number of blinks BEFORE perimetry (e.g. manual counting, click-counting with electronic device, click-counting using an external device such as eye tracker, etc.).</p>
<p>In the results section, I found there are the first 5 sentences (lines from 126 to 130) which are describing the subjects. I believe this should be moved in the participants section.</p>
<p>Table 2 caption (line 144 and 145) says: "Comparison of Blink Rate Parameters during Perimetry etc" but there are also included other tear metrics, not only the blink rate parameters.</p>
<p>Line 36: it says medications but I believe you want to say "lubricants" or "eyedrops".</p>
<p>Line 72: could you please define long=term follow-ups: days, weeks, months or years?</p>
<p>Line 85: could you please clarify what does it mean when you say "we only examined eyes in which perimetry were initally performed?" Is this an inclusion criteria?</p>
<p>Line 186 "ocular surface disorder", in this sentence should be "ocular surface parameters".</p>
<p>Lines 172, 186, 226, 236 please specify the sentence that says "some eyes" in number or percentage.</p>
<p>Lines 180, 181,205 please specify the standard deviations for those measurements.</p>
<p>Line 232 please specify "low" in number or percentage.</p>
<p>Lines from 242 to 245 and lines from 153 to 155: these short paragraphs are hard to follow, could you please rephrase them?</p>
<p>Line 258 it says medications but I believe you want to say "lubricants" or "eyedrops".</p>
<p>Line 225 a verb is missing where it does say "and not to decrease their...".</p>
<p>Line 231, strip meniscometry is not a non-invasive test as provoke tearing and measures tear reflex volume.</p>
<p>Line 212 "older age" should be "in elderly patients".</p>
<p>Line 110: this is just a suggestion. In order to improve consistency along the manuscript, I suggest to use all numbers when you mention "number of eyes" (e.g. line 110 says "eight eyes" while line 111 says "35 eyes"). Same in line 126 wherer it does say "twenty-seven eyes" and after "29 eyes").</p>
<p>Reviewer #2: The effect of perimetry on the ocular surface and the effect of the ocular surface on the data collected in perimetry is of interest, but the title only covers one of these aspects. What is critical is not the reliability indicators, but the actual field loss pattern and clinical decision making based on this. The authors should consider how to analyse this to understand the true impact of ocular surface disease on glaucoma management.</p>
<p>The abstract is hard to read without sub-headings.</p>
<p>Ln17 &#8220;specific effects&#8221; is not clear</p>
<p>Ln21 better to state &#8220;Forty-three patients with symptoms and an unstable tear film (DE according to the 2016 Japanese diagnostic criteria)&#8230;&#8221; why not use the more recent global diagnostic consensus?</p>
<p>Ln24 &#8220;fluorescein staining&#8221; would be clearer to the reader than &#8220;Bijsterveld score&#8221;. Why were symptoms measured before and after perimetry such as using the SANDE?</p>
<p>Ln28 why would TFBUT increase after perimetry? &#8211; state what this is compared to</p>
<p>Ln34 this is not a conclusion drawn from the data so remove &#8211; also relevant to Ln259. It can be in the discussion though as a possible remedy to the effects observed</p>
<p>Avoid personal pronouns such as &#8220;we&#8221; throughout</p>
<p>Ln62 The sample size needs to be justified</p>
<p>Ln100 explain how TFBUT was measured. It needs to be much clearer what were the baseline tests of ocular surface health and what were the characteristics studied to determine change with the perimetry</p>
<p>Ln104 &#8220;optometrists&#8221; misspelt</p>
<p>Ln105 were the participants unaware their blink rate was being observed</p>
<p>Ln108 and beyond. The study is almost certainly not powered to break the analysis down into groups as small as n=8. This should be removed throughout.</p>
<p>Ln115 was the data not normally distributed resulting in non-parametric tests being applied?</p>
<p>Ln127 it is essential to know whether the anti-glaucoma drops were preserved or not and to do an analysis of ocular surface parameters and the effect of perimetry base on this if the sample split size is sufficient</p>
<p>Do not repeat data which is rightly in the tables in the text, which currently makes it much harder to read</p>
<p>Ln221 high and low are relative terms so should be higher and lower</p>
<p>Ln228 explain what is meant about pattern of blinking.</p>
<p>More discussion is needed of the trade off between higher concentration leading to less blinking (and less likely to miss a stimulus), but then more ocular irritation leading to a loss of concentration.</p>
<p>Ln239-242 these sentences are unclear &#8211; the fact that metrics are associated does not mean one causes the other</p>
<p>**********</p>
<p>6. PLOS authors have the option to publish the peer review history of their article (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://journals.plos.org/plosone/s/editorial-and-peer-review-process#loc-peer-review-history" ns0:type="simple">what does this mean?</ext-link>). If published, this will include your full peer review and any attached files.</p>
<p>If you choose &#8220;no&#8221;, your identity will remain anonymous but your review may still be made public.</p>
<p><bold>Do you want your identity to be public for this peer review?</bold> For information about this choice, including consent withdrawal, please see our <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://www.plos.org/privacy-policy" ns0:type="simple">Privacy Policy</ext-link>.</p>
<p>Reviewer #1: No</p>
<p>Reviewer #2: No</p>
<p>[NOTE: If reviewer comments were submitted as an attachment file, they will be attached to this email and accessible via the submission site. Please log into your account, locate the manuscript record, and check for the action link "View Attachments". If this link does not appear, there are no attachment files to be viewed.]</p>
<p>While revising your submission, please upload your figure files to the Preflight Analysis and Conversion Engine (PACE) digital diagnostic tool, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://pacev2.apexcovantage.com/" ns0:type="simple">https://pacev2.apexcovantage.com/</ext-link>. PACE helps ensure that figures meet PLOS requirements. To use PACE, you must first register as a user. Registration is free. Then, login and navigate to the UPLOAD tab, where you will find detailed instructions on how to use the tool. If you encounter any issues or have any questions when using PACE, please email us at <email ns0:type="simple">figures@plos.org</email>. Please note that Supporting Information files do not need this step.</p>
</body>
</sub-article>
