<sub-article xmlns:ns0="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="editor-report" id="pone.0221750.r004" specific-use="acceptance-letter">
<front-stub>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0221750.r004</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title>Acceptance letter</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Katsanos</surname>
<given-names>Aristeidis H.</given-names>
</name>
<role>Academic Editor</role>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<permissions>
<copyright-year>2019</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>Aristeidis H. Katsanos</copyright-holder>
<license ns0:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
<license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" ns0:type="simple">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<related-object document-id="10.1371/journal.pone.0221750" document-id-type="doi" document-type="article" id="rel-obj004" link-type="peer-reviewed-article" />
</front-stub>
<body>
<p>
<named-content content-type="letter-date">20 Aug 2019</named-content>
</p>
<p>PONE-D-19-17386R1 </p>
<p>Aspirin better than clopidogrel on major adverse cardiovascular events reduction after ischemic stroke: a retrospective nationwide cohort study </p>
<p>Dear Dr. Hu:</p>
<p>I am pleased to inform you that your manuscript has been deemed suitable for publication in PLOS ONE. Congratulations! Your manuscript is now with our production department. </p>
<p>If your institution or institutions have a press office, please notify them about your upcoming paper at this point, to enable them to help maximize its impact. If they will be preparing press materials for this manuscript, please inform our press team within the next 48 hours. Your manuscript will remain under strict press embargo until 2 pm Eastern Time on the date of publication. For more information please contact <email ns0:type="simple">onepress@plos.org</email>.</p>
<p>For any other questions or concerns, please email <email ns0:type="simple">plosone@plos.org</email>. </p>
<p>Thank you for submitting your work to PLOS ONE.</p>
<p>With kind regards,</p>
<p>PLOS ONE Editorial Office Staff</p>
<p>on behalf of</p>
<p>Dr. Aristeidis H. Katsanos  </p>
<p>Academic Editor</p>
<p>PLOS ONE</p>
</body>
</sub-article>
