<sub-article article-type="author-comment" id="pone.0223097.r004">
<front-stub>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0223097.r004</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title>Author response to Decision Letter 1</article-title>
</title-group>
<related-object document-id="10.1371/journal.pone.0223097" document-id-type="doi" document-type="peer-reviewed-article" id="rel-obj004" link-type="rebutted-decision-letter" object-id="10.1371/journal.pone.0223097.r003" object-id-type="doi" object-type="decision-letter" />
<custom-meta-group>
<custom-meta>
<meta-name>Submission Version</meta-name>
<meta-value>2</meta-value>
</custom-meta>
</custom-meta-group>
</front-stub>
<body>
<p>
<named-content content-type="author-response-date">27 Aug 2019</named-content>
</p>
<p>August 27 2019,</p>
<p>Dear Dr. Conly,</p>
<p>Thank you for these comments. Each addressed below.</p>
<p>Sincerely,</p>
<p>Dr. Kevin Schwartz</p>
<p>On behalf of the co-authors</p>
<p>Comments:</p>
<p>&#8226; Thank you for the title change as per the reviewer comments - please add " for patients 65 years of age and older" as well to make this point even more explicit. Also mention this point in the sentence in the first paragraph of the Discussion.</p>
<p>Response: Added suggested line to title and line 215 in the discussion</p>
<p>&#8226; You have added the additional databases available in the Introduction as requested  but the references do not  reflect the actual databases - please apply more direct references and limit the your selection of self citations which are both  indirect and excessive.</p>
<p>Response: The references were selected as examples for the aforementioned databases. Reference 7 used IQVIAs GPM database; We have added reference 8, which used CompuScript; reference 9 is an example of the ODB database; reference 10 used IQVIAs Xponent database; reference 11 used EMRALD (an administrative electronic medical record database). We have removed one of the EMRALD references.</p>
<p>&#8226; There are an excessive number of references cited in the Introduction about the point of both the CDC and Health  Canada  using the IQVIA data ie 17-39 and not all are necessary - please reduce the number by at least 50%.</p>
<p>Response: Reduced as requested</p>
<p>&#8226; The sentence containing " and the validity of IQVIA data has been assessed in some jurisdictions. [15] [16]" provides examples from within Canada and for broader populations than 65 and older and deserves to have  this point added. Alternatively it could be added to the  second paragraph of the Discussion when you speak about the use of this data in the US and Canada and add it as part of the academic discussion on the use of these databases. </p>
<p>Response: Moved this point and references to Discussion paragraph 2, line 225 as suggested</p>
<p>&#8226; There is a stray legend in italics on lines 204-205 just near the end of the Results - please correct this.</p>
<p>Response: subheading removed as requested</p>
<p>&#8226; Despite an explicit request, the Reference section continues to have multiple errors - incorrect format not in the standard style for date ( sometimes at the front of the reference in brackets and other times elsewhere and ), non use if urls where they should be present,  case errors everywhere and non use of italics for Latin terms etc.  - again too numerous to count. . Please correct  (do not rely on Mendeley which does not pick up all the formatting issues) or the manuscript will be returned again .</p>
<p>Response: References edited to specifications</p>
</body>
</sub-article>
