<sub-article xmlns:ns0="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="editor-report" id="pbio.3000473.r001" specific-use="decision-letter">
<front-stub>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pbio.3000473.r001</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title>Decision Letter 0</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Richardson</surname>
<given-names>Lauren A</given-names>
</name>
<role>Senior Editor</role>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<permissions>
<copyright-year>2019</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>Lauren A Richardson</copyright-holder>
<license ns0:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
<license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" ns0:type="simple">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<related-object document-id="10.1371/journal.pbio.3000473" document-id-type="doi" document-type="article" id="rel-obj001" link-type="peer-reviewed-article" />
<custom-meta-group>
<custom-meta>
<meta-name>Submission Version</meta-name>
<meta-value>0</meta-value>
</custom-meta>
</custom-meta-group>
</front-stub>
<body>
<p>
<named-content content-type="letter-date">17 Jun 2019</named-content>
</p>
<p>Dear Dr Spielmann, </p>
<p>Thank you for submitting your manuscript entitled "EXP1 is critical for nutrient uptake across the parasitophorous vacuole membrane of malaria parasites" for consideration as a Research Article by PLOS Biology.</p>
<p>Your manuscript has now been evaluated by the PLOS Biology editorial staff as well as by an academic editor with relevant expertise and I am writing to let you know that we would like to send your submission out for external peer review.</p>
<p>However, before we can send your manuscript to reviewers, we need you to complete your submission by providing the metadata that is required for full assessment. To this end, please login to Editorial Manager where you will find the paper in the 'Submissions Needing Revisions' folder on your homepage. Please click 'Revise Submission' from the Action Links and complete all additional questions in the submission questionnaire.</p>
<p>**Important**: Please also see below for further information regarding completing the MDAR reporting checklist. The checklist can be accessed here: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://plos.io/MDARChecklist" ns0:type="simple">https://plos.io/MDARChecklist</ext-link> </p>
<p>Please re-submit your manuscript and the checklist, within two working days, i.e. by Jun 19 2019 11:59PM.</p>
<p>Login to Editorial Manager here: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://www.editorialmanager.com/pbiology" ns0:type="simple">https://www.editorialmanager.com/pbiology</ext-link> </p>
<p>During resubmission, you will be invited to opt-in to posting your pre-review manuscript as a bioRxiv preprint. Visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://journals.plos.org/plosbiology/s/preprints" ns0:type="simple">http://journals.plos.org/plosbiology/s/preprints</ext-link> for full details. If you consent to posting your current manuscript as a preprint, please upload a single Preprint PDF when you re-submit. </p>
<p>Once your full submission is complete, your paper will undergo a series of checks in preparation for peer review. Once your manuscript has passed all checks it will be sent out for review. </p>
<p>Feel free to email us at <email ns0:type="simple">plosbiology@plos.org</email> if you have any queries relating to your submission.</p>
<p>Kind regards,</p>
<p>Lauren A Richardson, Ph.D,</p>
<p>Senior Editor</p>
<p>PLOS Biology</p>
<p>==================</p>
<p>INFORMATION REGARDING THE REPORTING CHECKLIST:</p>
<p>PLOS Biology is pleased to support the "minimum reporting standards in the life sciences" initiative (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://osf.io/preprints/metaarxiv/9sm4x/" ns0:type="simple">https://osf.io/preprints/metaarxiv/9sm4x/</ext-link>). This effort brings together a number of leading journals and reproducibility experts to develop minimum expectations for reporting information about Materials (including data and code), Design, Analysis and Reporting (MDAR) in published papers. We believe broad alignment on these standards will be to the benefit of authors, reviewers, journals and the wider research community and will help drive better practise in publishing reproducible research. </p>
<p>We are therefore participating in a community pilot involving a small number of life science journals to test the MDAR checklist. The checklist is intended to help authors, reviewers and editors adopt and implement the minimum reporting framework.  </p>
<p>IMPORTANT: We have chosen your manuscript to participate in this trial. The relevant documents can be located here:</p>
<p>MDAR reporting checklist (to be filled in by you): <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://plos.io/MDARChecklist" ns0:type="simple">https://plos.io/MDARChecklist</ext-link></p>
<p>**We strongly encourage you to complete the MDAR reporting checklist and return it to us with your full submission, as described above.  We would also be very grateful if you could complete this author survey:</p>
<p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://forms.gle/seEgCrDtM6GLKFGQA" ns0:type="simple">https://forms.gle/seEgCrDtM6GLKFGQA</ext-link> </p>
<p>Additional background information:</p>
<p>Interpreting the MDAR Framework: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://plos.io/MDARFramework" ns0:type="simple">https://plos.io/MDARFramework</ext-link> </p>
<p>Please note that your completed checklist and survey will be shared with the minimum reporting standards working group.  However, the working group will not be provided with access to the manuscript or any other confidential information including author identities, manuscript titles or abstracts.  Feedback from this process will be used to consider next steps, which might include revisions to the content of the checklist.  Data and materials from this initial trial will be publicly shared in September 2019.  Data will only be provided in aggregate form and will not be parsed by individual article or by journal, so as to respect the confidentiality of responses.  </p>
<p>Please treat the checklist and elaboration as confidential as public release is planned for September 2019.</p>
<p>We would be grateful for any feedback you may have.</p>
</body>
</sub-article>
