<sub-article xmlns:ns0="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="aggregated-review-documents" id="pone.0223150.r003" specific-use="decision-letter">
<front-stub>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0223150.r003</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title>Decision Letter 1</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Vaismoradi</surname>
<given-names>Mojtaba</given-names>
</name>
<role>Academic Editor</role>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<permissions>
<copyright-year>2019</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>Mojtaba Vaismoradi</copyright-holder>
<license ns0:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
<license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" ns0:type="simple">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<related-object document-id="10.1371/journal.pone.0223150" document-id-type="doi" document-type="article" id="rel-obj003" link-type="peer-reviewed-article" />
<custom-meta-group>
<custom-meta>
<meta-name>Submission Version</meta-name>
<meta-value>1</meta-value>
</custom-meta>
</custom-meta-group>
</front-stub>
<body>
<p>
<named-content content-type="letter-date">27 Aug 2019</named-content>
</p>
<p>PONE-D-19-15237R1</p>
<p>Discharge care quality in hospitalised elderly patients: Extended validation of the Discharge Care Experiences Survey</p>
<p>PLOS ONE</p>
<p>Dear Ms Boge,</p>
<p>Thank you for submitting your manuscript to PLOS ONE. After careful consideration, we feel that it has merit but does not fully meet PLOS ONE&#8217;s publication criteria as it currently stands. Therefore, we invite you to submit a revised version of the manuscript that addresses the points raised during the review process.</p>
<p>We would appreciate receiving your revised manuscript by Oct 11 2019 11:59PM. When you are ready to submit your revision, log on to <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://www.editorialmanager.com/pone/" ns0:type="simple">https://www.editorialmanager.com/pone/</ext-link> and select the 'Submissions Needing Revision' folder to locate your manuscript file.</p>
<p>If you would like to make changes to your financial disclosure, please include your updated statement in your cover letter.</p>
<p>To enhance the reproducibility of your results, we recommend that if applicable you deposit your laboratory protocols in protocols.io, where a protocol can be assigned its own identifier (DOI) such that it can be cited independently in the future. For instructions see: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://journals.plos.org/plosone/s/submission-guidelines#loc-laboratory-protocols" ns0:type="simple">http://journals.plos.org/plosone/s/submission-guidelines#loc-laboratory-protocols</ext-link></p>
<p>Please include the following items when submitting your revised manuscript:</p>
<p><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>A rebuttal letter that responds to each point raised by the academic editor and reviewer(s). This letter should be uploaded as separate file and labeled 'Response to Reviewers'.</p></list-item><list-item><p>A marked-up copy of your manuscript that highlights changes made to the original version. This file should be uploaded as separate file and labeled 'Revised Manuscript with Track Changes'.</p></list-item><list-item><p>An unmarked version of your revised paper without tracked changes. This file should be uploaded as separate file and labeled 'Manuscript'.</p></list-item></list></p>
<p>Please note while forming your response, if your article is accepted, you may have the opportunity to make the peer review history publicly available. The record will include editor decision letters (with reviews) and your responses to reviewer comments. If eligible, we will contact you to opt in or out.</p>
<p>We look forward to receiving your revised manuscript.</p>
<p>Kind regards,</p>
<p>Prof, Mojtaba Vaismoradi, PhD, MScN, BScN</p>
<p>Academic Editor</p>
<p>PLOS ONE</p>
<p>[Note: HTML markup is below. Please do not edit.]</p>
<p>Reviewers' comments:</p>
<p>Reviewer #1: All my comments from the first round of the review were adequatly adressed. There are only 4 minor issues left, that should be worked out prior to publication.</p>
<p>Line 81: missing "to", should be ...for their discharge to home</p>
<p>Line 123: should be ....medicine ward specialised in gastroenterology</p>
<p>Line 321: should be "In a systematic review Beattie and colleagues identified 11 instruments measuring patient experience of healthcare quality [26]." or "Beattie and colleagues identified 11 instruments of measuring patient</p>
<p>experience of healthcare quality in a systematic review [26]."</p>
<p>And - sorry for grouching, but - the DOI for Reference 43 leads me to the wrong publication, I cannot retrieve the right publication with the given DOI 10.12788/jhm.3037 via <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://doi.org" ns0:type="simple">doi.org</ext-link>. In the citation 43 as given I can only find another publication, were the title and one authors name match.</p>
<p>The DOI 10.12788/jhm.3037 given in the citation 43 leads to the following publication:</p>
<p>Brotman DJ, Siddiqui Z, Siddiqui Z, Durkin N. Does Patient Experience Predict 30-Day Readmission? A Patient-Level Analysis of HCAHPS Data. Journal of Hospital Medicine. 2018;13. doi:10.12788/jhm.3037</p>
<p>The publication you cited as No. 43 has another DOI, when I look for the title only:</p>
<p>Siddiqui OI. Methods for Computing Missing Item Response in Psychometric Scale Construction. Current Research in Biostatistics. 2015;5: 1&#8211;6. doi:10.3844/amjbsp.2015.1.6</p>
<p>Reviewer #2: One additional suggestion to improve the manuscript content: line 147, add brief details of the search strategy.</p>
<p>Line 283: wording should be &#8220;discharge&#8221;</p>
<p>[NOTE: If reviewer comments were submitted as an attachment file, they will be attached to this email and accessible via the submission site. Please log into your account, locate the manuscript record, and check for the action link "View Attachments". If this link does not appear, there are no attachment files to be viewed.]</p>
<p>While revising your submission, please upload your figure files to the Preflight Analysis and Conversion Engine (PACE) digital diagnostic tool, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://pacev2.apexcovantage.com/" ns0:type="simple">https://pacev2.apexcovantage.com/</ext-link>. PACE helps ensure that figures meet PLOS requirements. To use PACE, you must first register as a user. Registration is free. Then, login and navigate to the UPLOAD tab, where you will find detailed instructions on how to use the tool. If you encounter any issues or have any questions when using PACE, please email us at <email ns0:type="simple">figures@plos.org</email>. Please note that Supporting Information files do not need this step.</p>
</body>
</sub-article>
