<sub-article xmlns:ns0="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="aggregated-review-documents" id="pone.0221187.r001" specific-use="decision-letter">
<front-stub>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0221187.r001</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title>Decision Letter 0</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Robinson</surname>
<given-names>D. Ashley</given-names>
</name>
<role>Academic Editor</role>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<permissions>
<copyright-year>2019</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>D. Ashley Robinson</copyright-holder>
<license ns0:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
<license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" ns0:type="simple">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<related-object document-id="10.1371/journal.pone.0221187" document-id-type="doi" document-type="article" id="rel-obj001" link-type="peer-reviewed-article" />
<custom-meta-group>
<custom-meta>
<meta-name>Submission Version</meta-name>
<meta-value>0</meta-value>
</custom-meta>
</custom-meta-group>
</front-stub>
<body>
<p>
<named-content content-type="letter-date">3 Jul 2019</named-content>
</p>
<p>PONE-D-19-14966</p>
<p>Application of whole genome sequencing in low diversity hospital extended-spectrum beta-lactamases producing Klebsiella pneumoniae population</p>
<p>PLOS ONE</p>
<p>Dear Dr. Lengerova,</p>
<p>Thank you for submitting your manuscript to PLOS ONE. After careful consideration, we feel that it has merit but does not fully meet PLOS ONE&#8217;s publication criteria as it currently stands. Therefore, we invite you to submit a revised version of the manuscript that carefully addresses each of the points raised during the review process.</p>
<p>We would appreciate receiving your revised manuscript by Aug 17 2019 11:59PM. When you are ready to submit your revision, log on to <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://www.editorialmanager.com/pone/" ns0:type="simple">https://www.editorialmanager.com/pone/</ext-link> and select the 'Submissions Needing Revision' folder to locate your manuscript file.</p>
<p>If you would like to make changes to your financial disclosure, please include your updated statement in your cover letter.</p>
<p>To enhance the reproducibility of your results, we recommend that if applicable you deposit your laboratory protocols in protocols.io, where a protocol can be assigned its own identifier (DOI) such that it can be cited independently in the future. For instructions see: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://journals.plos.org/plosone/s/submission-guidelines#loc-laboratory-protocols" ns0:type="simple">http://journals.plos.org/plosone/s/submission-guidelines#loc-laboratory-protocols</ext-link></p>
<p>Please include the following items when submitting your revised manuscript:</p>
<p><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>A rebuttal letter that responds to each point raised by the academic editor and reviewer(s). This letter should be uploaded as separate file and labeled 'Response to Reviewers'.</p></list-item><list-item><p>A marked-up copy of your manuscript that highlights changes made to the original version. This file should be uploaded as separate file and labeled 'Revised Manuscript with Track Changes'.</p></list-item><list-item><p>An unmarked version of your revised paper without tracked changes. This file should be uploaded as separate file and labeled 'Manuscript'.</p></list-item></list></p>
<p>Please note while forming your response, if your article is accepted, you may have the opportunity to make the peer review history publicly available. The record will include editor decision letters (with reviews) and your responses to reviewer comments. If eligible, we will contact you to opt in or out.</p>
<p>We look forward to receiving your revised manuscript.</p>
<p>Kind regards,</p>
<p>D. Ashley Robinson, Ph.D.</p>
<p>Academic Editor</p>
<p>PLOS ONE</p>
<p><bold>Journal Requirements:</bold></p>
<p>1. When submitting your revision, we need you to address these additional requirements.</p>
<p>Please ensure that your manuscript meets PLOS ONE's style requirements, including those for file naming. The PLOS ONE style templates can be found at</p>
<p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://www.journals.plos.org/plosone/s/file?id=wjVg/PLOSOne_formatting_sample_main_body.pdf" ns0:type="simple">http://www.journals.plos.org/plosone/s/file?id=wjVg/PLOSOne_formatting_sample_main_body.pdf</ext-link> and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://www.journals.plos.org/plosone/s/file?id=ba62/PLOSOne_formatting_sample_title_authors_affiliations.pdf" ns0:type="simple">http://www.journals.plos.org/plosone/s/file?id=ba62/PLOSOne_formatting_sample_title_authors_affiliations.pdf</ext-link></p>
<p>2. Our editorial staff has assessed your submission, and we have concerns about the grammar, usage, and overall readability of the manuscript. &#160;We therefore request that you revise the text to fix the grammatical errors and improve the overall readability of the text before we send it for review. We suggest you have a fluent, preferably native, English-language speaker thoroughly copyedit your manuscript for language usage, spelling, and grammar.</p>
<p>If you do not know anyone who can do this, you may wish to consider employing a professional scientific editing service. &#160;</p>
<p>Whilst you may use any professional scientific editing service of your choice, PLOS has partnered with both American Journal Experts (AJE) and Editage to provide discounted services to PLOS authors. Both organizations have experience helping authors meet PLOS guidelines and can provide language editing, translation, manuscript formatting, and figure formatting to ensure your manuscript meets our submission guidelines. To take advantage of our partnership with AJE, visit the AJE website (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://learn.aje.com/plos/" ns0:type="simple">http://learn.aje.com/plos/</ext-link>) and enter referral code PLOS15 for a 15% discount off AJE services. To take advantage of our partnership with Editage, visit the Editage website (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://www.editage.com" ns0:type="simple">www.editage.com</ext-link>) and enter referral code PLOSEDIT for a 15% discount off Editage services. If the PLOS editorial team finds any language issues in text that either AJE or Editage has edited, the service provider will re-edit the text for free.</p>
<p>Upon resubmission, please provide the following:</p>
<p>&#160;&#160; &#160;&#8226;&#160;&#160; &#160;The name of the colleague or the details of the professional service that edited your manuscript</p>
<p>&#160;&#160; &#160;&#8226;&#160;&#160; &#160;A copy of your manuscript showing your changes by either highlighting them or using track changes (uploaded as a *supporting information* file)</p>
<p>&#160;&#160; &#160;&#8226;&#160;&#160; &#160;A clean copy of the edited manuscript (uploaded as the new *manuscript* file)</p>
<p>Please note that PLOS ONE does not copyedit accepted manuscripts and that one of our criteria for publication is that articles must be presented in an intelligible fashion and written in clear, correct, and unambiguous English (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://www.plosone.org/static/publication#language" ns0:type="simple">http://www.plosone.org/static/publication#language</ext-link>). If the language is not sufficiently improved, we may have no choice but to reject the manuscript without review.</p>
<p><bold>Comments to the Author</bold></p>
<p>1. Is the manuscript technically sound, and do the data support the conclusions?</p>
<p>The manuscript must describe a technically sound piece of scientific research with data that supports the conclusions. Experiments must have been conducted rigorously, with appropriate controls, replication, and sample sizes. The conclusions must be drawn appropriately based on the data presented. </p>
<p>Reviewer #1: Yes</p>
<p>Reviewer #2: Yes</p>
<p>**********</p>
<p>2. Has the statistical analysis been performed appropriately and rigorously? </p>
<p>Reviewer #1: Yes</p>
<p>Reviewer #2: N/A</p>
<p>**********</p>
<p>3. Have the authors made all data underlying the findings in their manuscript fully available?</p>
<p>The <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://www.plosone.org/static/policies.action#sharing" ns0:type="simple">PLOS Data policy</ext-link> requires authors to make all data underlying the findings described in their manuscript fully available without restriction, with rare exception (please refer to the Data Availability Statement in the manuscript PDF file). The data should be provided as part of the manuscript or its supporting information, or deposited to a public repository. For example, in addition to summary statistics, the data points behind means, medians and variance measures should be available. If there are restrictions on publicly sharing data&#8212;e.g. participant privacy or use of data from a third party&#8212;those must be specified.</p>
<p>Reviewer #1: No</p>
<p>Reviewer #2: No</p>
<p>**********</p>
<p>4. Is the manuscript presented in an intelligible fashion and written in standard English?</p>
<p>PLOS ONE does not copyedit accepted manuscripts, so the language in submitted articles must be clear, correct, and unambiguous. Any typographical or grammatical errors should be corrected at revision, so please note any specific errors here.</p>
<p>Reviewer #1: Yes</p>
<p>Reviewer #2: Yes</p>
<p>**********</p>
<p>5. Review Comments to the Author</p>
<p>Please use the space provided to explain your answers to the questions above. You may also include additional comments for the author, including concerns about dual publication, research ethics, or publication ethics. (Please upload your review as an attachment if it exceeds 20,000 characters)</p>
<p>Reviewer #1: This manuscript is particularly well written and describes an interesting and well-designed study. My comments are quite minor.</p>
<p>&#8226; Not sure where the sequence data/sequence reads are deposited</p>
<p>&#8226; The figure legends are short and uninformative. I know they should not repeat was in the text, but I was having trouble understanding exactly how each figure was put together. Perhaps just a little more information is necessary. One thing that was specifically unclear was whether the dendrogram in Fig 3 was on the basis of allele number similarity, or overall sequence similarity. Similarly, it appears from the Methods that allele numbers were used to create the minimum spanning trees in Fig 4 &#8211; which seems odd given that the Results implies it is from actual sequence similarity. Can this be clarified?</p>
<p>&#8226; Can the authors give some thought to shortening the Discussion? The main points conclusions could possibly be stated more clearly and succinctly e.g. &#8220;miniMLST is a cost effective means of ruling out epidemiological linkage, but only complete genome analysis can provide strong evidence in favour of epidemiological linkage&#8221;.</p>
<p>&#8226; Line 61: should be &#8220;bacterial&#8221;</p>
<p>Reviewer #2: Title: Application of whole genome sequencing in low diversity hospital extended-spectrum beta-lactamases producing Klebsiella pneumoniae population</p>
<p>This manuscript presents a well written description of the application of mini-MLST in the surveillance of ESBL-KPN within a single hospital in the Czech Republic. Additionally, the authors discuss the limitations of mini-MLST in resolving closely related isolates, in particular outbreak strains, and the need for WGS in these situations. The authors then show the potential application of WGS in a limited sample set.</p>
<p>Minor comments:</p>
<p>Line 52 &#8211; the word &#8220;solution&#8221; should likely be &#8220;intervention&#8221;.</p>
<p>Line 237-238 &#8211; The authors indicate they have generated a new automatic algorithm that acts as a conversion key. Is it possible to utilize this conversion key with the existing MLST schema to generate a conversion list of MSLT to melT groups? This would allow for direct comparison of the large existing studies that use MLST with the use of melT groups and will also clarify the resolution of melT groups. I think this would help clarify the potential role of melT groups among a growing list of molecular epidemiology markers of bacterial diversity (e.g. PFGE, MLST, mini-MLST, cgMLST, WGS).</p>
<p>Line 63-65 &#8211; The authors define CgMLST and SNV analyses, but the descriptions are confusing. In particular, the authors indicate SNV analysis provides a higher resolution power as compared to cgMLST, but then use SNV as a precursor to CgMLST. It would be good to clarify that both are based upon the detection of variants, but while CgMLST is looking at variants in a specific pre-determined set of genes, true whole genome alignment allows for assessment of variants in all regions that are not masked.</p>
<p>Table 1.- Can the authors please include the percentage of each subgrouping with the count? This will help the reader understand the proportion of isolates, especially within the source section of the table.</p>
<p>Lines 95-97 &#8211; the methods listed for use with mini-MLST differ from the methods used in the previous reference within Diagnostic Microbiology and Infectious Disease (citation 14). Can the authors comment on why the methods were changed from the UltraClean Microbial DNA Isolation Kit to the Chelex based extraction?</p>
<p>Line 122 &#8211; Can the authors indicate how they defined ambiguous positions? Was this based upon a percent threshold for variant detection?</p>
<p>Line 235 &#8211; please update the number of ST types as it now appears there are 4,054 different MSLT profiles within the Pasteur MLST database.</p>
<p>Line 249 &#8211; Please update the sentence to say &#8220;WGS has become a powerful method&#8221;</p>
<p>Major comments:</p>
<p>Title &#8211; As this manuscript focuses heavily on mini-MLST, please add mini-MLST to the title.</p>
<p>Lines 35-37, 57-59, 318-323 &#8211; The authors describe the potential for mini-MLST in real-time epidemiology, but point out the need for mini-MLST to be combined with more discriminatory analyses in outbreak/low genetic diversity settings. Can the authors describe in more detail how this progressive application of mini-MLST and WGS would work in active surveillance? In specific, it would be good to identify how mini-MLST could be used to select isolates for WGS and how mini-MLST would be able to identify outbreaks to focus on.</p>
<p>Lines 146-156 &#8211; Do the authors intend to submit the WGS sequencing data to a repository such as the European Nucleotide Archive? If so, can the authors include the project ID within the manuscript?</p>
<p>Line 215-217 &#8211; What was the order of collection for the colonization and infection strains? Were colonization strains always collected before outbreak strains? This may be good information to include in a supplemental table. Additionally, can the authors discuss the number of remaining positions within the genome that are accounted for in calculating the number of SNVs between each pair of isolates?</p>
<p>Line 271-275 &#8211; Can the authors make it more clear if this discussion is referring to the 14 isolates described on lines 146-147, the 24 isolates described from lines 146-150, or does this refer to the entire set of 46 isolates (line 155)? If this is either the 14 or 24 isolates, this represents a small subset of the overall 922 isolates. Can the authors discuss the possibility that this is not a broad enough subsample of the total set of ESBL-KPN isolates to truly evaluate the role of WGS in a low diversity population?</p>
<p>Line 301-310 &#8211; I am confused about the application of the premise that &#8220;the colonization strain is the cause of the subsequent infection in most cases&#8221; to the idea of evaluating a hospital outbreak. In particular, hospital outbreaks are characterized by person-to-person transmission, or are mediated by fomites in the environment. Can the authors describe the potential for misclassification of colonizing and infecting strains if the infecting strain was acquired within the hospital environment?</p>
<p>In a time where there is more focus on acquired resistance genes, and in particular how these acquired genes can change the required antimicrobial treatment choices, how can a technique like mini-MLST be used to help target hospital infection control in the case of an outbreak?</p>
<p>Figure 2 &#8211; This figure is very data dense, but does not display well on a single printed page. Additionally, as the discussion of virulence factors is limited within the manuscript, it may be good to reformat this figure or move it to the supplemental files.</p>
<p>**********</p>
<p>6. PLOS authors have the option to publish the peer review history of their article (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://journals.plos.org/plosone/s/editorial-and-peer-review-process#loc-peer-review-history" ns0:type="simple">what does this mean?</ext-link>). If published, this will include your full peer review and any attached files.</p>
<p>If you choose &#8220;no&#8221;, your identity will remain anonymous but your review may still be made public.</p>
<p><bold>Do you want your identity to be public for this peer review?</bold> For information about this choice, including consent withdrawal, please see our <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://www.plos.org/privacy-policy" ns0:type="simple">Privacy Policy</ext-link>.</p>
<p>Reviewer #1: No</p>
<p>Reviewer #2: No</p>
<p>[NOTE: If reviewer comments were submitted as an attachment file, they will be attached to this email and accessible via the submission site. Please log into your account, locate the manuscript record, and check for the action link "View Attachments". If this link does not appear, there are no attachment files to be viewed.]</p>
<p>While revising your submission, please upload your figure files to the Preflight Analysis and Conversion Engine (PACE) digital diagnostic tool, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://pacev2.apexcovantage.com/" ns0:type="simple">https://pacev2.apexcovantage.com/</ext-link>. PACE helps ensure that figures meet PLOS requirements. To use PACE, you must first register as a user. Registration is free. Then, login and navigate to the UPLOAD tab, where you will find detailed instructions on how to use the tool. If you encounter any issues or have any questions when using PACE, please email us at <email ns0:type="simple">figures@plos.org</email>. Please note that Supporting Information files do not need this step.</p>
</body>
</sub-article>
