<sub-article xmlns:ns0="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="aggregated-review-documents" id="pbio.3000364.r002" specific-use="decision-letter">
<front-stub>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pbio.3000364.r002</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title>Decision Letter 1</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Richardson</surname>
<given-names>Lauren A</given-names>
</name>
<role>Senior Editor</role>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<permissions>
<copyright-year>2019</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>Lauren A Richardson</copyright-holder>
<license ns0:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
<license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" ns0:type="simple">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<related-object document-id="10.1371/journal.pbio.3000364" document-id-type="doi" document-type="article" id="rel-obj002" link-type="peer-reviewed-article" />
<custom-meta-group>
<custom-meta>
<meta-name>Submission Version</meta-name>
<meta-value>1</meta-value>
</custom-meta>
</custom-meta-group>
</front-stub>
<body>
<p>
<named-content content-type="letter-date">8 Jul 2019</named-content>
</p>
<p>Dear Dr Knoll,</p>
<p>Thank you very much for submitting your manuscript "Intestinal delta-6-desaturase activity determines host range for Toxoplasma sexual reproduction" for consideration as a Research Article by PLOS Biology. Your paper was evaluated by the PLOS Biology editors as well as by an Academic Editor with relevant expertise and by three independent reviewers. The reviewers appreciated the attention to an important topic. Based on the reviews, we will probably accept this manuscript for publication, providing that you will modify the manuscript according to the review recommendations.</p>
<p>We expect to receive your revised manuscript within two weeks. Your revisions should address the specific points made by each reviewer. In addition to the remaining revisions and before we will be able to formally accept your manuscript and consider it "in press", we also need to ensure that your article conforms to our guidelines, one of which is described below under DATA POLICY. A member of our team will be in touch shortly with a set of requests. As we can't proceed until these requirements are met, your swift response will help prevent delays to publication.</p>
<p>Upon acceptance of your article, your final files will be copyedited and typeset into the final PDF. While you will have an opportunity to review these files as proofs, PLOS will only permit corrections to spelling or significant scientific errors. Therefore, please take this final revision time to assess and make any remaining major changes to your manuscript.</p>
<p>Please note that you may have the opportunity to make the peer review history publicly available. The record will include editor decision letters (with reviews) and your responses to reviewer comments. If eligible, we will contact you to opt in or out.</p>
<p>Please note that an uncorrected proof of your manuscript will be published online ahead of the final version, unless you opted out when submitting your manuscript. If, for any reason, you do not want an earlier version of your manuscript published online, uncheck the box. Should you, your institution's press office or the journal office choose to press release your paper, you will automatically be opted out of early publication. We ask that you notify us as soon as possible if you or your institution is planning to press release the article.</p>
<p>To submit your revision, please go to <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://www.editorialmanager.com/pbiology/" ns0:type="simple">https://www.editorialmanager.com/pbiology/</ext-link> and log in as an Author. Click the link labelled 'Submissions Needing Revision' to find your submission record. Your revised submission must include a cover letter, a Response to Reviewers file that provides a detailed response to the reviewers' comments (if applicable), and a track-changes file indicating any changes that you have made to the manuscript. </p>
<p>Please do not hesitate to contact me should you have any questions.</p>
<p>Sincerely,</p>
<p>Di Jiang, PhD</p>
<p>Associate Editor</p>
<p>on behalf of</p>
<p>Lauren A Richardson, Ph.D, </p>
<p>Senior Editor</p>
<p>PLOS Biology</p>
<p>------------------------------------------------------------------------</p>
<p>DATA POLICY:</p>
<p>You may be aware of the PLOS Data Policy, which requires that all data be made available without restriction: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://journals.plos.org/plosbiology/s/data-availability" ns0:type="simple">http://journals.plos.org/plosbiology/s/data-availability</ext-link>. For more information, please also see this editorial: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.1001797" ns0:type="simple">http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.1001797</ext-link></p>
<p>Note that we do not require all raw data. Rather, we ask that all individual quantitative observations that underlie the data summarized in the figures and results of your paper be made available in one of the following forms:</p>
<p>1) Supplementary files (e.g., excel). Please ensure that all data files are uploaded as 'Supporting Information' and are invariably referred to (in the manuscript, figure legends, and the Description field when uploading your files) using the following format verbatim: S1 Data, S2 Data, etc. Multiple panels of a single or even several figures can be included as multiple sheets in one excel file that is saved using exactly the following convention: S1_Data.xlsx (using an underscore).</p>
<p>2) Deposition in a publicly available repository. Please also provide the accession code or a reviewer link so that we may view your data before publication. </p>
<p>Regardless of the method selected, please ensure that you provide the individual numerical values that underlie the summary data displayed in the following figure panels: Figures 2ab, 3h, 5a, 6ab, S1, as they are essential for readers to assess your analysis and to reproduce it. Please also ensure that figure legends in your manuscript include information on where the underlying data can be found.</p>
<p>Please ensure that your Data Statement in the submission system accurately describes where your data can be found.</p>
<p>------------------------------------------------------------------------</p>
<p>Reviewer remarks:</p>
<p>Reviewer #1: Summary</p>
<p>The work described in this manuscript is truly transformative as it not only identifies the trigger of the Toxoplasma sexual cycle and why this only occurs in cats, it continues to fulfil Koch&#8217;s postulates by overcoming this species barrier by demonstrating the completion of the cycle in mice (and largely in vitro as well) by mimicking the cat environment. The work is also transformative in its approach as this is the first application of cat intestinal organoids to Toxoplasma. Besides the major biological breakthrough, these insights are relevant toward developing sexual recombination experiments in Toxoplasma (a tool that has been cumbersome due to its poor efficiency and the need of cats) as well as toward developing control strategies of cats shedding oocysts, which is a responsible for a large portion of human infections with Toxoplasma. In addition, the work is timely in light of the recent sudden and politically motivated suspension of the use of cats at the USDA, which supplied the majority of the Toxoplasma field with Toxoplasma oocysts. This work is therefore relevant for a very wide audience of microbiologists, infectious disease specialists, clinicians, epidemiologists and basic parasitology researchers. By fulfilling Koch&#8217;s postulates the paper per definition is very rigorous. In summary, a through breakthrough manuscript well described and executed. Only one minor comment as described below.</p>
<p>Specific comments.</p>
<p>Supplementary information; No Fig S2, but a fig 6. This is likely a mix up. Legend says &#8220;strained&#8221; instead of &#8220;stained&#8221; for DBA staining.</p>
<p>P7 line 13: in the sentence is referred to sero conversion, however, no data supporting this statement are shown in neither Fig 6e nor S2.</p>
<p>Reviewer #2 (Felix Yarovinsky, signed review): In this groundbreaking work the authors succeeded in answering a major biological question in the field of parasite biology.  It was a mystery why the sexual cycle of Toxoplasma gondii is limited to felines, while the asexual life cycle can happen in any warm-blooded mammal. Using an elegant in vitro system based on the intestinal organoids, the authors identified that linoleic acid is essential for the expression of markers associated with the sexual cycle of the parasite.  The authors provide the detailed biochemical explanation for this requirement.  It appears that cats are deficient in delta-6-desaturase, the rate&#8208;limiting step for the conversion of linoleic acid to arachidonic acid. As a result, linoleic acid is the dominant fatty acid in cat serum. This explains why the felines have an increased level of linoleic acid.  </p>
<p>The authors next validated in vitro observation with mice that were fed with linoleic acid and delta-6-desaturase inhibitor.  This treatment results in the full sexual cycle of the parasite in the murine intestine.  This is a truly remarkable discovery in biology, and while there might be minor technical gaps in the work, I believe an immediate publication would benefit the scientific community. This is a highly significant work that not only teach us new biology, but also has a major clinical significance since it provides a novel biochemical tool to deal with toxoplasmosis in cats that may eventually lead to the elimination of this parasite in cats.  </p>
<p>I only have two minor comments </p>
<p>1. In the following statement &#8216;After 5 days of infection, we found that the addition of linoleic acid but not oleic acid caused approximately 35% of the T. gondii to express both merozoite stage markers (Fig. 2a)&#8217; the authors forgot to acknowledge the data shown in Fig 1d-1g as an additional experimental support in the above-mentioned statement. </p>
<p>Figure 2, Y- axis:  the labeling needs to be more specific, as &#8216;%GRA11B and BRP1 positive&#8217; is confusing.</p>
<p>Reviewer #3: Although it has been known for decades that felids are the definitive host for sexual replication of the intracellular protozoan parasite Toxoplasma gondii, the molecular underpinnings of this remarkable host specificity for parasite mating has remained an important unresolved mystery. The current work compellingly establishes that an excess linoleic acid drives sexual differentiation in culture and in mice, thus establishing for the first time in vitro and alternative in vivo models for T. gondii sexual development. The work represents a key breakthrough that will permit further dissection of sexual development, accelerate classical genetic linkage mapping of important traits, and reduce the dependence on using cats as an experimental model, among other avenues. The authors provide thorough qualitative and quantitative data that is appropriately interpreted and supportive of the conclusions. The following minor considerations should be addressed.</p>
<p>Line 21. Delete on of the &#8220;withs&#8221;</p>
<p>Page 8, line 5-7. This statement should be softened from &#8220;likely&#8221; given that no data is presented to support it. It is suggested that the authors rephrase it to e.g., It is possible that the multiple&#8230;</p>
</body>
</sub-article>
