<sub-article xmlns:ns0="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="aggregated-review-documents" id="pone.0221826.r001" specific-use="decision-letter">
<front-stub>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0221826.r001</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title>Decision Letter 0</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>Aimin</given-names>
</name>
<role>Academic Editor</role>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<permissions>
<copyright-year>2019</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>Aimin Zhang</copyright-holder>
<license ns0:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
<license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" ns0:type="simple">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<related-object document-id="10.1371/journal.pone.0221826" document-id-type="doi" document-type="article" id="rel-obj001" link-type="peer-reviewed-article" />
<custom-meta-group>
<custom-meta>
<meta-name>Submission Version</meta-name>
<meta-value>0</meta-value>
</custom-meta>
</custom-meta-group>
</front-stub>
<body>
<p>
<named-content content-type="letter-date">26 Jun 2019</named-content>
</p>
<p>PONE-D-19-14666</p>
<p>Genome wide genetic dissection of wheat quality and yield related traits and their relationship with grain shape and size traits in an elite &#215; non-adapted bread wheat cross</p>
<p>PLOS ONE</p>
<p>Dear Dr. Kumar,</p>
<p>Thank you for submitting your manuscript to PLOS ONE. After careful consideration, we feel that it has merit but does not fully meet PLOS ONE&#8217;s publication criteria as it currently stands. Therefore, we invite you to submit a revised version of the manuscript that addresses the points raised during the review process.</p>
<p>We would appreciate receiving your revised manuscript by Aug 10 2019 11:59PM. When you are ready to submit your revision, log on to <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://www.editorialmanager.com/pone/" ns0:type="simple">https://www.editorialmanager.com/pone/</ext-link> and select the 'Submissions Needing Revision' folder to locate your manuscript file.</p>
<p>If you would like to make changes to your financial disclosure, please include your updated statement in your cover letter.</p>
<p>To enhance the reproducibility of your results, we recommend that if applicable you deposit your laboratory protocols in protocols.io, where a protocol can be assigned its own identifier (DOI) such that it can be cited independently in the future. For instructions see: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://journals.plos.org/plosone/s/submission-guidelines#loc-laboratory-protocols" ns0:type="simple">http://journals.plos.org/plosone/s/submission-guidelines#loc-laboratory-protocols</ext-link></p>
<p>Please include the following items when submitting your revised manuscript:</p>
<p><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>A rebuttal letter that responds to each point raised by the academic editor and reviewer(s). This letter should be uploaded as separate file and labeled 'Response to Reviewers'.</p></list-item><list-item><p>A marked-up copy of your manuscript that highlights changes made to the original version. This file should be uploaded as separate file and labeled 'Revised Manuscript with Track Changes'.</p></list-item><list-item><p>An unmarked version of your revised paper without tracked changes. This file should be uploaded as separate file and labeled 'Manuscript'.</p></list-item></list></p>
<p>Please note while forming your response, if your article is accepted, you may have the opportunity to make the peer review history publicly available. The record will include editor decision letters (with reviews) and your responses to reviewer comments. If eligible, we will contact you to opt in or out.</p>
<p>We look forward to receiving your revised manuscript.</p>
<p>Kind regards,</p>
<p>Aimin Zhang, Ph.D.</p>
<p>Academic Editor</p>
<p>PLOS ONE</p>
<p>Journal Requirements:</p>
<p>1. When submitting your revision, we need you to address these additional requirements.</p>
<p>Please ensure that your manuscript meets PLOS ONE's style requirements, including those for file naming. The PLOS ONE style templates can be found at</p>
<p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://www.journals.plos.org/plosone/s/file?id=wjVg/PLOSOne_formatting_sample_main_body.pdf" ns0:type="simple">http://www.journals.plos.org/plosone/s/file?id=wjVg/PLOSOne_formatting_sample_main_body.pdf</ext-link> and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://www.journals.plos.org/plosone/s/file?id=ba62/PLOSOne_formatting_sample_title_authors_affiliations.pdf" ns0:type="simple">http://www.journals.plos.org/plosone/s/file?id=ba62/PLOSOne_formatting_sample_title_authors_affiliations.pdf</ext-link></p>
<p>2. We note that you have included the phrase &#8220;data not shown&#8221; in your manuscript. Unfortunately, this does not meet our data sharing requirements. PLOS does not permit references to inaccessible data. We require that authors provide all relevant data within the paper, Supporting Information files, or in an acceptable, public repository. Please add a citation to support this phrase or upload the data that corresponds with these findings to a stable repository (such as Figshare or Dryad) and provide and URLs, DOIs, or accession numbers that may be used to access these data. Or, if the data are not a core part of the research being presented in your study, we ask that you remove the phrase that refers to these data.</p>
<p>[Note: HTML markup is below. Please do not edit.]</p>
<p>Reviewers' comments:</p>
<p>Reviewer's Responses to Questions</p>
<p><bold>Comments to the Author</bold></p>
<p>1. Is the manuscript technically sound, and do the data support the conclusions?</p>
<p>The manuscript must describe a technically sound piece of scientific research with data that supports the conclusions. Experiments must have been conducted rigorously, with appropriate controls, replication, and sample sizes. The conclusions must be drawn appropriately based on the data presented. </p>
<p>Reviewer #1: Yes</p>
<p>Reviewer #2: Yes</p>
<p>**********</p>
<p>2. Has the statistical analysis been performed appropriately and rigorously? </p>
<p>Reviewer #1: Yes</p>
<p>Reviewer #2: Yes</p>
<p>**********</p>
<p>3. Have the authors made all data underlying the findings in their manuscript fully available?</p>
<p>The <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://www.plosone.org/static/policies.action#sharing" ns0:type="simple">PLOS Data policy</ext-link> requires authors to make all data underlying the findings described in their manuscript fully available without restriction, with rare exception (please refer to the Data Availability Statement in the manuscript PDF file). The data should be provided as part of the manuscript or its supporting information, or deposited to a public repository. For example, in addition to summary statistics, the data points behind means, medians and variance measures should be available. If there are restrictions on publicly sharing data&#8212;e.g. participant privacy or use of data from a third party&#8212;those must be specified.</p>
<p>Reviewer #1: Yes</p>
<p>Reviewer #2: Yes</p>
<p>**********</p>
<p>4. Is the manuscript presented in an intelligible fashion and written in standard English?</p>
<p>PLOS ONE does not copyedit accepted manuscripts, so the language in submitted articles must be clear, correct, and unambiguous. Any typographical or grammatical errors should be corrected at revision, so please note any specific errors here.</p>
<p>Reviewer #1: Yes</p>
<p>Reviewer #2: Yes</p>
<p>**********</p>
<p>5. Review Comments to the Author</p>
<p>Please use the space provided to explain your answers to the questions above. You may also include additional comments for the author, including concerns about dual publication, research ethics, or publication ethics. (Please upload your review as an attachment if it exceeds 20,000 characters)</p>
<p>Reviewer #1: The following expresses my opinion about the merits of the study:</p>
<p>1) The paper provides useful information for breeders of hard red spring wheat and for the wider wheat community, particularly since the paper addresses the association of wheat quality and yield traits with grain shape and size traits, a poorly studied area.</p>
<p>2) The use of a high-density map for the mapping procedures should enable high efficiency application of MAS in future breeding programmes based upon this germplasm or upon these general results.</p>
<p>3) The identification of novel alleles provided by the non-adapted line, especially (i) alleles for improved GPC with no detrimental effects on yield or other traits, and (ii) alleles influencing grain hardness, together potentially provide new opportunities for achieving genetic progress in these traits.</p>
<p>4) Other valuable features of the paper are: (i) the detailed analysis of epistasis, which provides additional evidence of the importance of taking this into account during selection; (ii) the evidence presented that selection for grain area during breeding might also provide dividends; and (iii) the extensive comparison between the QTLs mapped here and those published previously, which details which of the QTLs identifies here are truly novel.</p>
<p>A comment: the study would probably have been more valuable still if more than 160 RILs had been evaluated and, to boot, more site-year combinations had been included; nonetheless, I do not see these drawbacks as sufficient motive to hold up publication of the study as it stands.</p>
<p>Am I right in thinking that there is disagreement in the labelling of the parental phenotypic mean values between Table 1 and Fig. 1? I recommend checking this.</p>
<p>Grammatically the writing is generally clear, although it might be further improved by being looked over once more.</p>
<p>Based upon the above opinion, I feel the paper is well worthy of publication.</p>
<p>Reviewer #2: The manuscript has some new finding in the area (specified for hard red spring wheat) which can be useful in the breeding program.</p>
<p>It has dissected the genetics of wheat quality and yield traits and also identified novel QTL and markers closely associated with quality and yield. It shows data about the epistasis in the genetic control of quality and yield as well.</p>
<p>The manuscript is well written. My only concern is that only two replicates were used in this experiment. I think it should be more.</p>
<p>I think it is suitable for publication.</p>
<p>**********</p>
<p>6. PLOS authors have the option to publish the peer review history of their article (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://journals.plos.org/plosone/s/editorial-and-peer-review-process#loc-peer-review-history" ns0:type="simple">what does this mean?</ext-link>). If published, this will include your full peer review and any attached files.</p>
<p>If you choose &#8220;no&#8221;, your identity will remain anonymous but your review may still be made public.</p>
<p><bold>Do you want your identity to be public for this peer review?</bold> For information about this choice, including consent withdrawal, please see our <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://www.plos.org/privacy-policy" ns0:type="simple">Privacy Policy</ext-link>.</p>
<p>Reviewer #1: No</p>
<p>Reviewer #2: No</p>
<p>[NOTE: If reviewer comments were submitted as an attachment file, they will be attached to this email and accessible via the submission site. Please log into your account, locate the manuscript record, and check for the action link "View Attachments". If this link does not appear, there are no attachment files to be viewed.]</p>
<p>While revising your submission, please upload your figure files to the Preflight Analysis and Conversion Engine (PACE) digital diagnostic tool, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://pacev2.apexcovantage.com/" ns0:type="simple">https://pacev2.apexcovantage.com/</ext-link>. PACE helps ensure that figures meet PLOS requirements. To use PACE, you must first register as a user. Registration is free. Then, login and navigate to the UPLOAD tab, where you will find detailed instructions on how to use the tool. If you encounter any issues or have any questions when using PACE, please email us at <email ns0:type="simple">figures@plos.org</email>. Please note that Supporting Information files do not need this step.</p>
</body>
</sub-article>
