<sub-article article-type="author-comment" id="pone.0222787.r002">
<front-stub>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0222787.r002</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title>Author response to Decision Letter 0</article-title>
</title-group>
<related-object document-id="10.1371/journal.pone.0222787" document-id-type="doi" document-type="peer-reviewed-article" id="rel-obj002" link-type="rebutted-decision-letter" object-id="10.1371/journal.pone.0222787.r001" object-id-type="doi" object-type="decision-letter" />
<custom-meta-group>
<custom-meta>
<meta-name>Submission Version</meta-name>
<meta-value>1</meta-value>
</custom-meta>
</custom-meta-group>
</front-stub>
<body>
<p>
<named-content content-type="author-response-date">28 Aug 2019</named-content>
</p>
<p>Responses to reviewers</p>
<p>We thank the reviewers for the encouraging and constructive comments. In addition to the modifications below, the main text and the citation style were re-formatted to meet the journal&#8217;s standards.</p>
<p>Reviewer #1</p>
<p>&gt;Fig1: There could be a confusion in Part A between the spatial extent of vasculature and the</p>
<p>&gt; time variations in 1-3. It would be clearer if the time arrows were bigger. I didn&#8217;t understand</p>
<p>&gt; the usefulness of the second schematic in gray area.</p>
<p>Thanks to the Reviewer, we noticed that there was much room for improvement in the Figures. As pointed out, the arrows in the top panels indicated blood flow/vasomotion (over space), while that in the bottom panel indicated time. We removed the arrows from the panels 1-3, illustrating the vessel content, which seemed redundant. The broken rectangle in the top panel was also too big (vertically) and indeed confusing for the readers to understand the three panels. The text in the gray box was changed to clearly mention the purpose of inserting this scheme. This was to explain the difference between lag mapping and perfusion MRI using contrast agent. Figure legend was also modified for clarity.</p>
<p>&gt;Fig2: Putting a legend related to the colorlines in partB woud help.</p>
<p>&gt;Fig3: Part A. This was especially difficult to follow. The colorbars are missing as well as </p>
<p>&gt;the axis names. I would remove the resampling part and add graphs about instantaneous phase</p>
<p>&gt;differences times series and the corresponding averages. Part B. There is no colorbar to explain</p>
<p>&gt;the different line colors.</p>
<p>We modified the figures accordingly. Part A was changed to clearly indicate that the combination of a lag map and the corresponding time courses constitute a lag structure for each individual fMRI run (shaded rectangle). An example of instantaneous phase difference timeseries (after time-locked averaging) was inserted. Colorbar was added to the Fig 3B.</p>
<p>Citations are fixed, thank you.</p>
</body>
</sub-article>
