<sub-article xmlns:ns0="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="editor-report" id="pbio.3000364.r004" specific-use="decision-letter">
<front-stub>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pbio.3000364.r004</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title>Decision Letter 2</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Richardson</surname>
<given-names>Lauren A</given-names>
</name>
<role>Senior Editor</role>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<permissions>
<copyright-year>2019</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>Lauren A Richardson</copyright-holder>
<license ns0:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
<license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" ns0:type="simple">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<related-object document-id="10.1371/journal.pbio.3000364" document-id-type="doi" document-type="article" id="rel-obj004" link-type="peer-reviewed-article" />
<custom-meta-group>
<custom-meta>
<meta-name>Submission Version</meta-name>
<meta-value>2</meta-value>
</custom-meta>
</custom-meta-group>
</front-stub>
<body>
<p>
<named-content content-type="letter-date">17 Jul 2019</named-content>
</p>
<p>Dear Dr Knoll,</p>
<p>On behalf of my colleagues and the Academic Editor, Boris Striepen, I am pleased to inform you that we will be delighted to publish your Research Article in PLOS Biology. </p>
<p>The files will now enter our production system. You will receive a copyedited version of the manuscript, along with your figures for a final review. You will be given two business days to review and approve the copyedit. Then, within a week, you will receive a PDF proof of your typeset article. You will have two days to review the PDF and make any final corrections. If there is a chance that you'll be unavailable during the copy editing/proof review period, please provide us with contact details of one of the other authors whom you nominate to handle these stages on your behalf. This will ensure that any requested corrections reach the production department in time for publication.</p>
<p>Early Version</p>
<p>The version of your manuscript submitted at the copyedit stage will be posted online ahead of the final proof version, unless you have already opted out of the process. The date of the early version will be your article's publication date. The final article will be published to the same URL, and all versions of the paper will be accessible to readers.</p>
<p>PRESS </p>
<p>We frequently collaborate with press offices. If your institution or institutions have a press office, please notify them about your upcoming paper at this point, to enable them to help maximise its impact. If the press office is planning to promote your findings, we would be grateful if they could coordinate with <email ns0:type="simple">biologypress@plos.org</email>. If you have not yet opted out of the early version process, we ask that you notify us immediately of any press plans so that we may do so on your behalf.</p>
<p>We also ask that you take this opportunity to read our Embargo Policy regarding the discussion, promotion and media coverage of work that is yet to be published by PLOS. As your manuscript is not yet published, it is bound by the conditions of our Embargo Policy. Please be aware that this policy is in place both to ensure that any press coverage of your article is fully substantiated and to provide a direct link between such coverage and the published work. For full details of our Embargo Policy, please visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://www.plos.org/about/media-inquiries/embargo-policy/" ns0:type="simple">http://www.plos.org/about/media-inquiries/embargo-policy/</ext-link>.</p>
<p>Thank you again for submitting your manuscript to PLOS Biology and for your support of Open Access publishing. Please do not hesitate to contact me if I can provide any assistance during the production process.</p>
<p>Kind regards,</p>
<p>Harry Porter</p>
<p>Publication Assistant, </p>
<p>PLOS Biology</p>
<p>on behalf of</p>
<p>Lauren Richardson,</p>
<p>Senior Editor</p>
<p>PLOS Biology</p>
</body>
</sub-article>
