<sub-article xmlns:ns0="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="author-comment" id="pone.0220230.r003">
<front-stub>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0220230.r003</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title>Author response to Decision Letter 0</article-title>
</title-group>
<related-object document-id="10.1371/journal.pone.0220230" document-id-type="doi" document-type="peer-reviewed-article" id="rel-obj003" link-type="rebutted-decision-letter" object-id="10.1371/journal.pone.0220230.r002" object-id-type="doi" object-type="decision-letter" />
<custom-meta-group>
<custom-meta>
<meta-name>Submission Version</meta-name>
<meta-value>1</meta-value>
</custom-meta>
</custom-meta-group>
</front-stub>
<body>
<p>
<named-content content-type="author-response-date">9 Jul 2019</named-content>
</p>
<p>Reviewer #1: This revised version of the paper addresses all my previous points.</p>
<p>I do not have any further comment to do.</p>
<p>Authors&#8217; response: Thank you.</p>
<p>Reviewer #2: The article provides interesting information on the determinants of shingles vaccination uptake in a sample of UK elders, identified through the Clinical Practice Research Datalink (CPRD). As also the authors stated, is one of the few studies that have been conducted to assess the determinants of vaccine hesitancy specifically addressed at shingles vaccination. The methodology adopted is sound and well described in the manuscript.</p>
<p>I would recommend describing in the methods section the items used for assessing Perceived susceptibility, Perceived benefits, Perceived barriers, Practical barriers and Facilitators, Self-efficacy and Perceived control of disease, or alternatively use a footnote to Table 2, to help the reader understand the underlying elements of the HBM theoretical construct.</p>
<p>In the Discussion section, the authors state that &#8220;The study adds to evidence on the pivotal role of provider recommendations regarding vaccines in general and specifically getting the shingle vaccine&#8221; (lines 181-182). I would suggest also citing some research conducted on the acceptance of varicella vaccination in pediatric age, particularly in Italy, where the vaccination against varicella became mandatory in 2017 (e.g. Vezzosi L, Santagati G, Angelillo IF. Knowledge, attitudes, and behaviors of parents towards varicella and its vaccination. BMC Infect Dis. 2017 Feb 27;17(1):172. doi: 10.1186/s12879-017-2247-6; Rosso A, Massimi A, De Vito C, Adamo G, Baccolini V, Marzuillo C, Vacchio MR, Villari P. Knowledge and attitudes on pediatric vaccinations and intention to vaccinate in a sample of pregnant women from the City of Rome.Vaccine. 2019 Mar 28;37(14):1954-1963. doi: 10.1016/j.vaccine.2019.02.049; but also the German study Hagemann C, Streng A, Kraemer A, Liese JG. Heterogeneity in coverage for measles and varicella vaccination in toddlers - analysis of factors influencing parental acceptance. BMC Public Health. 2017 Sep 19;17(1):724. doi: 10.1186/s12889-017-4725-6.). All these studies identified the information received from healthcare providers as one of the determinants of vaccine acceptance for a disease which severity tends to be underestimated.</p>
<p>Authors&#8217; response:  Thank you for your suggestions. </p>
<p>We have incorporated a footnote to Table 2 to refer to the detailed table in Supporting Information (S1 Table) where items used for each individual construct are displayed.</p>
<p>This study was to assess the determinants of shingles vaccination as part of a national immunisation programme in the older population. Consequently, the authors have selected most relevant papers related to the study population and vaccine considered. We have carefully considered the research suggested however they refer to paediatric population/parental acceptance or pregnant women which were not the main population of interest in our research; thus, they were not added to the manuscript. The statement in the discussion section was revised as follows &#8220;The study adds to evidence on the pivotal role of provider recommendations regarding getting the shingle vaccine&#8221; as specific references related to the shingles vaccine were already included in the manuscript in the next sentence.</p>
<supplementary-material id="pone.0220230.s005" mimetype="application/vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.wordprocessingml.document" position="float" ns0:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0220230.s005" ns0:type="simple">
<label>Attachment</label>
<caption>
<p>Submitted filename: <named-content content-type="submitted-filename">R2R.docx</named-content></p>
</caption>
</supplementary-material>
</body>
</sub-article>
