<sub-article xmlns:ns0="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="editor-report" id="pgen.1008389.r004" specific-use="acceptance-letter">
<front-stub>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1008389.r004</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title>Acceptance letter</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Payseur</surname>
<given-names>Bret</given-names>
</name>
<role>Section Editor: Evolution</role>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Bai</surname>
<given-names>Lu</given-names>
</name>
<role>Guest Editor</role>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<permissions>
<copyright-year>2019</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>Payseur, Bai</copyright-holder>
<license ns0:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
<license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" ns0:type="simple">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<related-object document-id="10.1371/journal.pgen.1008389" document-id-type="doi" document-type="article" id="rel-obj004" link-type="peer-reviewed-article" />
</front-stub>
<body>
<p>
<named-content content-type="letter-date">10 Sep 2019</named-content>
</p>
<p>PGENETICS-D-19-00916R1 </p>
<p>Chromosome-wide co-fluctuation of stochastic gene expression in mammalian cells </p>
<p>Dear Dr Zhang, </p>
<p>We are pleased to inform you that your manuscript entitled "Chromosome-wide co-fluctuation of stochastic gene expression in mammalian cells" has been formally accepted for publication in PLOS Genetics!  Your manuscript is now with our production department and you will be notified of the publication date in due course.</p>
<p>The corresponding author will soon be receiving a typeset proof for review, to ensure errors have not been introduced during production. Please review the PDF proof of your manuscript carefully, as this is the last chance to correct any errors. Please note that major changes, or those which affect the scientific understanding of the work, will likely cause delays to the publication date of your manuscript. </p>
<p>Soon after your final files are uploaded, unless you have opted out or your manuscript is a front-matter piece, the early version of your manuscript will be published online. The date of the early version will be your article's publication date. The final article will be published to the same URL, and all versions of the paper will be accessible to readers.</p>
<p>Thank you again for supporting PLOS Genetics and open-access publishing. We are looking forward to publishing your work! </p>
<p>With kind regards,</p>
<p>Kaitlin Butler</p>
<p>PLOS Genetics</p>
<p>On behalf of:</p>
<p>The PLOS Genetics Team</p>
<p>Carlyle House, Carlyle Road, Cambridge CB4 3DN | United Kingdom</p>
<p><email ns0:type="simple">plosgenetics@plos.org</email> | +44 (0) 1223-442823</p>
<p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://plosgenetics.org" ns0:type="simple">plosgenetics.org</ext-link> | Twitter: @PLOSGenetics</p>
</body>
</sub-article>
