<sub-article xmlns:ns0="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="editor-report" id="pgen.1008386.r003" specific-use="decision-letter">
<front-stub>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1008386.r003</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title>Decision Letter 1</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Bomblies</surname>
<given-names>Kirsten</given-names>
</name>
<role>Section Editor: Evolution</role>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Didelot</surname>
<given-names>Xavier</given-names>
</name>
<role>Associate Editor</role>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<permissions>
<copyright-year>2019</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>Bomblies, Didelot</copyright-holder>
<license ns0:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
<license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" ns0:type="simple">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<related-object document-id="10.1371/journal.pgen.1008386" document-id-type="doi" document-type="article" id="rel-obj003" link-type="peer-reviewed-article" />
<custom-meta-group>
<custom-meta>
<meta-name>Submission Version</meta-name>
<meta-value>1</meta-value>
</custom-meta>
</custom-meta-group>
</front-stub>
<body>
<p>
<named-content content-type="letter-date">27 Aug 2019</named-content>
</p>
<p>Dear Dr Ho,</p>
<p>We are pleased to inform you that your manuscript entitled "In eubacteria, unlike eukaryotes, there is no evidence for selection favouring fail-safe 3&#8217; additional stop codons" has been editorially accepted for publication in PLOS Genetics. Congratulations!</p>
<p>Before your submission can be formally accepted and sent to production you will need to complete our formatting changes, which you will receive in a follow up email. Please be aware that it may take several days for you to receive this email; during this time no action is required by you. Please note: the accept date on your published article will reflect the date of this provisional accept, but your manuscript will not be scheduled for publication until the required changes have been made.</p>
<p>Once your paper is formally accepted, an uncorrected proof of your manuscript will be published online ahead of the final version, unless you&#8217;ve already opted out via the online submission form. If, for any reason, you do not want an earlier version of your manuscript published online or are unsure if you have already indicated as such, please let the journal staff know immediately at <email ns0:type="simple">plosgenetics@plos.org</email>.</p>
<p>In the meantime, please log into Editorial Manager at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="https://www.editorialmanager.com/pgenetics/" ns0:type="simple">https://www.editorialmanager.com/pgenetics/</ext-link>, click the "Update My Information" link at the top of the page, and update your user information to ensure an efficient production and billing process.&#160;Note that&#160;PLOS requires an ORCID iD for all corresponding authors. Therefore, please ensure that you have an ORCID iD and that it is validated in Editorial Manager. To do this, go to &#8216;Update my Information&#8217; (in the upper left-hand corner of the main menu), and click on the Fetch/Validate link next to the ORCID field.&#160; This will take you to the ORCID site and allow you to create a new iD or authenticate a pre-existing iD in Editorial Manager.</p>
<p>If you have a press-related query, or would like to know about one way to make your underlying data available (as you will be aware, this is required for publication), please see the end of this email. If your institution or institutions have a press office, please notify them about your upcoming article at this point, to enable them to help maximise its impact. Inform journal staff as soon as possible if you are preparing a press release for your article and need a publication date.</p>
<p>Thank you again for supporting open-access publishing; we are looking forward to publishing your work in PLOS Genetics!</p>
<p>Yours sincerely,</p>
<p>Xavier Didelot</p>
<p>Associate Editor</p>
<p>PLOS Genetics</p>
<p>Kirsten Bomblies</p>
<p>Section Editor: Evolution</p>
<p>PLOS Genetics</p>
<p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://www.plosgenetics.org" ns0:type="simple">www.plosgenetics.org</ext-link></p>
<p>Twitter: @PLOSGenetics</p>
<p>----------------------------------------------------</p>
<p><bold>Data Deposition</bold></p>
<p>If you have submitted a Research Article or Front Matter that has associated data that are not suitable for deposition in a subject-specific public repository (such as GenBank or ArrayExpress), one way to make that data available is to deposit it in the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://www.datadryad.org" ns0:type="simple">Dryad Digital Repository</ext-link>. As you may recall, we ask all authors to agree to make data available; this is one way to achieve that. A full list of recommended repositories can be found on our <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://journals.plos.org/plosgenetics/s/data-availability#loc-recommended-repositories" ns0:type="simple">website</ext-link>.</p>
<p>The following link will take you to the Dryad record for your article, so you won't have to re&#8208;enter its bibliographic information, and can upload your files directly:&#160;</p>
<p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://datadryad.org/submit?journalID=pgenetics&amp;manu=PGENETICS-D-19-00941R1" ns0:type="simple">http://datadryad.org/submit?journalID=pgenetics&amp;manu=PGENETICS-D-19-00941R1</ext-link></p>
<p>More information about depositing data in Dryad is available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://www.datadryad.org/depositing" ns0:type="simple">http://www.datadryad.org/depositing</ext-link>. If you experience any difficulties in submitting your data, please contact <email ns0:type="simple">help@datadryad.org</email> for support.</p>
<p>Additionally, please be aware that our <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" ns0:href="http://journals.plos.org/plosgenetics/s/data-availability" ns0:type="simple">data availability policy</ext-link> requires that all numerical data underlying display items are included with the submission, and you will need to provide this before we can formally accept your manuscript, if not already present.</p>
<p>----------------------------------------------------</p>
<p><bold>Press Queries</bold></p>
<p>If you or your institution will be preparing press materials for this manuscript, or if you need to know your paper's publication date for media purposes, please inform the journal staff as soon as possible so that your submission can be scheduled accordingly. Your manuscript will remain under a strict press embargo until the publication date and time. This means an early version of your manuscript will not be published ahead of your final version. PLOS Genetics may also choose to issue a press release for your article. If there's anything the journal should know or you'd like more information, please get in touch via <email ns0:type="simple">plosgenetics@plos.org</email>.</p>
</body>
</sub-article>
